<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/birmingh2-28160_1.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>Project No. 1485
March 2007.
LONGDALES ROAD, KINGS NORTON, BIRMINGHAM
2006 EXCAVATIONS
By Bob Burrows
With contributions by Jane Evans and Val Fryer
For further information please contact:
Birmingham Archaeology
The University of Birmingham
Edgbaston
Birmingham B15 2TT
Tel: 0121 414 5513
Fax: 0121 414 5516
E-Mail: bham-arch@bham.ac.uk
Web Address: http://www barch.bham.ac.uk/bufau
Longdales Road Archaeological Excavation 2006
LONGDALES ROAD, KINGS NORTON, BIRMINGHAM
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION 2006
POST-EXCAVATION ASSESSMENT
CONTENTS
1 INTRODUCTION ........................................................................................... 1
1.1 BACKGROUND TO THE PROJECT ........................................................................ 1
1.2 AIMS ...................................................................................................... 3
2 METHODOLOGY............................................................................................ 3
3 RESULTS ...................................................................................................... 4
3.1 PHASING ................................................................................................. 4
3.2 PHASE 1.................................................................................................. 4
Plot A........................................................................................................... 4
Plot B........................................................................................................... 5
Plot C........................................................................................................... 7
Plot D .......................................................................................................... 8
Dating evidence............................................................................................. 8
3.3 PHASE 2.................................................................................................. 9
Dating evidence........................................................................................... 10
4 ASSESSMENT ............................................................................................. 10
4.1 QUANTIFICATIONS..................................................................................... 10
4.2 SMALL FINDS........................................................................................... 11
4.3 POTTERY BY JANE EVANS ............................................................................. 11
Dating........................................................................................................ 13
Sources...................................................................................................... 14
Recommendations ....................................................................................... 14
4.4 CHARRED PLANT REMAINS BY VAL FRYER ........................................................... 14
Introduction and method statement ............................................................... 14
Results....................................................................................................... 14
Conclusions and recommendations for further work .......................................... 15
KEY TO TABLES .................................................................................................. 17
5 UPDATED PROJECT DESIGN ....................................................................... 17
5.1 GENERAL ............................................................................................... 17
Chronology ................................................................................................. 17
Site function and morphology: changes .......................................................... 18
Site economy and function............................................................................ 19
Site function and status................................................................................ 19
Roman, and post-Roman landscape archaeology .............................................. 20
5.2 LIST OF UPDATED AIMS ............................................................................... 20
6 PUBLICATION SYNOPSIS ........................................................................... 20
Text........................................................................................................... 21
Figures....................................................................................................... 21
8 TASK LIST ............................................................................................... 22
Birmingham Archaeology i
Longdales Road Archaeological Excavation 2006
7 ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS ............................................................................... 23
8 REFERENCES .............................................................................................. 23
Figures
1 Location of site within Birmingham
2 Longdales Road, areas excavated in 2002 (grey), 2003 (blue), 2004 (red) and
2006 (green)
3 Areas excavated in 2006, simplified plan
4 Ordnance Survey map of 1890, with areas excavated superimposed
Tables
1 Archive quantification
2 Finds quantification
3 Pottery, summary by context
4 Charred plant remains, assessment results
5 Charred plant remains, contexts assessed
Birmingham Archaeology ii
Longdales Road Archaeological Excavation 2006
SUMMARY
The third in a series of archaeological excavations was undertaken at Longdales Road,
Kings Norton, Birmingham (centred on NGR. SP 05337761), in August-September 2006.
This report describes the results of the most recent fieldwork and provides proposals to
being the results to publication. The fieldwork was undertaken by Birmingham
Archaeology on instruction from Birmingham City Council, and was undertaken in
advance of a cemetery development. The excavation followed an initial archaeological
evaluation in 2002 which identified remains of possible field boundaries and a pebble
surface adjoining Icknield Street. Earlier archaeological excavation elsewhere within the
cemetery development excavated a triple ditched enclosure, probably used for the
corralling of livestock. A second focus of activity was located by excavation in 2003-4,
also to the rear of the Icknield Street frontage, comprising ditched enclosure boundaries,
cobbled surfaces, pits and post-holes. The pottery dating indicates that the site was in
use from the 2nd to the early 4th century.
Two areas were excavated in 2006, one immediately adjoining the Icknield Street road
frontage. The earliest activity probably comprised the layout of ditched plot boundaries at
right-angles to the Roman road. The full width of three plots (A-C), and part of a fourth
plot (D) were recorded within the area investigated. The plot boundaries were further
defined by metalled roads adjoining the ditched boundaries. The excavated part of the
Plot A road frontage comprised a metalled surface, possibly used as a hardstanding for
storage, which was not continued along the frontage area of the other excavated plots to
the north. Plot B contained a rectangular ditched enclosure within which was sited part of
ring-gully. Plot C also contained a ring-gully, which may have been in use in late Phase
1-early Phase 2. Phase 2 activity was in general more limited. The main Phase 2 feature
was the northeastern angle of a ditched enclosure, cut through the two Phase 1 road
surfaces in Plot A. This enclosure was associated with an east-west aligned ditch. Further
to the north the only Phase 2 feature was a large pit. With the exception of the Phase 1
Plot B enclosure, activity was concentrated away from the road frontage, most notably in
Phase 2.
The pottery from Phase 1 contexts was dated mainly in the second half of the 2nd-3rd
century. This material included Severn Valley ware jars and bowls, a Malvernian tubby
cooking pot, and Black Burnished ware. Phase 2 activity was dated to the late 3rd-4th
century. It included Severn Valley jars and tankards, and mortaria from Oxfordshire and
Mancetter Hartshill.
Birmingham Archaeology iii
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
LONGDALES ROAD, KINGS NORTON, BIRMINGHAM
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION 2006
POST-EXCAVATION ASSESSMENT
1 INTRODUCTION
1.1 Background to the project
This report describes the results of a third archaeological excavation at Longdales Road,
Kings Norton, Birmingham, undertaken during August-September 2006 (centred on NGR.
SP 05337761; Area B, Fig. 1). Birmingham Archaeology was commissioned to undertake
the archaeological excavation by Birmingham City Council, which was undertaken in
accordance with the guidelines laid down in Planning Policy Guidance Note 16 (PPG16,
Department of the Environment, November 1990). The archaeological fieldwork was
undertaken in advance of proposals for a cemetery extension. This report provides a
post-excavation assessment of the results of the 2006 fieldwork, prepared in accordance
with the Management of Archaeology Projects 2 (MAP 2 - English Heritage). The fieldwork
was undertaken in accordance with a Design Brief prepared by the Council (Birmingham
CC 2006), and a Written Scheme of Investigation prepared by Birmingham Archaeology
(Birmingham Archaeology 2006), approved by the Planning Archaeologist, Birmingham
City Council, and following the requirements of the Council's Archaeology Strategy,
adopted as Supplementary Planning Guidance.
The site (Fig. 2) of the proposed cemetery is bounded by Longdales Road, Icknield Street
and Primrose Hill. The land is currently overgrown pasture, with the exception of those
areas presently laid out as a cemetery.
The proposed development site is bounded by Icknield Street to the east, which follows
the line of a Roman road. Just outside the site boundary is Lilycroft Farm, thought to be
of medieval origin and mentioned in a document of 13th century date. The farm is a
Grade II listed building, including fabric of late 17th and early 18th century date. Early
stages of work comprised a desk-based assessment, walkover survey, and trial-trenching
carried out by Worcestershire County Council Archaeological Service (Vaughan 2002) in
March 2002. The trial trenching involved machine-cut trenches in Fields 1-2 and 4, which
revealed ditches, shallow gullies and some pits/post holes. These features were
interpreted as a forming a Romano-British settlement focus, consisting of an enclosure
complex to the west of Lilycroft Farm, with an associated ditched field system to the
north.
Birmingham Archaeology 1
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
Preliminary fieldwork by Birmingham Archaeology in 2002 (Williams 2003a) included
further trial trenching in Field 1, close to Icknield Street, to determine the extent of
activity in this roadside zone, revealing ditches, pits and cobbled surfaces. Following
further trial trenching in Field 1, an excavation (Area A) was undertaken in the southwest
of the proposed cemetery site, to investigate a Romano-British enclosure complex which
was occupied from the 2nd to the 4th century AD. The sequence of Romano-British
activity was divided into three phases. The earliest activity (Phase 1) consisted of three
small ditches and a series of pits, largely concentrated in the south of the area
excavated. Phase 2 comprised the majority of the features, including the outermost two
enclosure ditches, as well as a ring gully and areas of stone surfacing. The latest
Romano-British activity was formed by an inner enclosure ditch and an internal,
rectangular stock enclosure, cut in Phase 3, possibly during a reduction in site activity.
The trial-trenching and Area A excavation results are described in a post-excavation
assessment (Williams 2003a), and the associated detailed specialist reports, site
narrative and illustrations have been prepared(Williams Evans and Burrows forthcoming).
The 2003 excavation (Area B), located to the west of the area investigated in 2006
revealed the remains of a Romano-British settlement dating from the 2nd-4th century
AD, represented by three phases of activity (Williams 2003b). The earliest phase of
activity (Phase 1) consisted of a single enclosure ditch or field boundary, with smaller
ditches and gullies dug outside the enclosed area. In Phase 2 two possible enclosure
ditches were cut in the north of the area investigated; a further ditch, gully and pit were
also contemporary. Also belonging to this phase were a number of structural remains,
including beam-slots, cobbled surfaces, a ring gully and four post pads, possibly
representing the remains of a large timber building with associated cobbled surfaces. One
of the cobbled surfaces was covered in an ashy deposit containing the charred remains of
spelt and glume, indicating the possibility of malting and beer production. The latest
Romano-British phase (Phase 3) was represented by two ditches and a large pit. Little
evidence of post-Romano-British activity (Phase 4) was recorded.
A watching brief was maintained in 2004 during groundworks associated with the
construction of the main cemetery roads, and associated drainage works (Mason 2004)
within Fields 1, 2 and 4. A number of ditched plot boundaries were identified, together
with post-holes and a ring-gully in the west of Field 1 (Mason 2004, fig. 3).
The purpose of the present report is to describe the results of the 2006 excavation
(Areas C-D), to assess the finds and environmental evidence from that excavation, and
Birmingham Archaeology 2
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
to provide proposals for an integrated publication of the 2002-3 and 2006 excavations in
a recognised archaeological journal.
1.2 Aims
The general aims of the 2006 excavation (Area C-D) were to identify archaeological
remains, and to preserve those remains by record. The specific aims were to reveal,
excavate and interpret any features associated with the occupation of the western
frontage of Icknield Street, and the area to the rear of the road frontage, where evidence
of plot or field boundaries may be anticipated.
2 METHODOLOGY
The 2006 fieldwork was undertaken in two stages. In Stage 1 two trenches, each
measuring 50m by 2m were excavated, positioned at an oblique angle to the main areas
for excavation, and between them. Stage 2 comprised the investigation of the two main
areas (C and D) selected for investigation, following completion of work in the two
trenches.
Within the excavated area the overburden was removed by a mechanical excavator
working under archaeological supervision to expose the uppermost horizon of the natural
subsoil. A base plan was prepared, from which the detailed strategy for sampling by
hand-excavation was devised. Within 60% of the excavated area sampling by hand-
excavation comprised half of each discrete feature, and 20-50% of linear features
associated with settlement. This sampling strategy was applied to the western of the two
areas investigated (Area D). Within the roadside area, where the feature density was less
intense, a single excavated slot was dug through each feature identified, and discrete
features were half-sectioned. As an exception, the eaves-drip gully was sampled by
means of several hand-dug segments. Further investigation of the eaves-drip gully has
been agreed, but is postponed due to bad weather.
Recording was by means of a continuously numbered sequence of cut and context
numbers. During the excavation, pre-printed pro-formas for contexts and cuts were
completed, together with digitally-surveyed plans (1:50) and hand-drawn sections (1:20
and 1:10). Monochrome and colour slide photographs were also taken.
Subject to permission from the landowner, it is proposed to deposit the finds and paper
archive with the Department of Human History, Birmingham Museums and Art Gallery.
Birmingham Archaeology 3
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
3 RESULTS
3.1 Phasing
The results from the 2006 excavation have been provisionally divided into two phases of
Romano-British activity, based on spot-dating of the pottery and the recorded
stratigraphy.
Phase 1 Early Romano-British activity, late 2nd-early 3rd century
Phase 2 Later Romano-British activity, later 3rd-4th century
The Romano-British archaeological features were all cut into the natural subsoil,
uncovered at a depth of between 0.3-0.45m below the modern ground surface. Those
excavated features which were merely changes in the natural geology, modern plough
furrows or field drains are not described below. Most of the features were attributed to
Phase 1. The Phase 1 features were cut into the natural red-brown clay subsoil
(6004/7002).
3.2 Phase 1
The main features excavated were a series of ditched plot boundaries cut on an east-
west alignment, at a right-angle to Icknield Street. Some of the plot boundaries were
further defined by metalled roads adjoining the ditched boundaries. Within the areas
excavated were examined an area close to the roadside frontage (Area C), and an area
to the rear of the frontage (Area D), close to the area investigated in 2003 (Area B).
<Node id="17157"/>Many, but not all of the east-west aligned ditched boundaries could be traced within
Areas C and D<Node id="17255"/>, in some cases because of differential preservation. The plots extended
over 100m to the rear of the Icknield Street frontage, assuming that the Roman road
was roughly contiguous with the modern road. Within Areas C and D were investigated
the full width of three plots (lettered A, B and C, from south to north), and part of a
fourth (D). Plot A measured approximately 28m in width (measured centre to centre of
the road surfaces). Plot B to the north measured 31m in width, and Plot C measured 22m
in width. Finally, Plot D was recorded for a maximum width of 14m, but its northern limit
was not recorded within the excavated area.
Plot A
The southern boundary of Plot A was formed by a pebble road surface, 6147, measuring
up to 4m in width. Towards the Roman road frontage the road joined an east-west
Birmingham Archaeology 4
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
aligned pebble surface, 6147A, recorded for a maximum width of 5.5m, and for a length
of 21m.
The only features recorded within Plot A were two adjoining pits, 6091 and 6095, each
measuring an average of 0.65m in diameter, located to the rear of the frontage, and
single post-hole, 7033, recorded closer to the Roman road frontage. The features were
backfilled with brown-grey silt-sand-clay.
The western continuation of road 6147 may have been located in Area B excavated in
2003 (F442, Williams 2003b, fig. 2), and during the watching brief in 2004 (F119, Mason
2004, fig. 2).
Plot B
The northern limit of Plot A and the southern boundary of Plot B were defined by an east-
west aligned metalled road, 6074, and a parallel ditch to the north, D1. The alignment of
the southern edge of this road varied between Areas C and D, possibly as a result of
resurfacing on a slightly different alignment. The road was better preserved in Area D,
being more truncated, perhaps as a result of ploughing, in the Roman roadside area. This
metalled surface was composed of pebbles measuring 0.02-0.10m in diameter with
occasional slightly larger sub-rounded stones. The road measured between 3.0 and 3.8m
in width and survived to a depth of between 0.04 and 0.09m in depth. A single post-hole,
7048, was cut into the road surface in Area C. In contrast to the road surface, the
associated ditch, D1, was better preserved towards the road frontage area, D1a. The
ditch segments cut in Areas C and D followed slightly different alignments; the alignment
recorded towards the road frontage, D1a, being tangential to ditch D1. Overall, the ditch
was cut to a U-shaped profile, and measured an average of 0.8m in depth, and between
0.16m and 0.26m in depth. It was backfilled with orange-brown sand-silt.
Within the excavated part of Plot B was recorded the eastern and western ends of a
rectangular enclosure, Enclosure E1, dug to the north of roadside ditch D1. Parts of the
northern, D6, the western, D5, and eastern, D4, sides of the enclosure were recorded
within the areas excavated. As so defined, the enclosure measured 22m (north-south),
by a maximum of 50m (east-west). The eastern side of the enclosure was misaligned
with the other sides of the enclosure, and with the Plot B boundaries.
The westernenclosure ditch, D5, was cut to the north of roadside ditch D1/D1a. <Node id="20496"/>No
relationship could be observed between the enclosure and roadside ditches<Node id="20572"/>, which may
have respected each other. D5 was cut to a U-shaped profile, and measured a maximum
Birmingham Archaeology 5
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
of 0.7m in width, and 0.32m in depth. The western edge of the ditch was cut by a post-
hole, 6113, which measured 0.3m in diameter. An entry-gap measuring 0.7m in width
was retained at the northwestern angle of the enclosure. The entry-gap was further
defined by a north-south aligned gully, 6136, cut flush with the western terminal of the
northern ditch of the enclosure, D6, and by a pit, 6134, cutting D5 towards its northern
terminal. The pit measured 0.98m in diameter. D6 was cut to a U-shaped profile, and
measured an average of 0.35m in depth, varying from 0.5m to 0.8m in width, at its
western and eastern terminals, respectively. The eastern ditch of the enclosure, D4
measured an average of 0.43m in depth, and between 0.8m and 0.52m in width, at its
northern and southern terminals, respectively. The southern terminal of D4 respected
D1a, the northern roadside ditch.
Within the Enclosure E1 interior, the main group of features were concentrated within its
southeastern angle, and comprised a circular ring-gully, R2, and associated features. The
earliest features of this group were two post-holes, 7062 and 7064, which were both cut
by ring-gully R2. The eastern half of the ring-gully was recorded within the excavated
area. R2 measured 8.2m in diameter. It measured 0.4-0.5m in width, and 0.15m in
depth, and was cut to a U-shaped profile. It was backfilled with charcoal-rich sand-silt-
clay, 7025. An oval, east-west aligned oval hearth, 7017, was recorded within R2. 7017
was backfilled with grey-brown silt-sand-clay, 7016, flecked with charcoal. A single post-
hole, 7060, was recorded within the interior of R2.
To the south of R1 was a line of small stones, 7074, which may represent the base of a
truncated gully, surviving to a depth of only 0.02m. This feature could possibly represent
the eastwards continuation of D1, although this could not be proven. Also to the east of
R2 was a pit, 7046, measuring 1.2m in diameter, and cut to a U-shaped profile.
Ditch D5 was backfilled with light grey-brown silt-clay. D6 and D4 were backfilled with
light grey silt-sand-clay.
Few features were located within Plot B outside the enclosure. A single post-hole, 7033,
was recorded immediately to the east of Enclosure E1. It measured 0.4m in diameter.
Further to the southeast was a further single post-hole, 7039. To the west of the
enclosure was a spread of stones, 6069/6103, curvilinear in plan, and recorded for a
length of 10m. This feature may represent the base of a heavily truncated ditch or gully.
This adjoined a single post-hole, 6115. Other possible features tested by hand-
excavation were proved to be of natural origin.
Birmingham Archaeology 6
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
The northern Plot A and southern Plot B ditched boundary may have been continued to
the west, into Area B (F419, Williams 2003b, fig. 2).
Plot C
The northern boundary of Plot B and the southern boundary of Plot C was formed by an
east-west aligned metalled surface, 6109, with a ditch to its northern edge, D2, similar to
the arrangement recorded on the Plot A/B boundary further to the south. Surface 6109
measured a maximum of 5m in width, and comprised small sub-rounded pebbles. Two
post-holes, 6011 and 6015, were cut into the surface. The post-holes averaged 0.6m in
diameter and 0.18m in depth. Ditch D2 was heavily truncated by a post-medieval field
boundary, 6123/7054, dug following the Roman alignment.
The main feature identified within the interior of Plot C was a ring-gully, R1, possibly oval
in plan. The southeastern half of the feature was recorded; the remainder, perhaps
originally less substantial in depth, having been removed by truncation. R1 measured
10.3m in diameter. An entry-gap, measuring 0.6m in width was recorded in the
southeastern angle of the feature. The ring-gully was cut to a U-shaped profile. It
measured a maximum of 0.6m in width and 0.18m in depth (in the southeast), to 0.26m
in width and 0.05m in depth along its southwestern side. R1 was backfilled with grey-
brown silt-sand-clay.
A number of features were recorded within the interior of R1. Three post-holes, 6071,
6076 and 6078, in the southwest of the ring-gully could have been associated with an
entrance structure not otherwise surviving. An adjoining pit, 6119, was also recorded.
Traces of stone-packing survived within 6071, which was cut to a U-shaped profile, and
measured 0.38m in diameter, and 0.18m in depth. Two further post-holes, 6080 and
6082, and a small pit, 6087, were recorded towards the centre of the ring-gully. The
post-holes measured an average of 0.35m in diameter, and 0.18m in depth. The central
group of features could have represented central supports to the structure.
R1 and the associated features could have been in use in late Phase 1, or early Phase 2,
as suggested by the pottery dating evidence.
The only other feature within Plot C was a large, flat-based pit, 6017, recorded to the
southwest of R1. In plan, it measured 6.4m by 5.8m, and was cut to a maximum depth
of 0.26m. It was backfilled with redeposited subsoil and light grey silt-clay, 6016. The
sequence of backfills suggests gradual backfilling of the feature, which is interpreted as
Birmingham Archaeology 7
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
an animal watering hole. The feature was surrounded by a possible pebble surface (not
illustrated). <Node id="26126"/>No features were recorded in this plot closer to the Roman road<Node id="26189"/>.
The northern Plot B/ southern Plot C boundary may have been continued to the west,
into Area B (F410, Williams 2003b, fig. 2).
Plot D
The northern limit of Plot C, and the southern side of Plot D was defined by an east-west
aligned ditch, D3, and a metalled road, 6146, recorded immediately to the north. D3 was
cut to a U-shaped profile, and measured 0.5-0.65m in width, and 0.1-0.23m in depth. In
Area D the ditch became notably less substantial in the east of the excavated area, which
might suggest its possible eastward continuation into Area C, adjoining the roadside
area, could have been entirely scoured-out by truncation. D3 was backfilled with brown
sand-clay. In contrast to the other ditched plot boundaries, ditch D3 was slightly
curvilinear in plan. <Node id="26956"/>This irregularity might suggest that it was not part of the original
Roman layout<Node id="27037"/>. This hypothesis is supported by the narrow width of Plot C (22m),
compared with a width of approximately 30m for Plots A and B, although admittedly it is
not possible to draw firm conclusions from the limited sample of the roadside area
provided by the 2006 excavation. <Node id="27309"/>The small excavated sample of the Plot D interior
contained no identifiable Roman features<Node id="27399"/>. The absence of features within the interior of
this plot is not surprising given that more of the plot's interior was tested towards the
Roman road frontage, which contained few features in Plots A-C to the south.
The southern Plot C/ northern Plot D boundary may have been continued to the west,
into Area B (F408, Williams 2003b, fig. 2). A further ditched boundary (F405), cut on the
same alignment in Area B was not recorded as continuing into Area C. A stone surface
(F421) was found in Area B to the south of plot boundary ditch F410. This stone surface
could be equivalent to surface 6109 found in Area C.
Dating evidence
Enclosure E1 contained pottery dating to the 2nd-3rd century, AD 120+, late 2nd century
+, and to the 2nd-3rd century from ditch D5, and to the 2nd-3rd century from ditch D4.
Ditches D1 and D2 contained Roman pottery. Ditch D3 contained pottery dating AD
120+, to the mid 2nd-early 3rd century, and to the 2nd-3rd century, as well as material
classed only as Roman. Road surface 6074 contained pottery dating to the 2nd-4th
century. Pit 6017 in Plot C contained 2nd century pottery.
Birmingham Archaeology 8
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
3.3 Phase 2
The metalled roads, 6147 and 6074, defining the southern and northern limits of Phase 1
Plot A had gone out of use by the end of Phase 1. <Node id="28735"/>It is not clear if the other parallel roads
and plot boundaries had gone out of use at the same time<Node id="28835"/>.
The main Phase 2 feature was the northeastern angle of a ditched enclosure, Enclosure
E2. Only part of the eastern side, and a very short length of the northern side of this
enclosure were recorded at excavation; its other sides lay outside the excavated area.
The eastern ditch of the enclosure, D7, was cut through Phase 1 roads 6147 and 6074,
and the northern ditch, D8, was also cut into surface 6074. The eastern ditch, D7, was
cut to a U-shaped profile, and measured between 0.8-1m in width, and 0.36m-0.5m in
depth. It was backfilled with grey silt-sand-clay. The short excavated length of the
northern ditch, D8, was cut to a similar profile, and measured a maximum of 1.58m in
width and 0.5m in depth. It was backfilled with mid grey-brown silt-sand-clay, 6072.
An east-west aligned ditch, D9, cut to the north of Enclosure E2 may have been
associated. D9 was cut for a distance of 20m. Ditch D9 was cut through the backfilled
Phase 1 ditch D5 (Enclosure E1) and into the subsoil, 6004. Ditch D9 was cut to a U-
shaped profile, and measured a maximum of 0.63m in width, and 0.15m in depth. It was
backfilled with grey-brown silt-sand-clay. This ditch may possibly represent a re-
definition of the Phase 1 northern Plot A, and southern Plot B boundary ditch D1. A gap
measuring 4m was retained between ditch D9 and the northern side of Enclosure E2, D8.
This gap could suggest that part of the width of Phase 1 road 6074 could have continued
in use during Phase 2, a suggestion which may be supported by the recovery of pottery
dating to the 2nd-4th centuries from its surface.
Further to the north was a pit, 6062, sub-circular in plan, measuring a maximum of 2.5m
in width, and 0.5m in depth. It was backfilled with charcoal-flecked silt-clay. In the
extreme northeastern angle of Area C was an irregular pebble spread, 7076, which
sealed the backfilled Phase 1 plot boundary, D3.
As noted above, R1 in Phase 1 Plot C could also have continued in use into Phase 2.
The northeastern side of Phase 2 Enclosure E2, D8, was approximately flush with the
northern terminals of ditches F416 and F417 (Williams 2003b, fig. 2), which might
suggest that they represented the northern end of the western side of this enclosure.
Assuming that this interpretation was correct, an entry-gap would have been retained at
Birmingham Archaeology 9
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
the northwestern angle of the enclosure, since no trace of the western end of its northern
side was recorded within Area B. The maintenance of an entry-gap at the corner of an
enclosure is an arrangement often associated with the sorting of livestock.
Dating evidence
Ditch D7 contained pottery dating AD 240+ and residual material dating AD 120+; of 2nd
to 3rd century date, and of 3rd to 4th century date, and residual material of late 2nd to
3rd century date from the same cut. Ditch D8 contained pottery of late 3rd to 4th
century date. Ring-gully R1 contained pottery dating AD 240+, and associated feature
6082 contained pottery dating to the 3rd-4th century which may suggest the features
continued in use into Phase 2. Finally, pit 6062 contained pottery dating to the 3rd-4th
century.
4 ASSESSMENT
4.1 Quantifications
TABLE 1: Archive quantification (excludes 2002 evaluation)
Record Number
Contexts/ features 280
Assemblage summaries 1 file
Colour slide 3 films
Colour print 2 films
Black and white prints 3 films
Drawings 80
Env sample record files 1
Survey file 1
Birmingham Archaeology 10
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
TABLE 2: Finds quantification (excludes 2002 evaluation)
Material type Quantity
Fired clay/daub 8
Romano-British coarse
pottery
430
Samian 4
Mortaria 1
Post-medieval pottery 9
Post-medieval iron
objects
5
Slag 13
Post-medieval coin 1
4.2 Small finds
<Node id="32624"/>None of the recovered finds, with the exception of the pottery, was worthy of assessment
or detailed study<Node id="32730"/>.
4.3 Pottery by Jane Evans
The 2006 fieldwork at Longdales Road produced 435 sherds of Romano-British pottery,
weighing 3.3kg. Sherds were heavily abraded, due to the acidic soils. Most context
groups were very fragmentary, though some contexts produced more substantial
fragments (for example a near complete profile of a tankard from 6062, f 6065). The
assemblage came from 48 stratified contexts, only 13 sherds being unstratified. The
assemblage is summarised and spot dated in Table 3 below.
Birmingham Archaeology 11
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
TABLE 3: Pottery, summary by context
Context/cut/
construct Qty. % Qty. Wt (g) % Wt. Spot date
6000 layer 2 0.5% 4 0.1% C2nd-C4th
6006/ 6007/ D5 6 1.4% 20 0.6% C2nd-C3rd
6006/ 6007/ D5 4 0.9% 43 1.3% c 120+
6008/ 6009/ D3 24 5.5% 127 3.9% c 120+
6010/ 6011 3 0.7% 2 0.1% Roman
6012/ layer 2 0.5% 30 0.9% Roman
6014/ 6015 9 2.1% 11 0.3% Roman
6016/ 6017 27 6.2% 181 5.5% C2nd
6024/ 6025/ D3 24 5.5% 165 5.0% Mid C2nd­Early C3rd
6028/ 6029/ R1 48 11.0% 320 9.8% c 240+?
6030/ 6031/ R1 1 0.2% 19 0.6% Roman
6032/ 6033/ R1 2 0.5% 3 0.1% c 120+
6036/ 6037/ D3 1 0.2% 22 0.7% Roman
6046/ 6047/ D7 20 4.6% 117 3.6% c 120+
6048/ 6049/ D3 9 2.1% 33 1.0% C2nd-C3rd
6050/ 6047/ D7 6 1.4% 50 1.5% c 240+
6051/ 6052/ D7 4 0.9% 41 1.2% C2nd-C3rd
6064/ 6068 4 0.9% 24 0.7% Roman
6065/ 6062 8 1.8% 175 5.3% C3rd-C4th
6072/ 6073/ D8 3 0.7% 92 2.8% Late C3rd-C4th
6074 layer 40 9.2% 148 4.5% C2nd-C4th
6081/ 6082/ R1 2 0.5% 26 0.8% C3rd-C4th
6083/ 6085/ D7 33 7.6% 485 14.8% C3rd-C4th
6084/ 6085/ D7 8 1.8% 136 4.1% Late C2nd-C3rd
6086/ 6087/ R1 1 0.2% 4 0.1% Roman
6096/ 6097/ D5 2 0.5% 92 2.8% Late C2nd+
6100/ 6101/ D5 1 0.2% 14 0.4% Roman
6104/ 6105/ D5 1 0.2% 19 0.6% C2nd-C3rd
6108/ 6109 2 0.5% 3 0.1% Roman
6125/ 6126/ D10 2 0.5% 4 0.1% Roman
6129/ 6130 1 0.2% 50 1.5% Roman
7001 layer 7 1.6% 26 0.8% Roman
7003/ 7005/ D1a 15 3.4% 46 1.4% Roman
7012/ 7013 2 0.5% 4 0.1% Roman
7014/ 7015/ R2 10 2.3% 48 1.5% c 120+
7016/ 7017/ R2 8 1.8% 149 4.5% Roman
7018/ 7019/ R2 4 0.9% 21 0.6% Roman
7020/ 7019/ R2 11 2.5% 62 1.9% Roman
7021/ 7022/ D4 5 1.1% 35 1.1% C2nd-C3rd
7023/ 7024/ D4 14 3.2% 100 3.0% Roman
7025/ 7026/ R2 2 0.5% 1 0.0% Roman
7030/ 7031/ R2 5 1.1% 118 3.6% Roman
7041/ 7042/ D1a 2 0.5% 1 0.0% Roman
7045/ 7046 14 3.2% 6 0.2% Roman
U/S 7 1.6% 59 1.8% Late C2nd-C3rd
U/S 1 0.2% 3 0.1% Roman
U/S 2 0.5% 1 0.0% c 120+
U/S 11 2.5% 43 1.3% c 120+
U/S 15 3.4% 99 3.0% Roman
Total 435 100.0% 3282 100.0%
Birmingham Archaeology 12
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
Dating
The spot dating of the assemblage is not precise, relying heavily on Severn Valley ware
forms with broad, overlapping date ranges. However, two broad phases of activity were
apparent.
Evidence for 2nd century activity (Phase 1) is provided by a Malvernian tubby cooking
pot (cf Peacock 1967, fig. 1.1, 2). A number of Severn Valley ware forms date broadly to
the 2nd to 3rd centuries: Webster type A6 and C22 jars (Webster 1976, fig.1, fig. 4
respectively) from D5/6105, f 6104; D4/7022, f 7021; 6017, f 6016. Some Severn
Valley ware bowls (from layer 6074; 6085, f 6084) dated more specifically to the late
2nd to 3rd centuries (Webster 1976 type F50, fig. 8). A Black Burnished ware, grooved
rim bowl or dish (layer 6024) also indicates activity some time around the mid 2nd to
early 3rd century (Seager Smith and Davies 1993, fig. 123, type 24). It is possible that
these latter forms provide a more reliable indication of the earliest activity on the site. A
few sherds of samian were also recovered, all very abraded. These have not been
identified and need to be examined by a specialist. It is possible, based on the evidence
from previous excavations at Longdales Road (Willis 2003) that these date to the
Antonine period. A fluorit of activity during the second half of the 2nd century would be
consistent with the evidence from the 2003 excavations (Evans 2005).
A variety of forms dated to the late 3rd or 4th century (Phase 2). The Severn Valley ware
included a Webster type C27 jar (Webster 1976, fig. 5) and a splayed tankard (Webster
1976 fig. 7, type E43 or E44), from D8/6073, f 6072 and 6062, f 6065, respectively.
Black burnished ware flange rimmed bowls (Seagar Smith and Davies 1993, fig. 124,
type 124) from R1/6082, f 6081; and D7/6085, f 6083 also provided good evidence
for this period of activity, as did Oxfordshire mortaria (Young 2000, fig. 21 M18 and fig.
22 M20) from R1/6029, f 6028 and D7/6047, f 6050. A rim from a Mancetter
Hartshill, multi-reeded hammerhead mortarium could be contemporary (context 6096).
Late 3rd to 4th century activity is also attested at the previously excavated Longdales
Road sites (Hancocks 2003; Evans 2005).
Some contexts were given a tpq of c AD 120, based on the presence of body sherds in
Black Burnished ware. It is likely that these in fact date to at least the mid-to-late 2nd
century, based on the BB1 forms identified. <Node id="37666"/>Other contexts provided no diagnostic fabrics
and forms and could only be broadly dated to the Roman period<Node id="37773"/>.
Birmingham Archaeology 13
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
Sources
The range of sources is similar to that noted in previous excavations at Longdales Road.
The assemblage is dominated by Severn Valley ware, representing more than 70% by
sherd count. Other sources included Dorset Black Burnished ware and Malvernian ware,
and mortaria from Mancetter Hartsh and the Oxfordshire kilns. Only 4 sherds of samian
were recovered, fragmentary body sherds and a base, all badly abraded. <Node id="38268"/>No amphorae
was present<Node id="38291"/>.
Recommendations
The assemblage complements the evidence from previous excavations at Longdales Road
(Hancocks 2003; Evans 2005) and needs to be fully recorded for publication. It is
estimated that c 25 sherds w require illustration. The material from the 2002 evaluation
w be integrated with the material from the 2006 excavation.
4.4 Charred plant remains by Val Fryer
Introduction and method statement
Samples for the retrieval of the plant macrofossil assemblages were taken from across
the excavated areas, and twenty two were submitted for assessment.
The samples were bulk floated by Birmingham Archaeology and the flots were collected
in a 500 micron mesh sieve. The dried flots were scanned under a binocular microscope
at magnifications up to x 16 and the plant macrofossils and other remains noted are
listed on Tables 4 and 5. Nomenclature within the tables follows Stace (1997). All plant
remains were charred. Modern contaminants including fibrous roots, seeds, fungal
sclerotia and arthropods were present throughout.
Results
With the exception of charcoal fragments, plant macrofossils were exceedingly scarce.
Single grains of barley (Hordeum sp.) and wheat (Triticum sp.) were recorded along with
a spelt wheat (T. spelta) glume base and individual seeds of persicaria (Persicaria
maculosa/lapathifolia) and dock (Rumex sp.). Preservation was quite poor, with most
remains being puffed and distorted (possibly as a result of combustion at very high
Birmingham Archaeology 14
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
temperatures) and very fragmented. As noted above, charcoal/charred wood fragments,
including some very large pieces, were present at varying densities throughout although
again, preservation was poor, with much of the material being heavily abraded. Other
plant macrofossils were all but absent, although minute pieces of charred root/stem were
recorded within three assemblages.
Other material types were also very scarce, and it is considered most likely that of those
recorded, most were intrusive within the contexts. Many of the porous and tarry residues
had the appearance of modern `coke' and small coal fragments were also recorded.
Conclusions and recommendations for further work
Without exception, the assemblages are all extremely small (most being considerably
 0.1 litres in volume) and most contain little other than charcoal/charred wood
fragments. <Node id="40698"/>There is no evidence for the primary deposition of material within any of the
features recorded<Node id="40793"/>, and it would appear most likely that the assemblages are largely
derived from scattered or wind-blown hearth waste, which accidentally became
incorporated within the feature fills. It is not clear whether this may imply that the site
was little used and peripheral to any main centre of activity or whether it was kept clear
of most refuse. The poor condition of the material may indicate that it was either
exposed for a considerable period prior to burial, or it has become abraded as result of
the subsequent disturbance of the deposits (as possibly suggested by the modern
contaminants).
As none of the assemblages are quantifiably viable (i.e. containing 100 specimens), no
further analysis is recommended.
Birmingham Archaeology 15
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
TABLE 4: Charred plant remains, assessment results
Sample No. 8 16 27 31 32 33 35
Context No. 7003 6063 6104 7018 7016 7023 7030
Feature No. 7005 6062 6105 7019 7017 7024 7031
Feature type Ditch D1a Pit Ditch D5 Ring gully
R2
Ring gully
R2
Ditch D4 Ring gully
R2
Plant macrofossils
Hordeum sp. (grains) x xcf
Triticum sp. (grains) xcf x
T. spelta L. (glume base) x
Cereal indet. (grains) x x
Persicaria maculosa/lapathifolia x
Rumex sp. x
Charcoal 2mm xxxx xxxx x xxxx xxx x xx
Charcoal 2mm xx xx x xxx xx x xx
Charcoal 5mm x x
Charred root/stem x x
Indet.seeds x x
Other materials
Black porous 'cokey' material x
Black tarry material x
Small coal frags. x x x
Vitrified material x
Sample volume (litres)
Volume of flot (litres) 0.1 0.1 0.1 0.1 0.1 0.1 0.1
% flot sorted 100% 100% 100% 100% 100% 100% 100%
Birmingham Archaeology 16
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
TABLE 5: Charred plant remains, contexts assessed
Sample no. Context Cut Feature type/construct Contents
4 6028 6029 Ring gully R1 CH;BTM;COAL
10 6016 6015 Ring gully R1 CH;CR/ST;BTM;COAL
20 6072 6073 Ditch D8 CH;BPC;BTM
23 6079 6080 Post hole CH;BPC;COAL
25 6086 6087 Pit CH
26 6100 6101 Ditch D5 CH
28 6096 6097 Ditch D5 CH
29 6112 6113 Post hole CH;BPC
30 6118 6119 Pit CH;BPC;COAL
34 7025 7026 Ring gully R2 CH
36 7021 7022 Ditch D4 CH
38 6129 6130 Road CH
40 6131 6132 Ditch D6 CH
41 6135 6136 Gully CH
42 6133 6134 Pit CH
Key to Tables
x = 1 ­ 10 specimens xx = 10 ­ 50 specimens xxx = 50 ­ 100 specimens xxxx = 100+ specimens
cf = compare CH = charcoal BTM = black tarry material CR/ST = charred root/stem
BPC = black porous `cokey' material
5 UPDATED PROJECT DESIGN
5.1 General
This section of the assessment defines the main research themes. Most of the research
themes identified in the previous assessments (Williams 2003a and 2003b) remain
relevant.
Chronology
For the purposes of assessment, the Roman features have been divided into two phases.
Phase 1 represents the first definition of the plot boundaries, also associated with
Enclosure E1 in Plot B. This phase is dated to the later 2nd-early 3rd century. Ring-gully
R1 in Plot C may also be attributed to this phase, although its later re-cutting and re-use
is suggested by the recovery of 3rd-4th century pottery from the fill. Phase 2 activity is
dated to the later 3rd-4th century. Only limited activity is recorded in this phase,
Birmingham Archaeology 17
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
comprising the cutting of a ditched enclosure (Enclosure E2) across Phase 1 Plot A, the
excavation of a pit, 6062, and the layout of a stone surface, 7076, close to the Roman
road frontage. The evidence from Areas C and D suggests that the floruit of this Roman
activity was during the later 2nd-early 3rd century. In contrast, activity in the adjoining
Area B (Williams 2003b) was more intense during the later 3rd-4th century. Further
analysis of the pottery from Areas C and D, and comparison with the material from Area
B, and the features found in that area w further refine the sequence and dating, as well
as facilitating comparison with the Area A evidence. It has been suggested above that
the different width of Plot C, and the slightly curvilinear plot boundary, D3, could suggest
that this plot was not part of the original layout, although this cannot be proven.
Area B ring-gully F411 (Williams 2003b) was cut by plot boundary F410, which may have
defined part of the Plot B/C boundary, suggesting that activity away from the road
frontage pre-dated the formal layout of plot boundaries which extended up to the Roman
road frontage.
Site function and morphology: changes
The earliest Roman activity within Areas C and D was the layout of plot boundaries,
defined by ditches, metalled roads or both. The limited dating evidence suggests that this
layout dates to the later 2nd century. With the exception of Plot B, few internal features
could be identified. Plot B contained a rectangular enclosure, Enclosure E1, one side
adjoining the southern ditched boundary of the plot. The enclosure contained a ring-gully
and a number of associated features, mainly post-holes. An entry-gap was recorded in
the northwestern angle of the enclosure, which suggests use of the enclosure for
livestock. A broad, flat-based pit, 6017 located in Plot C may be interpreted as an animal
drinking trough. Although not exactly the same in width, the similarity in the width of the
excavated plots A and B could suggest that they were laid out as one operation. An
intriguing possibility is that plot boundaries were laid out along the eastern and western
frontages of the Roman road at the same time. Ordnance survey mapping (Fig. 4)
indicates that the Plot A/B and C/D boundaries were approximately flush with existing
field boundaries recorded on the eastern frontage of Icknield Street. The southern
boundary of Field 1 is also likely to have been cut on the line of a Roman plot boundary;
the distance between the field boundary and the southern Plot A boundary was similar to
the average plot boundary width recorded. Moreover, Field 4 to the south is
approximately three such plot boundaries in width. Remaining on the western side of the
Roman road, there are three field boundaries which run at a right-angle to it recorded to
the north of Longdales Road (Fig. 4). Fieldwork by Worcestershire CC has identified a
Birmingham Archaeology 18
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
pebble surface to the east of Lilycroft Farm, and a continuation of Roman activity to the
south of Primrose Hill.
Phase 2 activity in Areas C and D was more limited in extent than that of the preceding
phase. <Node id="47233"/>With the exception of metalled surface 7076 no Phase 2 activity was recorded
close to the road frontage<Node id="47336"/>. This metalled surface clearly implies that the Plot C/D
boundary had gone out of use in this phase. Phase 2 Enclosure E2 could have been
associated with livestock, particularly if it was associated with the possible northwestern
side of the enclosure containing an entry-gap, as recorded in Area B (F416, F417,
Williams 2003b).
Site economy and function
Investigation of the Area C and D roadside areas is complimentary to the previous areas
investigated (Areas A and B). In each case an association with animal husbandry may be
suggested. Investigation of Areas C and D confirms that <Node id="47923"/>the site was not a `typical'
roadside settlement<Node id="47971"/>, in which case a concentration of features would be anticipated
immediately adjoining the Roman road. The results of the 2006 excavations suggest that
the occupation of the frontage area was not domestic in nature, with the sole exception
of ring-gully R2. Most significantly, the plot boundaries were recorded for a distance of at
least 90m to the rear of the Icknield Street frontage. Such a plot depth is unlikely to be
associated with domestic occupation, since roadside plots are typically no more than
approximately 30m in depth.
Comparison of the pottery w help to elucidate site status and trading patterns, as well
as any intra-site variations.
Site function and status
Excavation in 2006 has demonstrated that the roadside area was not the main focus of
activity. Rather, settlement was concentrated to the rear of the frontage, and the road
frontage area was also given up in the later 3rd century. The morphology of the Area A
enclosure complex (Williams 2003a) suggests an association with livestock. <Node id="48986"/>Evidence
from excavations in 2002, 2003, 2004 and 2006 suggests that the settlement remains
were not confined to a single farm<Node id="49112"/>. It is possible that the remains could have formed part
of a small hamlet (Hingley 1989, 76) where multiple `compounds' would be anticipated.
The economy of the site may have been dependant on livestock, rather than the
opportunities provided to sell goods or produce to travellers. One possibility is that the
site was a local market centre (Hingley 1989, 112), perhaps with a particular emphasis
Birmingham Archaeology 19
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
on the sale of livestock. The position of the Longdales Road settlement within the local
hierarchy of settlement should be explored in detail.
Roman, and post-Roman landscape archaeology
The identification of different settlement foci (Area A, Area B, and Area C/D roadside
activity) provides some opportunities for landscape reconstruction, and also for
comparison with other extensively-investigated Roman roadside settlements (e.g. M6
Toll, A5 Weeford-Fazeley, A1(M) Ermine Street, Cambridgeshire, A419/A417,
Wiltshire/Gloucestershire, among others). Evidence for the post-Roman landscape should
also be considered.
5.2 List of updated aims
1) To define the chronology of the enclosures and other Romano-British features.
2) To provide an understanding of the changes in site morphology and function.
3) To attempt to define the site economy and function, including a review of the
comparative evidence.
4) To relate the site to the hierarchy of later Roman rural settlements in the midlands
and in the surrounding region.
5) To attempt to reconstruct the Roman roadside landscape, and to provide comparison
with other Roman roadside excavations focusing on the corralling of livestock.
6 PUBLICATION SYNOPSIS
The results w be fully integrated with the results from the previous excavation and
published as a monograph in a recognised archaeological journal (eg BAR).
It is intended to publish the results of work in Areas A-D as sequential sections within a
single overall report, within the following overall arrangement
Chapter 1 Summary and introduction (Areas A-D and watching brief
Chapter 2 Area A
Description and interpretation of results
Finds
Discussion
Chapter 3 Area B
Description and interpretation of results
Birmingham Archaeology 20
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
Finds and environmental evidence
Discussion
Chapter 4 Areas C-D
Description and interpretation of evidence
Finds and environmental evidence
Discussion
Chapter 4 Summary of watching brief
Chapter 5 Synthesis and overview
The suggested layout of the Area C-D section of the overall report is as follows:
Text
Summary (250w)
Introduction, aims and methodology, archaeological setting (with Areas A-B, 1000w, 2
figures)
Description and interpretation of results (4,000w, 1 table, 5 figures, 5 plates)
Finds and environmental evidence
Roman pottery (3,000w, 2 tables, 1 figure)
Charred plant remains (1,000w, 1 table)
Discussion (3,000w)
Contribution to general discussion and synthesis (1,000w)
Total 13,250 w, 4 tables, 5 plates, 8 figures
Figures
1 Site location
2 Site location, topography and alignment of Roman road
3 Areas investigated (A-D)
4 Simplified plan, Phase 1-2 features
5 Detailed plans of ring-gullies
6 Phase 1 plan
7 Phase 1 sections
8 Phase 2 plan
9 Phase 2 sections
10 Pottery
Birmingham Archaeology 21
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
(Overall site plans w include details of features found by Worcestershire CC fieldwork)
8 TASK LIST
STAGE A, PRELIMINARY ANALYSIS. Performance indicator, completion 30/3/2007.
1 Project management AJ 1
2 Site archive/update phasing/plans BB 4
3 Data entry BB 3
4 Prepare detailed site plans/sections: roughs BB 2
STAGE B, REPORTING AND ILLUSTRATION. Performance indicator, completion
29/6/2007.
5 Project management AEJ 1
6 Roman pottery recording JE 3
7 Update database/finds management EM 1
8 Samian/ mortarium recording FW/KH 1/1
9 Prepare plans and sections ND 2
10 Prepare pottery illustrations ND 1
11 Library research AEJ 1
12 Roman coarse pottery reporting/discussion JE 3
13 Update stratigraphic text AEJ 1
14 Draft discussion AEJ 1
15 Corrections to illustrations ND 1
STAGE C, INTEGRATE WITH AREA A/B RESULTS AND COMPLETION OF FIRST DRAFT.
Performance indicator, completion 31/8/2007
16 Project management AEJ 1
17 Integrate and edit Area C/D and A/B texts together AEJ 1
18 Draft final discussion and synthesis AEJ 2
19 Corrections to drawings ND 0.5
20 Prepare archive BB 2
21 Liaison with referees/final corrections AEJ 1
22 Deposit archive - 1
Birmingham Archaeology 22
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
KEY: AEJ=A. Jones, Project Manager/editor; EM, E. Macey, Finds Supervisor; ND = Nigel
Dodds, Illustrator; JE=Roman coarse pottery; FW=Felicity Wild, samian; KH=Kay
Hartley, moratium.
7 ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
The excavation was commissioned by Birmingham City Council. Thanks are due to Dr
Mike Hodder for monitoring the project and giving on-site guidance. The project was
supervised by Bob Burrows, assisted by Ros Mckenna, Shaun Daly, Emily Hamiltonj, Liz
Bishop and Jenny White. The specialists are thanked for their contributions. The
illustrations were prepared by Nigel Dodds and the text was edited by Alex Jones, who
managed the project for Birmingham Archaeology.
8 REFERENCES
Birmingham Archaeology 2006 Written Scheme of Investigation, Archaeological
Excavation, Longdales Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham.
Birmingham City Council 2006 Project Design, Archaeological Excavation, Longdales
Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham.
Evans, C J, 2005 Longdales Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham, Area B draft pottery report.
Hancocks, A, 2003 Longdales Road, King's Norton Pottery report, in Williams 2003a, 11-
13.
Hingley, R, 1989 Rural Settlement in Roman Britain.
Mason, P, 2004 Longdales Road, Birmingham, Archaeological Watching Brief 2004. BA
report 1167.
Seager Smith, R, and Davies, S M, 1993 Black Burnished Ware Type Series. The Roman
Pottery from Excavations at Greyhound Yard, Dorchester, Dorset. Wessex Archaeology.
(Offprinted from P J Woodward, S M Davies, and A H Graham, `Excavations at the Old
Birmingham Archaeology 23
Longdales Road: Archaeological Evaluation 2005
Methodist Chapel and Greyhound Yard, Dorchester 1981-1984,' Dorset Natur. Hist.
Archaeol. Soc. Monogr. Ser. 12)
Stace, C, 1997 New Flora of the British Isles. Second edition. Cambridge University
Press.
Vaughan, T, 2002 Archaeological Evaluation at Proposed New Cemetery Site, Longdales
Road, Birmingham, WCC Report 960.
Webster, P V, 1976, Severn Valley Ware: A Preliminary Study. Trans. Bristol
Gloucestershire Archaeol. Soc. 94, 18-46
Willis, S, 2003 Dated Catalogue of the Samian Pottery, Area A, in Williams, Evans and
Burrows forthcoming.
Williams, J, 2003a Longdales Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham. Archaeological
Investigations 2002. Post-Excavation Assessment. BUFAU Report No. 958.
Williams, J, 2003b Longdales Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham. Archaeological
Investigations 2003. Post-Excavation Assessment. BA Report No. 958.01.
Williams, J, Evans, C J, and Burrows, B, forthcoming Excavations 2002-2006 at
Longdales Road, Kings Norton, Birmingham, British Archaeological Reports, British series.
Young, C J, 2000 The Roman Pottery Industry of the Oxford Region, BAR, Brit. Ser.
Birmingham Archaeology 24
Reproduced from the 1998 Ordnance
Survey 1:50,000 map with the
permission of the Controller of Her
Majesty's Stationary Office,
c Crown Copyright
Licensee : Field Archaeology Unit
University of Birmingham
Edgbaston
BIRMINGHAM
B15 2TT
Licence No. AL 51303A
c
SITE
Fig.1
Fig.2
P
r i m
r o
s
e
H
i l l
L
o
n
g
d
a
l e
s
R
o a d
IcknieldStreet
0 50m
Field 4
Field 3
Field 2
Field 1
Lilycroft
Farm
Tr.2
Tr.3
Tr.5
Tr.1W
Tr.2W
Tr.4
Tr.6 Tr.7
Tr.8
Tr.10
Tr.11
Tr.9
Tr.1
Tr.3W
Area B
Area A
Area D
Area C
A
B
C
D
T
0 20m
6017
Road/Hardstanding
Phase 1
Phase 2
Longdales
Road
7064
7046
7074
7060
Field 1
Plot D Plot C Plot B Plot A
AREA C
AREA D
R1
D3 D2
D6
D9
D7
D8
D1
D4
D6
D2
R2
D5
7076
6146
6109
6074
6074
6147A
6147
6136
6134
6115
6091
6095
6119
6069
6103
6078
6076
6071 6076
6080
6082
6087
7017
6062
6109
6123
Enclosure E2
Enclosure E1
Fig.3
6105
6011
6123
6113
6004
7033
70487062
D1a
7002
7054
7039
7033
Fig.4
1890
Pebble
Surface
Field Boundaries Aligned
to Roman Road
<Node id="57336"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="20496" EndNode="20572">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="3" Type="Negation" StartNode="26126" EndNode="26189">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="32624" EndNode="32730">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="8" Type="Negation" StartNode="37666" EndNode="37773">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="9" Type="Negation" StartNode="40698" EndNode="40793">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="10" Type="Negation" StartNode="47923" EndNode="47971">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="11" Type="Negation" StartNode="48986" EndNode="49112">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="12" Type="Negation" StartNode="28735" EndNode="28835">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="13" Type="Negation" StartNode="27309" EndNode="27399">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="14" Type="Negation" StartNode="38268" EndNode="38291">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="15" Type="Negation" StartNode="17157" EndNode="17255">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="17" Type="Negation" StartNode="26956" EndNode="27037">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="16" Type="Negation" StartNode="47233" EndNode="47336">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="57336">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
