<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/essexcou1-10460.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>1518
NEW POLICE STATION
SMITHS FARM
GREAT DUNMOW
ESSEX
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION BY
TRIAL TRENCHING
Field Archaeology Unit
September 2005
NEW POLICE STATION
SMITHS FARM
GREAT DUNMOW
ESSEX
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION BY
TRIAL TRENCHING
Prepared By:
Andrew Robertson
Position:
Project Officer
Signature:
Date:
Checked By:
Patrick Allen
Position:
Project Manager
Signature:
Date:
Approved By:
Mark Atkinson
Position:
Unit Manager
Signature:
Date:
Document Ref. 1518Rep.doc
Report Issue Date September 2005
Circulation Essex Police
ECC Historic Environment Management
ECC Historic Environment Record
As part of our desire to provide a quality service, we would welcome any comments you may
have on the content or the presentation of this report.
Please contact the Archaeological Fieldwork Manager, at the
Field Archaeology Unit,
Fairfield Court, Fairfield Road, Braintree, Essex CM7 3YQ
Tel: 01376 331470
Fax: 01376 331428
© Field Archaeology Unit, Essex County Council, c/o County Hall, Chelmsford
Essex CM1 1LF
CONTENTS
Page No.
SUMMARY 1
1.0 INTRODUCTION 2
2.0 BACKGROUND 2
2.1 Location and topography
2.2 Geology
2.3 History and archaeology
3.0 AIMS AND OBJECTIVES 3
4.0 METHOD 3
5.0 FIELDWORK RESULTS 3
6.0 FINDS AND ENVIRONMENTAL MATERIAL 6
7.0 CONCLUSIONS 6
Acknowledgements 7
BIBLIOGRAPHY 7
APPENDICES
APPENDIX 1: FIELDWORK DATA 8
APPENDIX 2: FINDS AND ENVIRONMENTAL MATERIAL 8
APPENDIX 3: ARCHIVE INDEX 9
APPENDIX 4: EHER SUMMARY 10
FIGURES
Figure 1 ­ Site Location 4
NEW POLICE STATION
SMITHS FARM
GREAT DUNMOW
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION
TRIAL TRENCHING
SUMMARY
Client: Essex Police
FAU Project No.: 1518
NGR: TL 6367 2072
Planning Application No.:UTT/0669/04
Site Code: GDSF 05
Date of Fieldwork: 25th to 26th August 2005
An archaeological evaluation was carried out by ECC FAU on behalf of Essex Police on the site of
a proposed new police station at Smiths Farm, on the south-eastern outskirts of Great Dunmow,
Essex. The site was formerly rough pasture. The Chelmsford Road, which is thought to be the
line of a Roman road, runs immediately to the east of the site.
Five 30m x 2m trenches were excavated within the footprint of the proposed building and the area
of associated carpark. Only one archaeological feature was revealed, a ditch containing
prehistoric pottery dating to the Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age along with burnt flints and flint
flakes. No other archaeological features were identified, although a number of prehistoric pottery
sherds and flint flakes were discovered on the surface of the natural geology.
<Node id="2539"/>Although the results of the evaluation do not suggest intensive landscape use during the Late
Bronze/ Early Iron Ages<Node id="2656"/> it is clear from this and other nearby investigations that a focus for the low
level activity seen may well lie in the general vicinity. <Node id="2794"/>The absence of Roman or medieval remains
indicates that this site was well outside the settlements of these periods<Node id="2909"/>. <Node id="2911"/>The low quantity and
quality of the remains encountered on the site suggests that there is only a minor archaeological
implication<Node id="3041"/> for the location of the proposed police station here.
1
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
1.0 INTRODUCTION
A planning application was made by Essex Police for the construction of a new police station at
Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow. The Historic Environment Management (HEM) team of Essex
County Council advised the local planning office that an archaeological condition be placed on the
application, in line with PPG 16 (DoE 1990). Consequently, Essex County Council Field
Archaeology Unit (FAU) was commissioned to undertake an archaeological evaluation by trial
trenching on the footprint of the building and the area of the associated car park. This report
presents the results of the evaluation. The archive w be deposited with Saffron Walden Museum.
2.0 BACKGROUND
2.1 Location and Topography (Figure 1)
The proposed Police Station site comprises a roughly rectangular plot covering approximately
6000m² in the southeast corner of the field (NGR TL 6367 2072, centred). The east side of the site
is bounded by the Chelmsford Road and the south by Hoblongs Industrial Estate, to the north and
west is open scrub and grassland. Prior to the commencement of works the site was rough
pasture with no signs of cultivation in the recent past.
In general the land around the site slopes down to the southeast, with the area of the site being the
lowest part of the field lying at approximately 50.2m OD.
2.2 Geology
Topsoil to a depth of c. 0.2m covered the whole site; below this was a light brown silty sand subsoil
which ranged in depth from c. 0.2m to c. 0.5m. The undisturbed natural was orangey brown silty
sand. The drift geology of the area consists of Boulder Clay.
2.3 History and Archaeology
Great Dunmow is a known Roman `small town' which was situated on the junction of Stane Street
running east­west and the north­south Great Chesterford to Chelmsford road. It is postulated that
the town covered an area of 10-12 hectares (Wickenden 1988; Havis 2005), most of which lies
under the present town.
The site is located outside the probable limits of the Roman town, and an early Roman cremation
cemetery has been excavated on the western side of the Roman Dunmow-Chelmsford road at
Haslar's Lane approximately 0.5km to the north of the present site (Hickling 2003). While no
archaeological investigation appears to have taken place in the immediate vicinity of the site there
are a number of entries on the Essex Heritage Environment Record (HER) for the general area.
2
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
These primarily relate to the archaeological investigation associated with the construction of the
new A120 road or to the Roman town of Dunmow. These are predominantly Roman, although
HER 19149 is an unurned cremation that is thought to be prehistoric in date.
3.0 AIMS AND OBJECTIVES
The general aim of the project was to `...determine, the location, extent, date, character, condition,
significance and quality ...' of the remains. More specific aims were to:
· Determine if any prehistoric evidence is located within the development area
· Determine if there is any Roman ribbon development or cemetery evidence alongside the
Roman road
· Determine whether any evidence of medieval activity is located within the development
area
· Examine the likely impact of the proposed development on the archaeological resource
4.0 METHOD
The topsoil, and subsoil, was removed from the trenches using a JCB excavator fitted with a
toothless ditching bucket, under archaeological supervision. All archaeological features and
deposits were then excavated by hand using standard ECC FAU procedures, with plans being
drawn at 1:20 and sections at 1:10. Finds were collected for dating and characterisation purposes.
Sections of all features were recorded following standard ECC FAU methodologies. A
photographic record, consisting of monochrome prints and colour transparencies, was maintained
on selected individual features as well as general trench shots. Levels were taken of ground levels
on and around each of the trenches as well as on individual features. The positions of the
trenches were located using GPS.
IFA standards and by-laws and ALGAO's Standards for Field Archaeology in the East of England
(Gurney, 2003) were adhered to during the fieldwork, which was monitored by Ms V Clarke of ECC
HEM on behalf of the local planning authority.
5.0 FIELDWORK RESULTS (Figure 1)
Five trenches were excavated to the top of the undisturbed natural geology across the area.
Trenches 2, 3, 4 and 5 were all devoid of archaeological features. All of the trenches were 30m
long and approximately 1.7m wide. Each trench is described briefly below with further information
located in Appendix 1. Trench and feature locations are shown on Figure 1.
3
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
4
#
#
Great
Dunmow
Chelmsford
ESSEX
SITE
Hoblongs industrial estate
B184
Chelm
sford
Road
-
course
ofRom
an
Road
SITE
Powerline
Trench
1
Trench 2
Trench 3
Trench4
Trench 5
[1]
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the contoller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA10019602.
Fig.1. Site location
0 50m
N
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
ð
TL 6359
2083
TL 6361
2081
TL 6361
2079
TL 6359
2078
TL 6353
2076
TL 6356
2077
TL 6353
2081
TL 6355
2078
TL 6354
2081
TL 6357
2083
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
Trench 1
Running approximately northwest to southeast along the western edge of the Chelmsford Road,
Trench 1 was c.0.85m deep. Below the topsoil were two subsoil layers. The upper, a mid-grey
silty sand, was approximately 0.15m thick and was probably deposited recently, possibly during the
construction of the modern road or one of the surrounding industrial estates. The lower light brown
subsoil was 0.5m thick.
A single ditch [1] was identified at the northwest end of the trench (Fig.1). The ditch was
approximately 0.85m wide and 0.42m deep and ran across the trench on a northeast-southwest
alignment. Its single sandy silt pale yellow brown f contained two flint flakes, two burnt flints and
seven pottery sherds. <Node id="9351"/>Even though there were no diagnostic pieces of pottery<Node id="9405"/>, it is probable that
they are Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age in date (identified by N. Lavender). A further sherd of
pottery and five more flint flakes were recovered from the surface of the undisturbed natural
geology along the rest of the trench.
Trench 2
Trench 2 ran approximately east-west from Chelmsford Road along the boundary to Hoblongs
Industrial Estate. Below 0.15m of topsoil was a light brown silty sand subsoil 0.35m thick, which
was itself above the undisturbed natural geology. <Node id="9904"/>No archaeological features or finds were
identified in this trench<Node id="9970"/>.
Trench 3
Orientated approximately east-west this trench was 0.55m deep. The topsoil was 0.15m thick and
overlay the light brown silty sand subsoil, which was 0.4m thick. Although no features were
identified, three sherds of prehistoric pottery and a single flint flake were recovered from the top of
the undisturbed natural geology.
Trench 4
Trench 4 was aligned north-south along the western edge of the development site. It was
excavated to a depth of 0.5m through 0.2m of topsoil and 0.3m of light brown silty sandy subsoil.
No archaeological features were identified, although a single flint flake was recovered from the
surface of the undisturbed natural geology.
5
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
Trench 5
<Node id="10757"/>No archaeological features or finds were identified in this trench<Node id="10823"/>. It ran approximately east-west
along the boundary to Hoblongs Industrial Estate. Below 0.3m of topsoil was a light brown silty
sand subsoil 0.2m thick, which was above the undisturbed natural geology.
6.0 FINDS AND ENVIRONMENTAL MATERIAL
Small groups of finds were recovered from a total of four contexts, three of which represent
unstratified finds from three of the excavated trenches. The finds were recorded by count and
weight, in grams, by context. Full details can be found in Appendix 2. All of the finds are
prehistoric, comprising flint flakes, burnt flints and flint-tempered pottery.
Eleven sherds of pottery, weighing a total of 26g, were recovered, most of which came from f 2 of
ditch 1. Most of the pottery comprises featureless body sherds in Fabric D (identified by N.
Lavender), indicating a probable Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age date.
Nine flint flakes were recorded, most of which are likely to be working waste. In addition, two burnt
flints came from the f of ditch 1.
It is of interest that, although only small groups of finds were recovered, all of the material is likely
to be prehistoric. Activity in the prehistoric period is recorded in the vicinity, although the nature
and scale of the activity remains obscure.
All of the finds should be retained, although further work on the assemblage is not warranted.
7.0 CONCLUSIONS
Although only one archaeological feature was identified on the site, the number of unstratified finds
recovered from the top of the natural geology indicates that there is prehistoric activity, probably of
Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age date, in the vicinity. <Node id="12448"/>Although no focus for prehistoric activity
has been identified in this area<Node id="12523"/>, a single unurned cremation (HER 19149) was excavated to the
south of the site, prior to the construction of the A120. This is likely to be prehistoric in date and
may be contemporary with the feature and finds identified on this site. Also, the route of
Chelmsford Road is thought to have origins as a trackway in the prehistoric period, and it is
therefore unsurprising that finds and features of this date have been recovered from Smiths Farm.
<Node id="12971"/>The absence of features, deposits and even unstratified artefacts of Roman or medieval date
indicates that this site lies beyond the limits of the settlement at Great Dunmow<Node id="13144"/> during these
6
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
periods. <Node id="13274"/>There is no evidence for roadside ribbon-development or cemeteries this far south
alongside the Chelmsford road.<Node id="13386"/> Indeed, recent excavations further north into Great Dunmow
appear to demonstrate that settlement was more-or-less confined to the top of the spur until the
post-medieval period. The Roman cremation cemetery at Haslers Lane is a clear indication of the
settlement periphery at this time (Hickling 2003).
The presence of a single prehistoric feature and <Node id="13739"/>the absence of later remains associated with
either settlement at Great Dunmow or exploitation of its surrounding landscape<Node id="13862"/> suggests that there
is little further archaeological implication for the proposed construction of the police station on this
site.
Acknowledgements
This project was commissioned and funded by Essex Police. Especial thanks go to Pauline Dines
of Essex Police and Julie Priess of Mantle Estates for their help throughout the project. The finds
were processed by D. Smith, who also assisted the author during the fieldwork. The analysis of
the finds was undertaken by J. Compton and the illustrations prepared by A. Lewsey. The project
was managed by P. Allen and V. Clarke of ECC HEM monitored the fieldwork on behalf of the local
planning authority.
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Gurney, D. 2003 Standards for Field Archaeology in the East of England East Anglian
Archaeol. Occ. Pap. 14
Havis, R. 2005 Archaeological Trenching and Excavation on a New Police Station at
Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow Archaeological brief
Hickling, S. 2003 Former Council Depot, Haslars Lane, Great Dunmow, Essex.
Archaeological Excavation. Essex CC FAU report 1096
Medlycott, M. 1998 Great Dunmow, Historic Towns Project Assessment Report ECC
Planning
Wickenden, N.P. 1988 Excavations at Great Dunmow, Essex, E. Anglian Archaeol. 41
7
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
APPENDIX 1: FIELDWORK DATA
All dimensions are given in metres.
Context Feature Trench Category Details Period
1 - 1 Ditch NE­SW aligned;1.7m long,0.85m wide,0.42m deep Prehistoric
2 1 1 F F of 1; Pale yellow brown sandy silt
3 - 1 unstrat Finds from top of natural geology
4 - 4 unstrat Finds from top of natural geology
5 - 3 unstrat Finds from top of natural geology
Trench Contexts Length Breadth Depth Height
1 [1]; (2); (3) 30 1.7 0.85 49.51mOD
2 - 30 1.7 0.5 50.30mOD
3 (5) 30 1.7 0.55 50.98mOD
4 (4) 30 1.7 0.5 51.54mOD
5 - 30 1.7 0.5 52.21mOD
APPENDIX 2: FINDS AND ENVIRONMENTAL MATERIAL
All weights given in grammes
Context Feature Count Weight Description Date
2 1 2 8 Flint flakes -
2 22 Burnt flints -
7 20 Pottery; body sherds, flint-tempered (one may be
baked clay)
Prehistoric
3 u/s (Tr 1) 5 26 Flint flakes -
1 2 Pottery; body sherd, flint-tempered Prehistoric
4 u/s (Tr 4) 1 14 Flint flake -
5 u/s (Tr 3) 1 4 Flint flake -
3 4 Pottery; body sherd and crumbs, flint-tempered Prehistoric
8
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
APPENDIX 3: ARCHIVE INDEX
NEW POLICE STATION, SMITHS FARM, GREAT DUNMOW (GDSF 05)
Index to the Archive
1. Introduction
1.1 Brief for Evaluation
1.2 Specification for Evaluation
2. Research Archive (Material generated after fieldwork)
2.1 Evaluation Report
2.2 Finds Report
3. Site Archive
3.1 Context Register
3.2 Original Context Records 1 to 5
3.3 Levels Sheet
3.4 2 x Photographic Registers
3.5 5 x Black and White Prints
3.6 5 x Colour slides
3.7 1 Plan and section sheet (A5)
Not in Files:
1 box of finds
9
New Police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Essex Police
APPENDIX 4: EHER SUMMARY SHEET
Site Name/Address:
New police Station, Smiths Farm, Great Dunmow
Parish:
Great Dunmow
District:
Uttlesford
NGR:
TL 6367 2072 (centred)
Site Code:
GDSF 05
Type of Work:
Evaluation by Trial trenching
Site Director/Group:
Andrew Robertson
ECC FAU
Date of Work:
25/08/2005 ­ 26/08/2005
Size of Area Investigated:
Development area: 6000m2
Trenching: 5 trenches = 255m2
Location of Finds/Curating Museum:
Saffron Walden
Funding Source:
Essex Police
Further Work Anticipated?
No
Related EHER Nos:
HER 19149
Final Report: EAH Summary
Periods Represented: Prehistoric
SUMMARY OF FIELDWORK RESULTS:
An archaeological evaluation was carried out by ECC FAU, on behalf of Essex Police, on the
site of a proposed new police station at the southern end of Great Dunmow, Essex. The site
was formerly rough pasture and known as Smith Farm. Immediately to the east of the site
ran Chelmsford road, which is thought to be the line of a Roman road.
Five 30m trenches were excavated within the footprint of the proposed building and carpark.
Only one archaeological feature was revealed, a northeast­southwest aligned ditch
containing prehistoric pottery, burnt flints and flint flakes. The pottery is undiagnostic but
probably dates to the Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age. No other archaeological features
were identified although a number of prehistoric pottery sherds and flint flakes were
discovered on the surface of the natural geology.
<Node id="18345"/>Although the results of the evaluation do not suggest intensive landscape use during the Late
Bronze/ Early Iron Ages<Node id="18462"/> it is clear from this, and other nearby discoveries, that a focus for the
low level activity seen may well lie in the general vicinity. <Node id="18599"/>The absence of Roman or Medieval
remains indicates that this site was well outside the settlements of these periods<Node id="18714"/>.
Previous Summaries/Reports:
None
Author of Summary:
Andrew Robertson
Date of Summary:
September 2005
10
<Node id="18820"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="2539" EndNode="2656">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="2" Type="Negation" StartNode="2794" EndNode="2909">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="3" Type="Negation" StartNode="2911" EndNode="3041">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="9351" EndNode="9405">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="5" Type="Negation" StartNode="9904" EndNode="9970">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="10757" EndNode="10823">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="7" Type="Negation" StartNode="12448" EndNode="12523">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="8" Type="Negation" StartNode="12971" EndNode="13144">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="9" Type="Negation" StartNode="13274" EndNode="13386">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="10" Type="Negation" StartNode="13739" EndNode="13862">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="11" Type="Negation" StartNode="18345" EndNode="18462">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="12" Type="Negation" StartNode="18599" EndNode="18714">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="18820">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
