<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/essexcou1-5166.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>1428
PRIORS GREEN
TAKELEY
ESSEX
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION BY
TRIAL TRENCHING
Phase 1, Stage 1
Field Archaeology Unit
March 2005
PRIORS GREEN
TAKELEY
ESSEX
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION BY
TRIAL TRENCHING
Prepared By: Andrew Robertson
Position: Project Supervisor
Signature:
Date:
Approved By: Mark Atkinson
Position: Unit Manager
Signature:
Date:
Document Ref. 1428Phase 1 Stage 1.doc
Report Issue Date MARCH 2005
Circulation Countryside Properties Plc
RPS (PTE) Plc
HEM
HER
As part of our desire to provide a quality service, we would welcome any comments you may have on the
content or the presentation of this report.
Please contact the Archaeological Fieldwork Manager, at the
Field Archaeology Unit,
Fairfield Court, Fairfield Road, Braintree, Essex CM7 3YQ
Tel: 01376 331470
Fax: 01376 331428
© Field Archaeology Unit, Essex County Council, c/o County Hall, Chelmsford
Essex CM1 1LF
CONTENTS
Page No.
SUMMARY 1
1. INTRODUCTION 2
2. BACKGROUND 3
2.1 Planning
2.2 Location and topography
2.3 Geology
2.4 History and archaeology
3. AIMS AND OBJECTIVES 5
4. METHOD 6
5. FIELDWORK RESULTS 7
5.1 Trench 1a
5.2 Trench 1b
5.3 Trench 2
5.4 Trench 4
5.5 Trench 5
5.6 Trench 6
5.7 Trench 7
5.8 Trench 8
5.9 Trench 9
5.10 Trench 10
5.11 Trench 11
5.12 Trench 12
5.13 Trench 13
5.14 Trench 20
5.15 Trench 22
5.16 Trench 23
5.17 Trench 25
5.18 Trench 26
5.19 Trench 27
5.20 Trench 28
5.21 Trench 29
5.22 Trench 31
5.23 Trench 32
5.24 Trench 33
5.25 Trench 34
5.26 Trench 35
5.27 Trench 37
5.28 Trench 38
5.29 Trench 39
6. FINDS 15
6.1 Finds Summary
6.2 Prehistoric Pottery
6.3 Medieval Pottery
6.4 Flints
7. DISCUSSION 18
8. ASSESSMENT OF RESULTS 23
Acknowledgements 25
BIBLIOGRAPHY 26
APPENDIX 1: TRENCH SUMMARY 48
APPENDIX 2: FEATURE LIST 50
APPENDIX 3: FINDS DATA 52
APPENDIX 4: ARCHIVE INDEX 54
APPENDIX 5: EHCR SUMMARY 55
FIGURES
Figure 1: Priors Green ­ location, excavated features and projected alignments 28
Figure 2: Trenches 1A, 1B 2 29
Figure 3: Trenches 4 5 30
Figure 4: Trenches 9 12 31
Figure 5: Trenches 10 11 32
Figure 6: Trenches 20, 25, 28, 34 35 33
Figure 7: Trenches 27 29 34
Figure 8: Trenches 28 34 35
Figure 9: Trenches 31 32 36
Figure 10: Trenches 26, 36, 37 38 37
Figure 11: Trench group 7,8,9,10, 11 33 38
Figure 12: Trench groups 28, 29 34 and 1b 39 39
Figure 13: Trench group 5,6 38 40
Figure 14: Sections 41
Figure 15: Section of Trench 38 42
Figure 16: Ditch alignments 1 and 2 43
Figure 17: Ditch alignments 3 and 4 44
Figure 18: Prehistoric and medieval features 45
Figure 19: Post-medieval features 46
Figure 20: Priors Green ­ excavated features and first edition O.S. map 47
11
PRIORS GREEN
TAKELEY, ESSEX
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EVALUATION BY TRIAL TRENCHING
SUMMARY
Client: RPS (PTE) on behalf of Countryside Properties Plc
FAU Project No.: 1428
NGR: TL5730 2140
Planning Application No.: UTT/0816/00/OP
Site Code: TAPG04
Date of Fieldwork: 29/11/04 ­ 17/12/04
An archaeological evaluation, covering c.9.9 hectares, was carried out on the site of proposed housing
development at Priors Green, Takeley. Forty trenches were opened, covering 2980 sq m (c.3%). The
majority of features uncovered were ditches and gullies with only a few pits and post-holes scattered across
the site.
In the western third of the site three parallel Early Iron Age ditches running northwest-southeast were
identified. Along with fragments of further ditches that seem to run northeast-southwest these possibly form
a co-axial field system. The other prehistoric features identified include a possible ring ditch and cremation
burial at the eastern end of the site.
<Node id="3560"/>No Roman or Saxon period remains were identified but a handful of medieval ditches<Node id="3642"/> and pits were; mostly
in the eastern third of the site. In the southeast corner the possible remains of a small medieval enclosure
were investigated but no definite conclusions were reached.
A number of post-medieval ditches, including at least nine parallel, north-south aligned ditches in the
southwest corner of the site, were investigated. Several of these late ditches correspond to field boundaries
marked on the 1874 1st edition O.S. map. The parallel ditches were perpendicular to the present Dunmow
Road, parallel to existing field boundaries, and are probably the remains of a strip field system.
A large possible boundary ditch running approximately east­west across the centre of the western third of
the site may be geological in origin although the evidence from the excavated segments is inconclusive.
In general, all the features seem to be agricultural in nature and n<Node id="4528"/>one produced significant quantities or types
of finds indicative of settlement activity<Node id="4615"/>, of any period, in close proximity. However, evidence of the
prehistoric exploitation and usage of the Essex boulder clay is of significance as it is traditionally considered
as less agriculturally viable land.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
22
1. INTRODUCTION
This report contains the results of an archaeological evaluation prior to the construction of housing
at Priors Green, Takeley, Essex (Fig. 1). The evaluation consisted of trial trenching across an area
of perceived archaeological potential. The investigation was designed to determine the presence,
nature, date and survival of any archaeological remains in the proposed development area.
Essex County Council Field Archaeology Unit (ECC FAU) carried out the evaluation for RPS
Planning Transport and Environment, the latter acting as consultants on behalf of Countryside
Properties Plc. The project was carried out in accordance with a brief prepared by the Heritage
Advice, Management and Promotion (HAMP) Team of Essex County Council, who also monitored
the work. The site archive w be deposited at Saffron Walden Museum. A copy of this report will
be deposited with the Essex Heritage and Conservation Record (EHCR) and a summary will
appear in Essex Archaeology and History (EAH).
Evaluation work and the reporting of it have been carried out to professional standards and
guidance issued by the Institute of Field Archaeologists (Institute of Field Archaeologists 1999) and
the Association of County Archaeological Officers (ACAO 1993).
The report is structured to describe the background to the project, followed by the results of the
fieldwork. Finds reports are then organised by category with an overall discussion, followed by an
assessment of the results are at the end. Appendices include trench, context and finds data, in
addition to the details of the archive contents and the EHCR summary. All illustrations are placed
together towards the back of the report.
Phase 1 mitigation proposals are subject of a separate document (RPS 2005).
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
33
2. BACKGROUND
2.1. Planning
A planning application (UTT/0816/00/OP) for a c.30ha housing development was submitted to
Uttlesford District Council by Countryside Properties Plc in August 2000. After the completion of
an archaeological desk-based assessment (CgMS 2000) followed by an Environmental Impact
Assessment and Statement (RPS 2000) the HAMP Team of Essex County Council recommended
that pre-determination archaeological evaluation work was required before the determination of the
application. However, after negotiation and preliminary field walking it was agreed that the
archaeological issues facing the development could be addressed by the placing of an
archaeological planning condition on Outline Consent. Due to the perceived low archaeological
potential of the proposed development area, it was agreed that a 2.5% archaeological evaluation
sample (with the option to increase the sample to a maximum of 5% should significant
archaeological remains be uncovered) would be an appropriate strategy to implement. In response
to this condition Countryside Properties Plc commissioned RPS Planning Transport and
Environment to manage the historic environment issues. RPS in turn commissioned Essex County
Council Field Archaeology Unit (ECC FAU) to undertake an evaluation, by trial trenching, on Phase
1 of the development, an area of c. 9.9ha. This report presents the results of the trial trenching
investigation.
2.2 Location and Topography (Fig. 1)
The proposed development lies within a parcel of land bounded to the north by Jacks Lane, to the
east by Thornton Road, to the south by Dunmow Road and to the west by property boundaries (TL
5730 2140) (Fig.1).
The site is currently fallow fields which until recently have been under cultivation. It is a relatively
flat, roughly grassed area with a fall to the south, towards Dunmow Road. The highest point,
situated at the northwest corner of the site, is 99.37m O.D. and the lowest, at the southern end of
Warwick Road, is 92.49m O.D. There is also a slight downwards slope west - east with the
northeast corner of the site having a height of 94.88m O.D. The area is traversed by Hamilton
Road, Warwick Road and a public footpath, all running north-south, and by Clarendon Road
running east-west. Several houses are situated around the edges of the area.
2.3 Geology
The depth of the topsoil averaged c.0.30m, although many trenches exhibited a significant sub-soil
layer of disturbed silty-clay of c.0.25m deep below this.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
44
The drift geology of the site was generally that of pale brown chalky boulder-clay of the Lowestoft
Formation, although this was mixed with deposits of purer mid brown clay across the site. A few
patches of natural gravel were also observed, especially towards the south of the area. The solid
geology of the area is London Clay (BGS map EW222 Great Dunmow v.2).
2.4 History and Archaeology
The site is located within a wider agricultural landscape, dating from the Bronze Age through to the
present day, that is becoming increasingly better understood and documented as a result of
archaeological field work taking place in advance of construction development work. This is shown
particularly by recent work at Stansted Airport (Havis Brooks, 2004; Framework Archaeology, in
prep), evaluation and excavation work undertaken in advance of the re-alignment and construction
of the A120 (Fitzpatrick 2001) and also be recent work undertaken at Takeley, some 1.5km to the
west of the present site (Roberts 2003).
To the immediate south of the site Dunmow Road is on the approximate line of Stane Street, the
Roman road from Braughing/ Puckridge to Colchester (Drury and Rodwell 1980). To the northeast
at Frogs Hall is a presumptive Roman villa (ESMR 9140) with associated Roman features whilst
Warish Hall (ESMR 4572), a Scheduled medieval moated site (protected under the Ancient
Monuments and Archaeological Areas Act, 1979), lies 1km to the north. Another medieval moated
site, Jacks Green (ESMR 4655), is located immediately to the north west of the current site, but is
of lower status. Jacks Lane, a bridleway that runs east west to the north of the site, is also thought
to have medieval origins.
The picture emerging from this increasing body of evidence is that the area between Stansted and
Braintree was well settled and farmed from the Bronze Age onwards. From the Late Iron Age
onwards, with an increasing Roman influence on the landscape and the apparent re-alignment of
the focus of the landscape, small farmsteads began to appear along the road line (e.g. Buildings
Farm, Lavender 1997), some which developed into small towns, such as Great Dunmow
(Robertson (a) in press; Wickenden 1986) and Braintree (Drury and Rodwell 1980), during the
Roman period.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
55
3 AIMS AND OBJECTIVES
The evaluation work was undertaken to locate, identify and record any surviving remains within the
proposed Phase 1 development area. In particular, the evaluation sought to clarify:
· Whether surface flint finds from the 2001 walkover survey relate to buried archaeology
of Neolithic and/ or Bronze age date
· Whether there is evidence within the Proposal Site which can be related to settlement
evidence of prehistoric, Roman and medieval date recorded at Stanstead Airport
· Whether there is any evidence of medieval occupation in the land surrounding the
moated site of Jacks Green or the medieval routeway of Jacks Green lane
· The impact that the proposed development would have on the archaeological resource
(RPS 2004)
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
66
4 METHOD
A mechanical excavator with a flat-bladed bucket was used to open 40 trenches under
archaeological supervision.
Standard ECC FAU methodologies were employed with regard to excavation and recording. All
features were recorded using the FAU's context recording system. Planning and surveying was
tied to the Ordnance Survey National Grid. A photographic record consisting of colour slide, black
and white print and digital images was maintained thought the course of the excavation.
The machine-excavated surface of the trenches was sufficiently cleaned to ensure that any
features present were visible. Archaeological features and deposits were excavated using hand
tools, other than obviously modern features and particularly large ditches, which were partially
machine excavated under close archaeological supervision, with the agreement of RPS and
HAMP.
The original trench plan, as proposed in the Written Scheme of Investigation, was modified with the
agreement of HAMP and RPS to clarify questions that arose during the excavation. In addition to
the original 32 trenches (Trench 1 was split in to 1a and 1b to avoid electricity cables), eight further
trenches (32 to 39) were excavated, giving a total of 40 trenches. The original trenches comprised
a total of 2.5% of the total area with a contingency for a further 2.5% if needed. The extra
trenching increased the total area investigated to 2980 sq m, 3% of the total area.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
77
5. FIELDWORK RESULTS (Fig 1)
Thirty-one of the trenches measured approximately 40 x 2m, four measured 20 x 2m, two
measured 25 x 2m and one measured 10 x 2m, the remaining two measured 15 x 8m and 20 x 5m
respectively. Trenches 14, 15, 16, 17, 19, 24, 30 and 36 contained no archaeological features and
Trenches 3, 18 and 21 contained features, which were probably geological in nature. The
remaining trenches and the features contained in them are described, in summary, below.
A number of the features identified across the site show evidence of plough truncation. In general
there is very little stratigraphy with few intercutting features identified. The dating evidence
collected was not of sufficient quantity or quality to allow more than the broadest dating of features
to be undertaken. It should be noted that few of the features are securely dated at this stage. With
a few exceptions, which are noted in the descriptions below, all the features were filled with a mid
brown homogenous silty clay containing chalk pebbles and small stones.
Further information on individual trenches is presented in Appendix 1 and individual features,
including dimensions, are listed in Appendix 2. All pertinent trench plans (Figs 2 ­ 12) and
sections (Figs.13 and 14) are situated at the rear of the report. In the descriptions below the
excavated context number is cited in brackets ­ thus [136]. Where the same feature was
recorded, either by excavation or plan, in more than one trench a group number has also been
assigned, primarily for use in the discussion. Heights of the excavated ground surface above
Ordnance Datum (O.D) for the centre of each trench are noted alongside the individual trench
headers.
5.1 Trench 1a (Fig.2a) 97.53m O.D
In the northwest corner of the site Trench 1a ran east-west, parallel to Jacks Lane. Two ditches
were recorded in this trench. Ditch [136] lay at the western end of the trench and ran southwest­
northeast. Ditch 138 lay at the eastern end of the trench and ran northwest­southeast. Neither
ditch contained dateable material. However, ditch [138] potentially lines-up with ditches in
trenches 5 and 6 (Group 158).
5.2 Trench 1b (Figs. 2b and 12b) 97.88. O.D
Approximately 75m to the east of Trench 1a, Trench 1b ran east-west and was again positioned
parallel to Jacks Lane. Two features were recorded in this trench. A ditch terminal [128] ran
northeast to southwest through the centre of the trench, with the terminal towards the north. No
dating evidence was recovered from this feature. The second feature, the remains of a hedge line
[174], which is marked on 1st edition O.S. map, ran north-south through the western end of the
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
88
trench and was also noted in Trench 39. This was filled with dark brown lose loam and numerous
rotted roots and contained car spark plugs, amongst other modern detritus.
5.3 Trench 2 (Figs. 2c and 14a) 96.18m O.D
Slightly to the southeast of Trench 1b, Trench 2 ran north-south parallel to the boundary of
Gamecards Cottage. Two ditches and a pit were recorded in this trench. <Node id="17288"/>Ditch [112] ran
northwest-southeast across the centre of the trench and contained no datable material<Node id="17389"/>. Ditch [114]
ran east west also in the centre of the trench, from which an undated, single struck flint flake was
recovered. Pit [100] lay towards the northern end of the trench and contained nine sherds of
pottery dating to the 12th to 14th centuries. None of the features in this trench have been equated
with similar remains in other trenches.
5.4 Trench 4 (Figs 3a and 14b) 96.27m O.D
Trench 4 lay immediately to the south of Trench 1a and ran north-south. Two post-holes [132] and
[130] and a possible gully [134] were identified in this trench. Post-hole 130 lay along the eastern
baulk in the central part of the trench. Post-hole 132 lay towards the northern end of the trench.
Gully 134 was very shallow and filled with topsoil and was probably a plough scar. None of the
features contained any dating evidence. This trench exhibited a variable geology with the chalky
boulder clay interleaved with areas of purer clay.
5.5 Trench 5 (Fig 3b, 13 and 14c) 96.66m O.D
Running east-west Trench 5 was situated to the south of Trench 3. Four features were identified in
the trench, two pits [81] [83], a gully [71] and a large northeast­southwest running ditch [69].
<Node id="18560"/>Small pit [83] lay towards the eastern end of the trench and contained no dateable material<Node id="18651"/>. <Node id="18653"/>Pit
[81] lay immediately to its east and, although it contained no dateable material, cut gully [71]<Node id="18753"/>. Gully
[71] ran northwest-southeast and contained 60 small sherds of Early Iron Age pottery (weighing 46
grams in total). A continuation of it was seen in Trenches 1a and 6 (Group 158). Ditch 69 is
particularly large at approximately 5m wide and 1.4m deep. It only contained one f of sterile clay
but had very clear edges. The sides of this ditch sloped at approximately 45° and it had a flat
base. It was also seen in Trench 38 (Group 171).
5.6 Trench 6 (Fig. 13) 96.62m O.D
To the south and east of Trench 5, Trench 6 ran north-south. A single ditch running northwest-
southeast was identified in this trench but was only planned as further parts of it had been
previously investigated in Trenches 5 and 1a (Group 158).
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
99
5.7 Trench 7 (Fig 11) 95.98m O.D
Running east-west, parallel to Clarendon Road, Trench 7 lay to the west of Trench 6. Four ditches
were identified in this trench but were only planned as they were encountered and excavated in
other trenches. The three most westerly of the ditches ran approximately north-south, parallel to
one another, and were also identified in Trenches 10, 11 and 33 (Groups 166, 165 and 164)
respectively. The most easterly ran northwest-southeast and was also identified in Trench 12
(Group 159). The projected line of this ditch ran parallel with that encountered in Trenches 1a, 5
and 6.
5.8 Trench 8 (Fig 11) 95.79m O.D
Immediately to the southwest of Clarendon Road Trench 8 ran northwest southeast. Two parallel,
shallow ditches [144] and [142] ran north-south at the western end of the trench. Ditch [144]
contained one sherd of Late Iron Age pottery which may be a residual find as the context also
contained two fragments of charcoal and coal while [142] yielded two small fragments of
undiagnostic prehistoric pottery and one burnt flint. Three other ditches also ran north-south and
were planned only, being excavated in Trenches 33 11.
5.9 Trench 9 (Figs. 4a, 11 and 14d) 94.14m O.D
Situated in the southwest corner of the site, Trench 9 ran north-south. Three ditches and a
possible pit were recorded in the trench. All the ditches [73], [91] and [96] were situated in the
southern half of the trench and ran northwest-southeast. The pit [75] was cut by ditch [73] but is
probably a natural feature. No dating evidence was recovered from this trench.
5.10 Trench 10 (Figs. 5, 11 and 14e) 93.94m O.D
Trench 10 lay to the east of Trench 9 and also ran north-south. Trench 11 was joined
perpendicularly to the southern end of Trench 10. Parallel ditches [65] (Group 161) and [56]
(Group 162) ran northwest-southeast across this trench and were projected continuations of
ditches evaluated in Trench 11 and planned in Trench 33. The f of ditch [56] contained a single
sherd of Late Iron Age pottery and a single sherd of Early Iron Age pottery.
Pit [67] lay towards the northern end of the trench and pit [85] towards the southern. <Node id="21737"/>Both were
probably natural in origin possibly tree throws or solution hollows and did not contain any dating
evidence<Node id="21854"/>. At the very south of the trench undated post-holes [87] and [89] were recorded.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1010
5.11 Trench 11 (Figs. 5 and 11) 94.41m O.D
Perpendicular to Trench 10, Trench 11 ran east-west. It contained the highest number of features
on the site with nine ditches and a small pit. Parallel Ditches [150] (Group 167), [152] (Group 168),
[154] (Group 169), [146] (Group 170), [108] (Group 165) and [120] (Group 164) all ran north-south
and are also seen in Trenches 33, 7 and 8. Ditches [93] (Group 162), and [106] (Group 161) seem
to run at a slightly different angle to the other ditches and were also identified in Trenches 10 and
33. Undated ditch [156] ran northeast-southwest. At the eastern end of the trench was small pit
[126]. The average dimensions of these ditches were approximately 0.8m wide and 0.4m deep
although the maximum width was 1.36m and the minimum depth was 0.11m. A more
comprehensive list of dimensions is laid out in Appendix 2. Ditch [93] contained two `crumbs' of
undiagnostic prehistoric pottery, one small sherd of Roman pottery, a small fragment of iron and a
fragment of modern, `fibrous' tile suggesting that the early ceramic material was residual. Ditch
[120] yielded two sherds of pottery dating to the Early Iron Age; ditch [154] produced a single sherd
of undiagnostic prehistoric pottery and ditch [108] a single piece of abraded post-medieval pottery.
5.12 Trench 12 (Figs. 4b and 14f) 93.89m O.D
To the west of Trench 10, Trench 12 ran north south. Only one northwest-southeast aligned ditch
[58] was identified and was a continuation of one planned Trench 7 (Group 159). The pottery from
the ditch (91 sherds from a single vessel) suggests that the feature is Early Iron Age in date. It
represents the most reliable dating evidence on the site.
5.13 Trench 13 (Fig 1) 96.29m O.D
To the south of the boundary to Gamecards Cottage, Trench 13 ran north-south, parallel to
Warwick Road. A single, east-west running, ditch was identified in the trench but it was only
planned as it was recorded and further investigated in Trenches 23, 27 and 26 to the east, where it
was revealed to be modern.
5.14 Trench 20 (Figs. 6a and 14g) 95.21m O.D
Trench 20 was located towards the eastern end of the site and ran east-west. Single shallow gully
[22] ran north-south through the centre of the trench. The pottery recovered from the feature
indicates that it was either Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age in date, a single intrusive sherd of
Roman pottery and two struck flint flakes were also collected. This gully may have curved and be
associated with gully [98] in Trench 35. A small undated pit [33] was located towards the eastern
end of this trench.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1111
5.15 Trench 22 (Fig 1) 95.67m O.D
Situated to the east of Warwick Road, and slightly to the north of No 5 Hamilton Road, this trench
ran east-west. It contained a small pit [45], which seems to have contained a fire as the
surrounding clay was scorched. <Node id="24980"/>No dateable material was recovered from this feature<Node id="25032"/>.
5.16 Trench 23 (Fig 1) 96.32m O.D
Parallel to Warwick Road, directly to the east of Trench 13, Trench 23 ran north-south. A single
east-west running ditch was identified. This was machine excavated as the surface finds, such as
coal and china, indicated that it was modern in origin. The ditch proved to have a land drain
situated in its base and so was only recorded in plan. It was also identified in Trenches 13, 27 and
26.
5.17 Trench 25 (Fig 6b) 96.03m O.D
Running east-west, Trench 25 lay to the west of Hamilton Road. Modern pit [28] and undated
post-hole [26] lay in the centre of this trench. Towards the western end V-shaped ditch [30] ran
north-south. The ditch and pit [28] contained modern glass and cans, all of which was discarded
on Health and Safety grounds. Ditch [30] aligns with an extant property boundary to the north and
appears as a field boundary on the 1st edition OS map.
5.18 Trench 26 (Fig 10a) 95.79m O.D
In the southeast corner of the site Trench 26 ran northwest-southeast from Thornton Road.
Ditches [24], [25], [61] and [63], gully [40] and possible post-holes [52] and [50] were identified in
the trench. Ditches [24] (containing post medieval roof tile fragments and iron nails) and [25] ran
approximately east-west and appear to be part of the same modern ditch seen in Trenches13, 23
and 27. Gully [40] cut ditch [25] but was probably a plough scar. Post-holes [50] and [52] were
very shallow and irregular and may only have been pockets of natural silting. Shallow ditch [61]
ran east-west and was also identified in Trench 37 immediately to the west. Ditch [63] ran north
south but was not identified in any other trench. No other dating evidence was recovered from this
trench.
5.19 Trench 27 (Figs. 7a and 14h) 95.94m O.D
To the west of Trench 26, Trench 27 ran north-south. It contained a single east-west running ditch
[42], which contained post-medieval artefacts and had a ceramic land drain at its base. The ditch
was also identified in Trenches 13, 23 and 26 and appears on the 1st edition OS map as a field
boundary.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1212
5.20 Trench 28 (Figs. 8 and 12a) 95.15m O.D
Perpendicular to Thornton Road and to the north of Trench 20, Trench 28 contained ditch [14], pit
[16] and possible cremation burial [8], and ran east west. Shallow ditch [14] ran northeast-
southwest and was also identified in Trenches 29 and 34. <Node id="27492"/>No finds were recovered from this
feature<Node id="27533"/>. <Node id="27535"/>Small oval pit [16] contained no datable material<Node id="27584"/>. The f of possible cremation burial [8]
was 100% sampled (Sample 1 ) and passed through a flotation tank. It contained a small
quantity (seven sherds) of Late Bronze Age pottery and two sherds of possible Roman pottery
(burning hindered diagnosis) together with burnt bone, slag, charcoal fragments and six carbonised
grains. The tiny quantity of burnt bone present does not allow species identification and it is
unclear whether it is human or animal. The area around the putative cremation burial was opened-
up (see Trench 34), <Node id="28116"/>but no other cremation-like features were identified<Node id="28168"/>.
5.21 Trench 29 (Figs. 7b and 12a) 95.91m O.D
Running north-south to the east of Trench 28, Trench 29 contained ditches [6], [12], and [20] and
pit [18]. At the southern end of the trench parallel ditches [6] (Group 172) and [20] (Group 173) ran
northeast to southwest and were identified in Trench 34, some 9m apart. Ditch [6] (containing a
single piece of 13th to 14th century pottery) was further identified in Trench 28 and.<Node id="28597"/> Undated
narrow ditch [12] ran east-west across the centre of the trench<Node id="28669"/>. <Node id="28671"/>Pit [18] contained no finds and was
located between ditches 6 and 20<Node id="28739"/>. It may in fact have been a ditch terminal rather than a pit, as it
was similar in depth and breadth.
5.22 Trench 31 (Fig. 9) 94.53m O.D
In the northeast corner of the site Trench 31 ran north-south from Jacks Lane. The only feature
present was a modern ditch [10] that ran northwest-southeast and contained a land drain in its
base. This ditch is shown on the 1st edition OS map as a field boundary. Natural feature [4] was
situated in the centre of the trench but upon excavation it proved to be geological.
5.23 Trench 32 (Fig. 9) 94.53m O.D
Adjoining Trench 31, Trench 32 was 25m long and ran east-west. A northward continuation of
modern boundary ditch [10] was recorded, though not further excavated.
5.24 Trench 33 (Fig. 11) 94.53m O.D
Trench 33 lay immediately to the north of Trench 10 and was parallel to Clarendon Road. Six
north-south ditches were present, but only one [148] (Group 164) was excavated. No dating
evidence was recovered from this feature. The others were planned only, further parts of these
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1313
having been excavated in Trenches 7, 11 and 10. The only other feature present was a probably
natural deposit of silt, [140].
5.25 Trench 34 (Figs. 8 and 12a) 94.83m O.D
An area measuring 10 x 8m was opened around the eastern end of Trench 28 to determine
whether any further putative cremation burials lay in the vicinity. None were identified but further
parts of ditches investigated in Trenches 29 and 28 were plotted. <Node id="30283"/>No artefacts were identified on
the surface of the ditches were identified<Node id="30357"/>.
5.26 Trench 35 (Fig. 6a) 93.26m O.D
Perpendicular to, and adjoining, Trench 20, Trench 35 ran north south for 20m. A single gully
terminal [98] was investigated and pottery recovered from it dated to the Early Iron Age. A number
of flints were also collected, including a twice-worked core. This feature may be part of gully [22] in
Trench 20.
5.27 Trench 37 (Figs. 10a and 14i) 92.58m O.D
Running north-south for 25m from the south-western side of Trench 26, Trench 37 contained
ditches [116] and [118]. Shallow ditch [116] was a continuation of ditch [61] investigated in
adjacent Trench 26 and confirmed the westerly continuation of this feature. The pottery recovered
from ditch [116] was Early Iron Age and Roman in date but the abraded nature of all of these
sherds may suggest that they are all residual. Vertical-sided ditch [118] ran approximately north
south and contained abraded sherds of 12th to 14th century pottery. Ditches [116] and [118] may
in fact be contemporary, but their intersection lay outside the trench and so a precise relationship
was not established.
5.28 Trench 38 (Figs 10b, 13 and 15) 96.87m O.D
Trench 38 was 20m long and ran northwest to southeast between Trenches 2 and 13. Large Ditch
[123] (Group 171) measured approximately 9m wide and 1m deep and ran approximately east-
west through this trench and contained two fills. It is likely that this is the same feature as ditch
[69] recorded in Trench 5. Although reduced by machine a 1m wide section was hand excavated
through this ditch. Two small sherds of pottery were recovered from the upper f of the hand
excavated section, one prehistoric and one 12th to 13th century in date. Both sherds were
retrieved during manual excavation from the very top of the feature, which allows a modicum of
doubt as to the nature/circumstance of their deposition, especially if the sterile nature of the
remaining inf is considered. A currently unprocessed column sample was taken from the section
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1414
(Samples 2 and 3 ). A modern east-west ditch ran to the south of ditch [123] and was
recorded in plan only.
5.29 Trench 39 (Fig 12b) 97.56m O.D
This was the smallest trench on the site, measuring 10m long, and was situated to the west of
Trench 2, running northwest to southeast. The features in it were planned only and consisted of an
undated northeast-southwest aligned ditch [160] and the eastern edge of the old hedge line also
observed in Trench 1b.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1515
6 FINDS
6.1 Finds Summary by J Compton
Small amounts of finds were recovered from a total of twenty-three contexts, across fourteen of the
excavated trenches. All of the material was counted and weighed, in grams, by context; full details
can be found in Appendix 3. The finds types present comprise mainly struck flints and pottery,
predominantly of prehistoric date. Few site features can be closely dated, but, in general, the
medieval and post-medieval material was recovered near to currently-occupied buildings. In
addition, modern and post-medieval finds were located in a drainage trench running across the
centre and east of the investigated area. A fragment of modern fibrous tile came from ditch [93],
Trench 11 and a piece of burnt stone, possibly derived from tarmac, from pit [89], Trench 10.
Prehistoric material was recovered from features in the west of the excavated area, but these finds
are also few in number. Prehistoric pottery came from twelve contexts, and amounted to 175
sherds, weighing 620g. Seven contexts produced a total of fifteen worked flints, weighing 200g.
The flints, prehistoric pottery and medieval pottery (15 sherds, weighing 81g) form the subject of
separate short reports, and, since the remaining categories are few, these are described together
below.
Late Iron Age and Roman pottery was recovered from five contexts, amounting to 7 sherds,
weighing 24g. <Node id="34389"/>These are small body sherds, none of which can be closely dated within the Late
Iron Age and Roman periods<Node id="34495"/>; two sherds are in grog-tempered ware, ditches [56] and [144], and
three are sandy grey ware, ditches [22], [117] and [93].
Six pieces of post-medieval roof tile, weighing 68g, came from three contexts. These are small
and abraded. The fragments from f (39) of ditch [25] are associated with a sherd of post-
medieval red earthenware and a clay pipe stem. Those from f (36) of ditch [24] are associated
with two iron nails. A flat iron fragment was found in f (94) of ditch [93], in the same context as
the fibrous tile noted above. <Node id="35029"/>This ironwork is likely to be post-medieval, although there are no
diagnostic features which confirm this date<Node id="35139"/>.
A fragment of iron was also recovered from the f of possible cremation burial [8], in Trench 28.
Twenty-four burnt bone fragments, weighing less than 2g, were recovered from the feature, but the
amount is too small to ascertain whether these are animal or human. Also present were quantities
of slag and charcoal, and the latter included six carbonised cereal grains. The few sherds of
pottery present are prehistoric, with two which are either Roman in date, or have been severely
burnt. Identification as a cremation burial is problematic, as the burnt bone is not necessarily
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1616
human. The presence of iron, slag and prehistoric pottery together is improbable, unless one
category is residual or the other intrusive.
Baked clay and slag fragments were present in two fills of post-medieval ditch [42]. The sole
animal bone is a very abraded sheep/goat molar in f (60) of Early Iron Age ditch [58]. Charcoal
and coal fragments were found in three contexts ((23), (43) and (145)); these were discarded after
recording.
The prehistoric pottery and the flints attest to prehistoric activity in the vicinity. However, the
assemblage, including the prehistoric finds, is fragmentary and abraded. The average sherd
weight for all of the pottery is 3.5g, indicating a potentially high level of residuality. In addition,
there are instances of modern intrusion, such as coal and fibrous tile, over much of the site. It
seems likely that few of the finds are in their original places of deposition.
Quantities are too small for further study, although more work at Takeley may provide enough
evidence to define the prehistoric activity. The finds should all be retained, except for the modern
and post-medieval items.
6.3 Prehistoric Pottery by N.J. Lavender
The excavation produced a total of 175 sherds (625g) of prehistoric pottery from twelve contexts,
and includes two unidentifiable burnt sherds from f (9) of possible cremation burial [8] which may
be later (possibly Roman). The pottery was recorded using a system developed for prehistoric
pottery in Essex (Brown 1988). Most of the material is in flint-and-sand tempered Fabric E, with a
small number of flint-tempered sherds and some grog-and-vegetable tempered (Fabric M) sherds
from f 9. The assemblage is fragmentary and mostly abraded.
Only one context (f (60)) contained diagnostic material, including small fragments of a flat base
and the neck and shoulder of a slightly angular shouldered, upright-rimmed Form D jar. Sherds
from a slightly flared rim are finer and unlikely to be from the same vessel. The Form D jar belongs
to the Late Bronze Age or Early Iron Age. The slightly flared, flat-topped rim sherds from the same
context indicate an Early Iron Age date, as does the sand-and-flint tempered fabric, which
comprises most of the assemblage.
6.4 Medieval and Post-medieval Pottery by Helen Walker
A very small amount of medieval and later pottery was recovered, 15 sherds weighing 81g. The
earliest pottery is a sherd with very sparse shell-tempering, which is similar, but not identical, to a
fabric recovered from the nearby Stansted Airport excavations datable to the 12th to early 13th
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1717
centuries from ditch [123] (Group 171, Trench 38). This sherd may be intrusive as earlier pottery
was also recovered from the same feature. Dating to the 13th to 14th century is a single tiny
sherd of sandy orange ware, most likely from a jug, showing the remains of white slip decoration
from ditch [6] (Group 172, Trench 29). There are also several abraded sherds of medieval coarse
ware, perhaps from cooking pots, which are probably contemporary with the sandy orange ware
sherd from ditch [118] (Trench 37). In spite of a medieval drove road and moated site in the
vicinity, there is very little evidence from the pottery of medieval activity. The post-medieval period
is represented by only two sherds of post-medieval red earthenware one from ditch [25] (Trench
26) and one from ditch [108] (Group 165, Trench 11), a ware manufactured throughout the post-
medieval period, <Node id="39378"/>but as these examples are glazed they are unlikely to date before the late
16th/17th century<Node id="39470"/>.
6.5 Flints by Hazel Martingell
Twenty pieces of flint, weighing a total of 200g, came from seven contexts. Fifteen of these were
humanly worked and five were natural. Patination occurs on three of the worked pieces.
There are two cores and two core-trimming flakes. One, from f 99 of ditch 98, is a good core
from which flakes have been removed at different times. The three earliest flake removal surfaces
are patinated and then, later, flakes were removed from this core using the patinated surfaces as
platforms. A core-trimming flake (f (119), ditch [118]) also has a patinated platform.
The second patinated piece is an interesting retouched flake (f (115), ditch [114]). It has fine
invasive retouch all along one curved edge. This flake was removed from a larger implement,
possibly a knife.
The remaining ten pieces consist of flakes and one fragment.
The patinated flints should be of an early prehistoric date, but patination can occur at later dates on
artefacts from chalky soils, for instance, the core from ditch 98 occurs with Early Iron Age pottery,
but the trimming flake is associated with medieval pottery and must be residual. The unpatinated
flints suggest a late prehistoric date, <Node id="40675"/>but no closer dating is possible for these artefacts<Node id="40727"/>.
Most of the assemblage was recovered from excavated ditch segments, mainly in the eastern part
of the site, but some flints are clearly residual. Even the patinated flints are probably residual in
later prehistoric features.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1818
7 DISCUSSION
The Phase 1 site can perhaps be divided into three distinctive areas based upon the
archaeological remains uncovered by the trial trenching evaluation. The western third of the site
contains the majority of the Prehistoric remains as well two possible phases of Post-medieval field
systems, the central third is largely blank apart from a few undated discrete features and the
eastern third contains mainly medieval and Post-medieval remains with Prehistoric remains
represented by a solitary putative cremation burial and two small gullies which may be part of a
ring ditch. Interpretation and discussion of the significance of the major features is presented, by
broad period, below.
Prehistoric (Fig.18a)
A series of ditches at the western end of the site appear to be the remains of prehistoric field
systems. Two possible alignments (alignments 1 and 2) (Fig.16) have been identified, but it should
be stressed that these are speculative at present as the distances between the observed segments
are often in excess of 50m.
Ditch Alignment 1 (Fig 16a)
The first and probably most speculative of the alignments (alignment 1) runs northeast to
southwest and consists of shallow ditch segments in Trenches 1a (ditch [136]), 1b (ditch [128]), 39
(ditch [160]) and 11 (ditch [156]). <Node id="42350"/>No artefacts were retrieved from their single homogonous fills<Node id="42412"/>
and their tentative dating is deduced from the similarity of feature dimension and f type with
datable ditches in prehistoric alignment 2. All but ditch [156] cluster in the northwest corner of the
Phase 1 area. Although similarly proportioned and aligned, the south-westerly location of [156]
may suggest that it is not directly associated with the others.
Ditch Alignment 2 (Fig 16b)
Ditch alignment 2 runs northwest to southeast and roughly perpendicular to that of alignment 1. It
comprises three parallel ditches [112] (Trench 2), (158) (Trenches 1a, 5, 6) and (159) (Trenches 7
and 12), the longest of which exceeds 160m in length. These shallow features again contained a
single homogenous f and generally few artefacts. However, the excavated segments in Trenches
5 and 12 (ditches [71] and [58], respectively) yielded Early Iron Age pottery that appears to be in
situ and therefore constitutes reliable dating evidence.
Their relative position suggests that alignments 1 and 2 may be contemporary and are the remains
of a co-axial field system and therefore indicative of Early Iron Age agricultural exploitation of the
boulder clay landscape at this location. It is interesting to note that neither of the alignments seems
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
1919
to relate to those of the perceived succeeding elements of the surrounding landscape; Stane Street
(Roman) and Jacks Lane (Medieval). This may substantiate the tentative prehistoric date assigned
to these features. <Node id="43961"/>While no remains indicative of associated settlement activity of this date has
been identified<Node id="44055"/> within the Phase 1 evaluation area, the nearby excavations at Stansted Airport
have revealed earlier Iron Age sites that include several storage structures, `ritual' pits and rubbish
pits (Havis and Brooks 2004, 519). Although it is unlikely that the Priors Green remains are directly
associated those at Stansted, it is evident that they add to the growing appreciation that the
boulder clays of northwest Essex were widely occupied and exploited during the period.
Other Prehistoric features
Apart from these ditch systems, only a small number of discrete features of prehistoric, or possible
prehistoric, date have been identified. The substantial ditch [171], running approximately east-west
through Trenches 5 and 38 (Fig.12), may be of natural origin but the single prehistoric pottery
sherd as well as the probable intrusive medieval sherd (both from high up in the top fill), and the
fact that it runs contrary to the prevailing north-south alignment for periglacial features as noted
from this and previous excavations in this vicinity, both suggest otherwise. If archaeological in
nature, it clearly represents a small part of a substantial boundary feature, though <Node id="45232"/>not obviously
associated with settlement activity<Node id="45281"/>. Though projected to intersect with alignment 2 ditch [158] to the
south of Trench 5, <Node id="45368"/>this was not substantiated in the field and so their relative chronology is not
determined<Node id="45458"/>.
Two small gully segments, [98] and [22], revealed in Trenches 35 and 20, may be parts of a single
feature. Although lacking any direct relationship, their similar V-shaped profiles and relative
positions suggest they may be parts of a ring gully. If so, and if regular, this feature could be
postulated to be in the order of c.30m diameter. <Node id="45801"/>Although ring ditches and gullies are not
exclusively of prehistoric date<Node id="45874"/>, this is a distinct probability if such conjecture is right. The presence
of worked flints and early Iron Age pottery would seem to support an interpretation as a small
enclosure, though the seemingly intrusive sherd of Roman pottery introduces an element of
caution.
The possible cremation burial [8] (Trench 20) is a seemingly isolated occurrence. <Node id="46225"/>There is no
evidence for any associated structures or features<Node id="46287"/>. It is not unusual to find solitary prehistoric
cremations at a considerable distance from settlements. Although this feature is significant in that
it indicates prehistoric activity in the area, <Node id="46484"/>it does not necessarily suggest that settlement is in the
near vicinity<Node id="46555"/>. Indeed the presence of iron slag and carbonised grain throws the classification of this
feature as a cremation burial into doubt.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2020
Late Iron Age and Roman
<Node id="46811"/>No Late Iron Age or Roman features have been identified on the site<Node id="46878"/> and the few sherds of pottery
recovered are likely to be residual in medieval or later features. This absence is interesting in itself
given the proximity of the Phase 1 area to the Roman fields, kilns/hearths, cremation burials and
presumptive villa alongside the river Roding at Frogs Hall some 8km to the north-east (T. Ennis
pers comm.). Past investigation alongside both the old and new A120 roads has further
established that Roman farming settlement sites occur with regular frequency alongside Stane
Street, often slightly set back amid a well-developed agricultural landscape such as at Buildings
Farm (Lavender 1997), Stansted Airport and new A120 (Fitzpatrick 2001, 363 ­ 364).
It is interesting to note that the settlements alongside Stane Street appear to have been sited on
gravel rather than boulder clay and it may be the case that soil-type, geology and topography is
key. The fact Phase 1 Priors Green happens to be located on less-preferred clay may account for
the apparent no use of the area during theses periods. However, some of the sites at Stansted
Airport were situated on similar clays, which suggests that this may not be the sole reason for the
<Node id="48054"/>lack of visible activity during the Late Iron Age to Roman periods<Node id="48120"/>.
Medieval (Fig.18b)
Within the Phase 1 development area, medieval period remains are confined to ditches [116]/[61]
(Trenches 26 and 37), [118] (Trench 37), (172) and (173) (Trenches 29, 28 and 34), and a single
pit [100]. The ditches all lay in the eastern third of the site. Ditches (172) and (173) ran parallel to
each other and may constitute the remains of a trackway. Ditches [116]/[61] and [118] may be part
of a small enclosure or structure, but this is speculative on the present evidence. <Node id="48620"/>None of the
ditches are particularly well-dated<Node id="48667"/>, with only a few sherds of 12th to 14th century pottery from each.
In Trench 2, Pit [100] contained a 9 sherds of pottery but the fill, which contains no obvious organic
material or silting resulting from being left open, looks to have been backfilled quickly after the
feature was dug. It is likely that several of the undated pits and post-holes in the north-western
corner of the site are also medieval in origin and perhaps associated with pit [100]. However, <Node id="49132"/>none
of the medieval features on the site seem to have any direct relationship<Node id="49210"/> with either Jacks Lane or
any of the moated sites that lie just beyond the peripheries of the Phase 1 area. <Node id="49319"/>The relative
absence of medieval period remains<Node id="49366"/> at this location may be due to tangible activities being
confined within the moated sites themselves, the closest being Jacks Green, just off the north-west
corner of the evaluation area. The results of excavation at Frogs Hall suggests that medieval
agricultural and processing/manufacturing activities were not particularly different from those of the
Roman period, with traces of fields and pottery manufacture being identified alongside the river
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2121
Roding (M. Atkinson pers comm.). It is therefore perhaps likely that a similar pattern of land-use
and avoidance can be expected in the medieval period as for the Roman at Priors Green.
Post-medieval (Fig. 19)
A series of parallel ditches at the western end of the site appear to be the remains of one, or
possibly two, Post-medieval field systems (alignments 3 and 4).
Ditch Alignment 3 (Fig 17a)
Alignment 3 consists of three pairs of parallel ditches approximately 23m apart, in the south-west
corner of the site. They all run approximately NNW to SSE. All contained homogenous single fills.
Although, small quantities of Late Iron Age pottery were retrieved from ditches [142] and [144]
(Trench 8) and Ditch [56] (Group 162, Trench 10), Roman and post-medieval pottery was
recovered from segment [93] (Group162, Trench 11). The fragmented nature of the earlier pottery
sherds suggests that it is likely to be residual in significantly later features. There is <Node id="50882"/>no clear
indication as to what these pairs of ditches represent<Node id="50945"/> and it may be that they are actually part of
alignment 4.
Ditch Alignment 4 (Fig.17b)
Alignment 4 comprises nine parallel ditches, again located in the south-west corner of Phase 1.
Closely and regularly spaced at approximately 4m apart, these features run slightly nearer north-
south than those of alignment 3. While they form the most convincing group in plan and uniformity,
they are poorly dated ­ relying solely upon a three small abraded sherds of prehistoric pottery from
ditch segments [120] and [154] (Groups 164 and 169, Trench 11) and a Post-medieval sherd from
ditch segment [108] (Group165, Trench 11).
It is possible that alignments 3 and 4 are part of a single system of ditches and that their slightly
differing alignments merely constitute re-cutting or re-establishment/replacement, either wholesale
or piecemeal. Both, and particularly alignment 4, appear to lie perpendicular to the lines of Stane
Street and Jacks Lane, at either end of the Phase 1 area. Furthermore, alignment 4 is seemingly
parallel with the existing field boundary just to its west. Although both alignments contain
prehistoric pottery and worked flints, this is likely to be wholly residual. A similar arrangement of
ditches containing small abraded sherds of prehistoric pottery was identified by trial trenching
evaluation at Marks Hall School, Harlow. Subsequent open area excavation showed them to be in
fact of Post-medieval, perhaps early 19th century, date (Robertson (a), in press).
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2222
Several other post-medieval ditches were also encountered in the Phase 1 area, the majority of
which can be directly related to boundary features marked on the 1st edition O.S map of 1874
(Fig.20). <Node id="52728"/>None of the excavated segments suggest that the ditches had significantly earlier origins<Node id="52817"/>
and their fills contained frequent items of 19th and 20th century rubbish. Although parts of a few of
these old field boundaries are now incorporated into modern property boundaries, the majority
have clearly been deliberately infilled to create larger fields.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2323
8. ASSESSMENT OF RESULTS
The results of the evaluation in relation to the stated aims of the project are addressed below;
Whether surface flint finds from the 2001 walkover survey relate to buried archaeology of
Neolithic and/ or Bronze Age data.
<Node id="53426"/>There was no evidence of archaeological features or deposits dating to the Neolithic or Bronze
Ages<Node id="53525"/>. The few worked flints recovered from around the site were residual in later features. Bronze
Age sites have been identified in the general area (Couchman 1980) so it is therefore not
surprising that residual flints are found in later features.
Whether there is evidence within the Proposal Site which can be related to settlement
evidence of prehistoric, Roman and medieval date recorded at Stanstead Airport.
None of the revealed archaeology at Priors Green seems to be directly related to the settlements
uncovered at Stanstead Airport. However, it is clear that the area of the site formed part of the
wider landscape in which the settlements functioned.
The Early Iron Age field systems are potentially outer fields for the settlements at Stanstead Airport
but equally they may relate to other, as yet unidentified, settlements. <Node id="54360"/>Although no evidence for
significant settlement was identified within the Phase 1<Node id="54441"/> development area the early Iron Age
enclosure gully in Trenches 20 and 35, together with pit [8] and its burnt remains, may indicate a
small habitation area in the east of the site.
<Node id="54624"/>The lack of substantive Roman and the low incidence of the medieval remains<Node id="54699"/> may reflect a
preference for utilising less heavy soils during these periods.
Whether there is any evidence of medieval occupation in the land surrounding the moated
site of Jacks Green or the medieval routeway of Jacks Green lane.
The investigation of medieval activity alongside Jacks Lane, particularly in the form of dwellings
and plots fronting onto this thoroughfare, has not proved productive. It appears that there has
been no significant past activity along, and associated with, this part of the ancient track. <Node id="55221"/>There is
no obvious relationship between the medieval features on Phase 1<Node id="55294"/> and close-by sites such as the
Jacks Green and Warish Hall moated farms. However, parallel ditches (172) and (173) may be the
remains of a trackway which further investigation may show to connect to other medieval sites.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2424
The impact that the proposed development would have on the archaeological resource.
Most of the features are less than 0.5m deep with good preservation and definition of
archaeological horizons. There is evidence of significant modern plough truncation, which
indicates that any intrusion of construction works into sub-soil deposits w have an adverse effect
upon any archaeological remains present. Furthermore, it is very likely that the majority of the
archaeological remains on the site w be totally removed by any groundworks in excess of 1m in
depth.
However, bearing in mind that the trenched area totals only some 3% of the proposed
development, it is possible that both extensive ditches and smaller, discrete, features may lie
undiscovered in the intervening spaces. From the trial trenching it is possible to identify two
potential `hot spots' of archaeological activity, in the western third of the site and in the
southeastern corner. The impact of the development outside these areas is likely to be negligible
on the present evidence.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2525
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
This project was commissioned by RPS (PTE) Plc on behalf of Countryside Properties Plc.
Thanks go to S Blatherwick and R Masefield for their assistance throughout the project. The
project was conducted by Essex County Council Field Archaeology Unit. The fieldwork was
carried out by the author with the assistance of J Archer, B Barker, C Down, A Turner and D Smith.
All finds were processed by Phil McMichael and analysed by Joyce Compton, Nick Lavender and
Hazel Martingell. Digitising of plans and digital illustration was undertaken by Andy Lewsey. The
project was managed by Mark Atkinson of ECC FAU. Richard Havis of the ECC HAMP Team
monitored the fieldwork.
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2626
BIBLIOGRAPHY
ACAO 1993 Model Briefs and Specifications for Archaeological Assessments and
Field Evaluations
Brown, N. 1988 `A Late Bronze Age enclosure at Lofts Farm, Essex' Proc. Prehist.
Soc. 54, 249-302
Brown, N. 
Glazebrook, J.
(ed)
2000 Research and Archaeology: a Framework for the Eastern Counties
2. Research agenda and strategy, EAA Occ. Pap.8
CgMS 2000 Archaeological Desk Based Assessment; Land at Priors Green
Couchman,
C.R.
1980 ` The Bronze Age in Essex' in Archaeology in Essex to AD1500,
Buckley, D.G. (ed), CBA 34,40 - 46
Drury, P.J. 
Rodwell, W.
1980 `Settlement in the later Iron Age and Roman periods' in Archaeology
in Essex to AD1500, Buckley, D.G. (ed), CBA 34, 59 - 75
Framework
Archaeology
In
prep
Archaeological Excavations at Stanstead Airport
Fitzpatrick, A.P. 2001 `East Anglia' in Roman Britain in 2000 Britannia XXXII, 311 ­ 400
Haselgrove, C.
Et al
2001 Understanding the British Iron Age: An agenda for action, Wessex
Archaeology
Havis, R. 
Brooks, H.
2004 Excavations at Stansted Airport, 1986 ­ 91 E. Anglian Archaeol. 107
Institute of Field
Archaeologists
1999 Standard and Guidance for archaeological field evaluation
Lavender, N.J. 1997 Middle Iron Age and Romano-British settlement at Great Dunmow:
excavations at Buildings Farm 1993 Essex Archaeol. Hist. 28, 47 ­
92
Robertson, A.
(a)
In
Press
Mark Hall School, Harlow, Essex Archaeological Excavation Essex
Archaeol. Hist. In press
Robertson, A.
(b)
In
Press
Redbond Lodge, Chequers Lane, Great Dunmow, Essex.
Archaeological Watching Brief and Excavation Essex Archaeol. Hist.
In press
Roberts, B. 2003 Land South of the A120 Essex (Report 1301) Arch. Sol. Client
Report
RPS 2000 Priors Green Takeley, Environmental Statement
RPS 2004 Priors Green, Takeley, Brief for Archaeological Evaluation Costing,
Uttlesford District Council, Central NGR TL 5730/2140 RPS Brief of
Priors Green, Takeley
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared for Countryside Properties Plc
2727
Archaeological Works
RPS 2005 Priors Green Takeley Archaeological Research Design and
Mitigation Strategy RPS project design
Walker, H. 2004 `Medieval pottery', in Havis and Brooks, 2004, 398-435
Wickenden,
N.P.
1988 Excavations at Great Dunmow, Essex: a Romano-British Small Town
in the Trinovantian Civitas EAA 41
2828
#
09 05
58 00
45 11
00 21
00 78
80 77
12 80
00 02
La yw oo d
Sp riw oo d
Y an gu
S ilv er tho rn
R un nel 's He y
R un nel 's He y
Path
(um)
G ar age
Re ma rc
Mon
Abri
TheBu
ngalow
Dreadn
ought
Th eO liv ia s
S pin ne y
L od geSt Jo hn s
Er sam in e
Ne w Ca mb rid ge
Ga rag e
1
.22m
RH
T re e To ps
Tra
ck
LB
N or th Vi ew
P o nd D ra
in
B ail eys
9 3. 3m
B M 94 .5 8m
D ra
in
D ra
in
9 4. 5m
War ren F armM o tel
Wh ite
Ko um a la
Ev an sto n
2
8
1
5
Th eR e st D ra
in
9 2. 4m
B M 94 .4 9m
T he H om es te ad
TheR
ise
Willo w s
Th e
H ou se
Ne w
C R
C
FCH
D ra
in
9 6. 3m
S o uth vie w
V as
Nurs
ery
Cotta
ges
2
1
1
G ar
age
Wi llow T re e
11
1
Ta ke le yN ur se rie s
T ra
ck
Ta nk Ta nk
B ro ad me ad
Bu rb an k
S
S
C LA R EN D
ON R OA D
WARWIC
KROAD
Ro se m ary C ott ag e
P o nd
Iss ue s RH
1.2 2m
R H
E
D an d W ar
d B dy
J A
C K'S
LA N
E
Autu
mns
Copp
ins
LaTe
leve
Vie
w
Kam
bria
Cypru
s
Twy
ford
Dra
in
P o nd
P o nd
J ac k's
G re en
P o nd
Dra
in
Pa
th
1.2 2m
R H
B M 10 3.5 4m
Pa rk er' sF ar m
W a ter
Dra
in
O a kL od ge
S
P
Path
(um)
A 1
20
Co tta ge s
Lio n
A 1
20
B
B
D UN M OW
R O AD
S tan e
Str ee t
R O M AN
R OA D
Wa rre nC ot tag es
Th e
P um p
War ren Y ar d
T ra
ck
HAMILTO
NROAD
THORNTO
NROAD
F F
BROADFIE
LDROAD
Tk s
4
Pa
th
Th eL io na nd L am b
(PH )
P o nd
Path
(um)
A lm aro
Th eN e st
Ga me ca rd sC o ttag e
Mo at
Fie
ld
Co tta ge
Clo ud s
Ho us e
We st vie w
Co tta ge
1
3
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
Fig.1. Priors Green - location, excavated features and projected alignments
LB
WarrenMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
New
F
CH
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
y g
Pond
ssues
RH
1.22m RH
ED and Ward Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
Pump
W
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
1a 2
34
5
7
6
13
14
8
9
10
11
12
16
15
17
18
19
21
22
25
2423
31
30
29
28
20
27
26
1
4
1
6
8
10
5
1
8
2
0
6
1
2
30
28
26
33
22
4
2
4
8
4
5
33
32
5
8
50
52
24
2540
61
54
63
34
35
37
36
38
1b
39
6
9
7
1
8
1
8
3
9
8
1
03
110
100
112
114
128
1
16
1
18
1
30
1
32
1
34
142
144
1
36
1
38
140 148
65
67
56
85
87
89
150 156
152 154
146 93
106 108
126
120
123
Jacks Lane
Takeley
ESSEX
Greater
London
Chelmsford
Takeley
Site
100m0
N
Dunmow Rd
(Stane St)
2929
N
0 10m
136
138
100
112
114
128
Trench 1A
Trench 2
Trench 1B
Fig.2. Trenches 1A, 1B 2. 1:200.
Fig.2a
Fig.2b
Fig.2c
Fig.14a
Old hedge line
(on 1ed OS map)
natural feature
3030
10m0
N
83
81
71
69Trench 5
Fig.3. Trenches 4 5. 1:200.
Fig.3b
Fig.14c
Fig.3a
Fig.14b
Trench 4
130
132
134
natural feature
3131
10m0
N
Trench 9 Trench 12
58
75
73
73
91
96
Fig.4. Trenches 9 12. 1:200.
Fig.4a Fig.4b
Fig.14d
Fig.14f
natural
feature
3232
65
67
56
85
87
89
146154 93
106 108
152
156
150
126
120
Trench 10
Trench 11
Fig.14e
10m0
N
Fig.5. Trenches 10 11. 1:200.
3333
Trench 25
30
28 26
Trench 20
Trench 35
33
22
98
N
0 10m
Fig.6. Trench 20, 25, 28, 34 35. 1:200.
Fig.6b
Fig.6a Fig.14g
Possible Ringditch
3434
Fig.7. Trenches 27 29. 1:200.
N
0 10m
42
Trench 27
Fig.14h
Fig.7a Trench 29
12
6
18
20
Fig.7b
3535
Trench 28
Trench 34
14 16 8
10m0
N
Fig.8. Trenches 28 34. 1:200.
3636
10m0
N
4
10
Trench 31
Trench 32
Fig.9. Trenches 31 32. 1:200.
natural
feature
3737
10m0
N
24
25
40
116 61
63
52
50
Trench 26
Trench 37
Trench 36
Fig.10. Trenches 26, 36 , 37 38. 1:200.
Fig.14i
Fig.15
Fig.10b
123
Trench 38
Fig.10a
118
Hand excavated
slot
3838
N
0 20m
Fig.11. Trenches 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 33. 1:500
142
144
Trench 7
Trench 8
Trench 33 140
148
Trench 10
Trench 11
65
67
56
85
87
89
93146150
156
152 154 106
108
126
120
Trench 9
96
91
73
75
3939
Trench 29
Fig.12. Trenches 28, 29 34 and 1b 39. 1:500
20m0
N
Fig.12a
Fig.12b
Trench 28
Trench 34
12
6
18
20
14
16 8
Trench 35
Trench 1b
Trench 39
128
old hedge
line
4040
N
0 20m
Trench 38
123
Trench 5
69
7181
83
Trench 6
Fig.13. Trench group 5, 6 38. 1:500
4141
1
2
70
3
3
Fig.14c. Trench 5
69
E W
101
100
N S
Fig.14a. Trench 2
1
2
131
130
Fig.14b. Trench 4
N S
74
73
Fig.14d. Trench 9
W E
1
2
66
65
Fig.14e. Trench 10
S N
60
59
Fig.14f. Trench 12
58
SW NE
1
23
22
22
Fig.14g. Trench 20
E W
1
43
4442
Fig.14h. Trench 27
N
S
modern
pipe
117
116
Fig.14i. Trench 37
S N
Fig.14. Sections
0 2m
97.77m ?
97.06m 93.95m
95.68m
94.4m
95.45m
94.89m 92.73m
1
2
4242
2m0
Fig.15. Section of Trench 38
NNE SSW
96.98m
1
124
125
123
4343
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
TheNew
F
CH
Drain
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
N
0 100m
N
LB
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CF
CH
Drain
Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
Figure 16a - Alignment 1
136
128
160
156
0 100m
Figure 16b - Alignment 2
Figure 16 - Ditch alignments 1 and 2
112158
159
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
4444
Garage
LB
94.5
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CR
CF
CH
Drain
ew
eries
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
y g
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
W arren Cottages
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
3
N
0 100m
N
LB
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homes tead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CR
CF
CH
Drain
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
W arren Cottages
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
3
142
144
16173
96
162
Figure 17a - Alignment 3
0 100m
91
163
164165
166
169
168167
170
Figure 17b- Alignment 4
Figure 17 - Ditch alignments 3 and 4
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
4545
Garage
LB
North View
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CR
CF
CH
Drain
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
W arren Cottages
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
3
N
0 100m
N
LB
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homes tead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CR
CF
CH
Drain
s
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
Iss ues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
W arren Cottages
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
3
0 100m
Fig.18a. Prehistoric features
#
Figure 18b - Medieval features
Figure 18 - Prehistoric and medieval features
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
4646
LB
94.5m
Warren FarmMotel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CF
CH
Drain
Tank Tank
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
Issues
RH
1.22mRH
ED and W ard Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
The
Pump
Warren Yard
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
Fig.19. Post-medieval features
0 100m
N
4747
New Cambridge
Garage
T
LB
North View
Motel
White
Koumala
Evanston
2
8
1
5
The Rest Drain
92.4m
BM 94.49m
The Homestead
TheRise
Willows
The
House
New
CR
CF
CH
Broadmead
Burbank
SS
CLARENDON ROAD
WARWICKROAD
Rosemary Cottage
Pond
ues
RH
1.22m RH
ED and Ward Bdy
Path
SP
DUNMOW ROAD
Stane Street
ROMAN ROAD
Warren Cottages
The
HAMILTONROAD
THORNTONROAD
Path(um)
Almaro
The Nest
Gamecards Cottage
Clouds
1
3
1a 2
34
5
7
6
13
14
8
9
10
11
12
16
15
17
18
19
21
22
25
2423
31
30
29
28
20
27
26
1
4
1
6
8
10
5
1
8
2
0
6
1
2
30
28
26 33
22
4
2
4
8
4
5
33
32
5
8
50
52
24
2540
61
54
63
34
35
37
36
38
1b
39
6
9
7
1
8
1
8
3
9
8
1
03
110
100
112
114
128
1
16
1
18
1
30
1
32
1
34
142
144
1
36
1
38
140
148
65
67
56
85
87
89
150
156
152 154 146 93
106 108
126
120
123
100m0
N
Mapping reproduced by permission of Ordnance Survey on behalf of
the controller of HMSO. Crown copyright. Licence no.LA100019602.
Fig.20. Priors Green - excavated features and first edition OS map
4848
APPENDIX 1 : TRENCH SUMMARY
All dimensions are given in metres
Trench Length Width Depth Area Grid Refs.
NW SE corner
Orientation Features
1a 20 2 0.6 40 TL 57282/21538
57301/21524
East-West Ditch 136, Ditch 138
1b 20 2 0.37 40 TL 57379/21538
57401/21540
East-West Ditch 128, Mod Hedge line
2 40 2 0.38 80 TL 57410/21532
57411/21492
North-South Pit 100, Ditch 112, Ditch 114
3 40 2 0.55 80 TL 57355/21512
57353/21471
North-South Natural Feature 110
4 40 2 0.6 80 TL 57355/21511
57296/21473
North-South Ph 130, Ph 132, Gully 134
5 40 2 0.75 80 TL 57354/21438
57394/21443
East-West Ditch 69 71, Pit 81, Ph 83
6 40 2 0.5 80 TL 57397/21425
57399/21384
North-South Planned only - 1 ditch
7 40 2 0.43 80 TL 57342/21363
57380/21383
East-West Planned only ­ 4 ditches
8 40 2 0.54 80 TL 57314/21363
57342/21335
Northwest-
Southeast
Ditch 142, Ditch 144 ­
3 other ditches planned only
9 40 2 0.55 80 TL 57304/21309
57305/21268
North-South Ditch 73, Ditch 91, Ditch 96,
Pit 75
10 40 2 0.54 80 TL 57362/21319
57362/21279
North-South Pit 85, Pit 87, Ph 89,
Ditch 65, Pit 67, Ditch 56
11 40 2 0.54 80 TL 57340/21279
57379/21276
East-West Ditches 93, 106, 120, 108, 146,
150, 154, 156, Ph 126
12 40 2 0.5 80 TL 57417/21342
57419/21301
North-South Ditch 58
13 40 2 0.3 80 TL 57451/21462
57453/21421
North-South Planned only ­ 1 ditch (Mod)
14 40 2 0.45 80 TL 57438/21398
57478/21396
East-West Blank
15 40 2 0.46 80 TL 57502/21348
57492/21347
East-West Blank
16 40 2 0.46 80 TL 57404/21283
57442/21281
East-West Blank
17 40 2 0.42 80 TL 57452/21337
57473/21296
North-South Blank
18 40 2 0.7 80 TL 57492/21291
57494/21255
North-South Layer 102, Nat Feat 103
19 40 2 0.5 80 TL 57529/21287
57562/21266
Northwest-
Southeast
Blank
20 45 2 0.6 90 TL 57622/21483
57653/21481
East-West Ditch 22, Ph 33
21 40 2 0.43 80 TL 57528/21352
57529/21311
North-South Pit 48
22 40 2 0.37 80 TL 57511/21401
57549/21399
East-West Pit 45
23 40 2 0.4 80 TL 57502/21470
57505/21430
North-South Modern ditch ­ Machine
excavated
24 40 2 0.32 80 TL 57518/21443
57557/21443
East-West Blank
25 40 2 0.3 80 TL 57529/21482
57569/21480
East-West Ph 26, Pit 28, Ditch 30
26 40 2 0.45 80 TL 57657/21446
57687/21420
Northwest-
Southeast
Pit 50, Pit 52,
Ditches 24, 25, 40, 61,63
27 40 2 0.4 80 TL 57624/21461
57626/21421
North-South Ditch 42
28 40 2 0.54 80 TL 57620/21535
57659/21534
East-West Crem 8, Ditch 14, Pit 16
29 40 2 0.55 80 TL 57593/21545
57594/21504
North-South Pit 20, Pit 18
Ditch 06, Ditch 12
30 40 2 0.63 80 TL 57588/21583 East-West Blank
4949
57627/21575
31 40 2 0.5 80 TL 57650/21619
57644/21577
North-South Nat feat 04, Ditch 10
32 25 2 0.6 50 TL 57622/21595
57645/21594
East-West Planned only ­ 1 ditch
33 40 2 0.80 80 TL 57333/21327
57373/212328
East-West Nat feat 140, Ditch 148
5 ditches planned only
34 15 8 0.43 120 TL 57646/21540
57659/21529
N/A Planned only ­ 2 ditches
35 20 2 0.5 40 TL 57618/21503
57621/21483
North-South Ditch 98
36 20 5 0.53 100 TL 57668/21415
57685/21420
East-West Blank
37 25 2 0.4 50 TL 57665/21439
57667/21415
North-South Ditch 116, Ditch 118
38 20 2 0.36 40 TL 57410/21468
57426/21455
Northwest-
Southeast
Ditch 123
1 other ditch planned only
39 10 2 0.45 20 TL 57392/21509
57400/21502
Northwest-
Southeast
Planned only ­ 1 ditch
5050
APPENDIX 2: FEATURE LIST
All dimensions are given in metres.
Number Type Filled by Equals Length Breadth Depth Trench Date
1 Topsoil All
2 Subsoil All
3 Undist Nat All
4 Pit 5 - 1.1 0.78 0.35 31
6 Ditch 7 14 0.55 0.98 0.57 29 13­14 C
8 Crem Pit 9 - 0.3 0.29 0.15 28 LBA or Roman
10 Ditch 11 - 0.95 1.12 0.35 31
12 Ditch 13 - 0.8 0.54 0.28 29
14 Ditch 15 6 +1 1.2 0.26 28
16 Pit 17 - 0.35 0.78 0.12 28
18 Pit 19 - 0.8 0.65 0.19 29
20 Pit 21 - 1.65 0.6 0.15 29
22 Ditch 23 - 0.7 0.56 0.29 20 Prehist or Roman
24 Ditch 35, 36 42 0.5 1.05 0.4 26 P Med
25 Ditch 37, 38, 39 - 0.7 1.14 0.62 26 L16-19 C
26 Post-hole 27 - 0.46 0.28 0.09 25
28 Pit 29 - 0.75 0.65 - 25
30 Ditch 31, 32, 77, 78, 79, 80 - +1 1.8 0.9 25
33 Pit 34 - - 0.55ø 0.26 20
40 Ditch 41 - 0.5 0.4 0.3 26
42 Ditch 43, 44 24 0.6 2.4 1.4 27 Modern
45 Pit 46, 47 - 1.16 0.74 0.17 22
48 Pit 49 - - 1.2 0.22 21
50 Pit 51 - 0.47 0.88 0.11 26
52 Pit 53 - 0.58 0.6 0.06 26
54 Ditch 55 63 2 1.7 0.7 26
56 Ditch 57 93 0.68 0.6 0.25 10 LBA/EIA
58 Ditch 59, 60 - 2.7 1.06 0.51 12 EIA
61 Ditch 62 116 2 0.6 0.36 26
63 Ditch 64 54 2 1.3 0.53 26
65 Ditch 66 106 2.1 0.58 0.12 10
67 Pit 68 - 1.28 1 0.27 10
69 Ditch 70 123 1.9 3.5 1.04 5
71 Ditch 72 138? 1 0.95 0.18 5 EIA
73 Ditch 74 - 0.48 0.7 0.98 9
75 Pit 76 - 1.05 0.58 0.32 9
81 Pit 82 - 0.4 0.48 0.13 5
83 Post-hole 84 - 0.55 0.5 0.21 5
85 Pit 86 - 2.5 0.74 0.43 10
87 Post-hole 88 - 0.93 0.8 0.19 10
89 Post-hole 90 - 0.85 0.7 0.15 10 Modern
91 Ditch 92, 95 - 0.7 0.6 0.25 9
93 Ditch 94 56 0.91 0.81 0.27 11 Modern
96 Ditch 97 - 0.8 0.82 0.31 9
98 Ditch 99 - +1.7 0.5 0.26 35 EIA
100 Pit 101 - +1.9 2.8 0.8 2 12 ­ 14 C
103 Nat Feat 104, 105 - 2 0.5 1 18
106 Ditch 107 65 0.9 0.7 0.24 11
5151
108 Ditch 109 - 0.84 0.76 0.11 11 P.med
110 Nat Feat 111 - 0.7 1.15 4.9 3
112 Ditch 113, 122 - +1 1.25 0.5 2
114 Ditch 115 - +1 0.86 0.38 2
116 Ditch 117 - +2 0.71 0.38 37 Roman or later
118 Ditch 119 - +8 0.6 0.51 37 12 ­ 14 C
120 Ditch 121 148 0.92 0.69 0.22 11 EIA
123 Ditch 124,125 69 +2 8.7 0.94 38 Prehist or 12/13 C
126 Post-hole 127 - - 0.7ø 0.13 11
128 Ditch 129 - +1 0.9 0.28 1b
130 Post-hole 131 - +0.35 0.6 0.3 4
132 Post-hole 133 - 0.5 0.4 0.15 4
134 Ditch 135 - +2 0.35 0.08 4
136 Ditch 137 - +5.5 0.4 0.1 1a
138 Ditch 139 71? +2.5 0.9 0.6 1a
140 Pit 141 - +1.9 2.35 0.27 33
142 Ditch 143 - +2.5 0.75 0.18 8 Prehist
144 Ditch 145 - +2.5 0.89 0.26 8 LIA
146 Ditch 147 - 1 0.73 0.26 11
148 Ditch 149 120 +1.9 1 0.23 33
150 Ditch 151 - +1.9 0.89 0.45 11
152 Ditch 153 - 0.8 1.25 0.36 11
154 Ditch 155 - 0.94 1.36 0.45 11 Undiag prehist
156 Ditch 157 - +2 0.83 0.22 11
158 Group - 138, 71 - - - 1a; 5; 6
159 Group - 58 - - - 12; 7
160 Ditch Planned only - - - - 39
161 Group - 106, 65 - - - 10; 11; 33
162 Group - 93, 56 - - - 10; 11; 33
163 Ditch Planned only - - - - 8
164 Group - 120, 148 - - - 11; 33; 7
165 Group - 108 - - - 11; 33; 7
166 Group - - - - - 33; 7
167 Group - 150 - - - 11; 8
168 Group - 152 - - - 11; 33; 8
169 Group - 154 - - - 11; 33
170 Group - 146 - - - 11; 33
171 Group - 123, 69 - - - 5; 38
172 Group - 6, 14 - - - 28,29,34
173 Group - 20 - - - 28, 34
174 Group 1b, 39 Modern
5252
APPENDIX 3: FINDS DATA
All weights are given in grams
Context Feature Count Weight Description Date
7 6 1 1 Pottery; body sherd, sandy orange ware showing
traces of slip-coating or slip-painting
13th to 14th C
9 8 1 2 Iron fragment from sample 1 -
- 22 Slag fragments from sample 1 (magnetic but very
lightweight)
-
24 1 Burnt bone fragments from sample 1 (not possible to
ascertain whether human or animal)
-
- 150 Charcoal fragments, including six carbonised grains,
from sample 1
-
9 26 Pottery; body sherds, inc 5 sherds, 8g, from sample 1
(two may be Roman or may just be burnt)
Late Bronze
Age
23 22 1 - Charcoal (Discarded) -
2 8 Flint flakes -
1 - Pottery; crumb, grey ware Roman
2 6 Pottery; body sherds, flint-tempered Prehistoric
36 24 2 36 Iron nails, with heads -
2 18 Roof tile fragments Post med.
39 25 1 8 Flint flake -
1 4 Clay pipe stem Post med.
2 36 Roof tile fragments Post med.
1 6 Pottery; body sherd PMRE, glazed both sides Later 16th to
19th C
43 42 1 102 Slag -
3 1 Charcoal and coal fragments (discarded) Modern
3 18 Baked clay -
44 42 2 6 Baked clay -
2 14 Roof tile, joining fragments Post med.
57 56 1 10 Pottery; body sherd, grog-tempered ware LIA
1 2 Pottery; body sherd, flint-tempered Early Iron Age
60 58 1 2 Animal bone; sheep/goat molar, badly eroded -
91 519 Pottery; rim, base and body sherds, flint-tempered,
mostly all same vessel
Early Iron Age
72 71 60 46 Pottery; body sherds and crumbs, very friable Early Iron Age
90 89 1 12 Burnt stone (looks modern) -
94 93 1 4 Iron; flat fragment SF1 -
1 2 Tile fragment; fibrous Modern
3 2 Pottery; body sherd, grey ware, abraded (Roman);
two crumbs, flint-tempered (prehistoric)
Various
99 98 5 102 Three flint flakes, one patinated core fragment and
two unworked flints
-
3 6 Pottery; body sherds, flint-tempered Early Iron Age
101 100 9 58 Pottery; body sherds, medieval coarse ware, most
likely from cooking pots
12th to 14th C
109 108 1 6 Pottery; body sherd PMRE, showing a red wash and
traces of glaze, very abraded
Post med.
115 114 1 12 Flint flake, patinated -
117 116 3 20 Two flint flakes and an unworked flint -
5353
4 2 Pottery; crumbs, three are Roman grey ware, one is
prehistoric
Various
119 118 7 44 Flint core fragment, three flakes, two flakelets and an
unworked flint
-
2 4 Pottery; body sherds, medieval coarse ware, abraded 12th to 14th C
121 120 2 6 Pottery; body sherds, flint-tempered Early Iron Age
124 123 1 6 Body sherd with very sparse shell-tempering, similar
fabric at Stansted (Fabric 13i, Walker 2004)
12th to early
13th C
1 2 Pottery; body sherd Prehistoric
143 142 1 6 Burnt flint, grey and white, crazed -
2 1 Pottery; crumbs Prehistoric
145 144 2 1 Charcoal and coal fragments (Discarded) -
1 10 Pottery; body sherd, grog-tempered ware LIA
155 154 1 6 Pottery; body sherd, flint-tempered Prehistoric
5454
APPENDIX 4: ARCHIVE INDEX
SITE NAME: TAPG04
Index to the Archive
File containing:
1. Introduction
1.1 Brief for Evaluation
1.2 Specification for Evaluation
2. Research Archive
2.1 Evaluation Report
2.2 Analytical Reports
2.2.1 Finds Reports
2.3 Finds Catalogues
2.3.1 Context Finds Record
3. Site Archive
3.1 5 x Context Record Register
3.2 Original Context Records 1 to 157
3.2.1 2 x Plans Register
3.2.2 5 x Sections Register
3.3 12 x Levels Register
3.4 6 x Photographic Register
3.5 Site Photographic Record (90 x B+W prints; 90 x Colour Slides)
Not in Files:
Site Drawings ­ 6 A1-size Permatrace section sheets
21 A1-size Permatrace plan sheets
22 A5-size Permatrace plan sheets
1 box of finds
5555
APPENDIX 5: EHCR SUMMARY SHEET
Site Name/Address: Priors Green, Takeley, Essex.
Parish: Takeley District: Uttlesford
NGR: TL 5730 2140 Site Code: TAPG04
Type of Work: Evaluation by Trial Trenching Site Director/Group: A Robertson
ECC Field Archaeology Unit
Date of Work:
29 November 2004 until 17 December 2004
Size of Area Investigated:
Development area c.9.92 ha
Trenching: 40 trenches = 2980m2
(3%)
Location of Finds/Curating Museum:
Saffron Walden
Funding Source: RPS (PTS) on behalf of
Countryside Properties Plc
Further Work Anticipated?
Yes
Related EHCR Nos:
4572; 4655
Final Report: N.A.
Periods Represented: Prehistoric Medieval Post-medieval Modern
SUMMARY OF FIELDWORK RESULTS:
An archaeological evaluation, covering c.9.9 hectares, was carried out on the site of proposed housing
development at Priors Green, Takeley. Forty trenches were opened, covering 2980 sq m (c.3%). The majority of
features uncovered were ditches and gullies with only a few pits and post-holes scattered across the site.
Prehistoric
In the western third of the site three parallel Early Iron Age ditches running northwest-southeast were identified,
long with fragments of further ditches which seem to run northeast-southwest. Tthese possibly form a co-axial
field system. The other prehistoric features identified include a possible ring ditch/gully enclosure and a possible
cremation burial at the eastern end of the site.
Medieval
<Node id="80421"/>No Roman remains were identified<Node id="80453"/> but a handful of medieval ditches and pits were, mostly in the eastern third of
the site. In the southeast corner the possible remains of a small medieval enclosure were investigated but no
definite conclusions were reached.
Post Medieval
A number of post-medieval ditches, including at least nine parallel, north-south aligned ditches, in the southwest
corner of the site were investigated. Several of the post-medieval ditches correspond to field boundaries marked
on the 1874 1st edition O.S. map. The parallel ditches are probably the remains of a strip field system and are
perpendicular to the present Dunmow Road and parallel to existing field boundaries.
A large possible boundary ditch running approximately east ­ west across the centre of the western third of the
site may be geological in origin as the evidence from the excavated sections is inconclusive.
5656
In general all the features seem to be agricultural in nature and <Node id="81394"/>none produced significant quantities of finds
indicative of settlement activity<Node id="81473"/>, of any period, in close proximity. However, evidence of the prehistoric exploitation
and development of the Essex boulder clay is of significance, as it is traditionally considered as less agriculturally
viable land.
Previous Summaries/Reports: N.A.
Author of Summary:
A. Robertson (ECC FAU)
Date of Summary:
January 2005
<Node id="81797"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="2" Type="Negation" StartNode="3560" EndNode="3642">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="17288" EndNode="17389">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="5" Type="Negation" StartNode="18560" EndNode="18651">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="18653" EndNode="18753">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="7" Type="Negation" StartNode="21737" EndNode="21854">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="8" Type="Negation" StartNode="24980" EndNode="25032">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="9" Type="Negation" StartNode="27492" EndNode="27533">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="10" Type="Negation" StartNode="27535" EndNode="27584">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="11" Type="Negation" StartNode="28597" EndNode="28669">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="12" Type="Negation" StartNode="28671" EndNode="28739">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="13" Type="Negation" StartNode="30283" EndNode="30357">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="14" Type="Negation" StartNode="34389" EndNode="34495">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="15" Type="Negation" StartNode="35029" EndNode="35139">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="17" Type="Negation" StartNode="40675" EndNode="40727">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="16" Type="Negation" StartNode="39378" EndNode="39470">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="19" Type="Negation" StartNode="43961" EndNode="44055">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="18" Type="Negation" StartNode="42350" EndNode="42412">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="21" Type="Negation" StartNode="46225" EndNode="46287">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="20" Type="Negation" StartNode="45801" EndNode="45874">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="23" Type="Negation" StartNode="48054" EndNode="48120">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="22" Type="Negation" StartNode="46811" EndNode="46878">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="25" Type="Negation" StartNode="49319" EndNode="49366">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="24" Type="Negation" StartNode="48620" EndNode="48667">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="27" Type="Negation" StartNode="53426" EndNode="53525">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="26" Type="Negation" StartNode="52728" EndNode="52817">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="29" Type="Negation" StartNode="54624" EndNode="54699">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="28" Type="Negation" StartNode="54360" EndNode="54441">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="31" Type="Negation" StartNode="80421" EndNode="80453">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="30" Type="Negation" StartNode="55221" EndNode="55294">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="34" Type="Negation" StartNode="28116" EndNode="28168">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="35" Type="Negation" StartNode="49132" EndNode="49210">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="32" Type="Negation" StartNode="50882" EndNode="50945">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="33" Type="Negation" StartNode="4528" EndNode="4615">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="38" Type="Negation" StartNode="46484" EndNode="46555">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="39" Type="Negation" StartNode="45368" EndNode="45458">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="36" Type="Negation" StartNode="81394" EndNode="81473">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="37" Type="Negation" StartNode="45232" EndNode="45281">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="81797">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
