<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/foundati1-5205.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
LAND OFF BODIAM AVENUE, GLOUCESTER, 
GLOUCESTERSHIRE
NGR: SO 8155 1476
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION
February 2003
Andrew Hood BSc. (Hons.)
SITE CODE: BAG03ex
Report No. 297
June 2003
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
This report has been compiled with all reasonable skill, care and attention to detail within the terms of the 
project as specified by the client and within the general terms and conditions of Archaeological 
Management Services Ltd trading as Foundations Archaeology. This report is confidential to the client. 
AMS Ltd accepts no responsibility whatsoever to third parties to whom this report or any part thereof is 
made known. Any such party relies on this report at their own risk.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
CONTENTS
Summary
Glossary of Archaeological Terms and Abbreviations
1 INTRODUCTION
2 ARCHAEOLOGICAL PROJECT BACKGROUND
3 AIMS
4 METHODOLOGY
5 NATURE OF THE RECORD
6 RESULTS
7 DISCUSSION
8 CONCLUSIONS
9 BIBLIOGRAPHY
10 ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
11 APPENDIX 1 ­ POTTERY REPORT
12 APPENDIX 2 ­ HUMAN BONE REPORT
LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS
Figure 1 Site Location Map
Figure 2 Trench Location Map
Figure 3 Trench 1 Plan and Sections
Figure 4 Trench 2 Plan and Sections
Figure 5 Trenches 3, 4 and 5 Plans and Sections
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
SUMMARY
In January 2003 Foundations Archaeology was commissioned by John Samuels 
Archaeological Consultants to undertake an archaeological excavation on land off 
Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester (centred at NGR: SO 8155 1476). The fieldwork was 
undertaken during Feburary 2003.
A programme of archaeogeophysical survey combined with archaeological field 
recording and evaluation, undertaken between 1998 and 2002, revealed the presence of a 
substantial RomanoBritish boundary ditch situated adjacent to the A38, which is 
possibly associated with the Olympus Park villa complex. An archaeological excavation 
was subsequently required in order to preserve the feature by record.
The current programme of works comprised the excavation and recording of five 
trenches, 20m long by 2m wide, across the projected location of the RomanoBritish 
ditch.
 
The excavation revealed numerous undated and truncated linear ditches, a complex of 
eastwest aligned, undated linear ditches and an undated and truncated northsouth 
aligned adult inhumation. <Node id="2835"/>No artefacts were associated with the inhumation<Node id="2883"/>. 
<Node id="2886"/>Limited evidence of RomanoBritish activity was provided by pottery sherds dating to 
this period occurring in the subsoil<Node id="3007"/>.
Truncation of features across the site indicates a high level of plough damage in and 
around the investigated area. 
The excavation failed to locate, date and define the previously identified RomanoBritish 
ditch.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
GLOSSARY OF ARCHAEOLOGICAL TERMS AND ABBREVIATIONS
Archaeology
For the purposes of this project archaeology is taken to mean the study of past human 
societies through their material remains from prehistoric times to the modern era. <Node id="3646"/>No 
rigid upper date limit has been set<Node id="3685"/>, but AD 1900 is used as a general cutoff point.
CBM
Ceramic Building Material.
Medieval
The period between the Norman Conquest (AD 1066) and c AD 1500.
Natural
In archaeological terms this refers to the undisturbed natural geology of a site. 
NGR
National Grid Reference from the Ordnance Survey Grid.
OD
Ordnance Datum; used to express a given height above sealevel.
OS
Ordnance Survey.
RomanoBritish
The period between AD 43 c AD 410.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
1 INTRODUCTION
1.1 Between 1998 and 2002 a programme of archaeogeophysical prospection 
combined with archaeological field recording and evaluation revealed the 
presence of a substantial RomanoBritish boundary ditch situated adjacent to the 
A38, which is possibly associated with the Olympus Park villa complex (Bartlett 
1998, Cotton 1998, OAU 1998 Nichols 2002).
 
1.2 In February 2003 a programme of archaeological excavation, centred on the 
RomanoBritish ditch, was undertaken. The excavation comprised five trenches, 
20m long by 2m wide (total = 200m2
). 
1.3 The archaeological works were undertaken in response to a proposal to construct 
residential housing on the site (planning applications 98/00212/OUT, 
91/1160/OUT and 91/1161/OUT). The excavation was undertaken in accordance 
with a Specification prepared by John Samuels Archaeological Consultants 
(2002). The Specification was prepared in accordance with IFA Standards and 
Guidance on Archaeological Excavation (1994, revised 2001), and approved by 
the Local Planning Authority's nominated archaeologist. The programme of 
archaeological works was undertaken in accordance with the principles of 
Planning Policy Guidance note 16, Archaeology and Planning (DoE 1990). 
1.4 This document provides an assessment of the evidence recovered during the 
excavation. This document conforms to the specification set out in Appendices 4 
and 5 of The Management of Archaeological Projects (English Heritage 1991).
2 ARCHAEOLOGICAL AND PROJECT BACKGROUND
2.1 The site lies within the parish of Quedgeley, located immediately to the west of 
Bodiam Avenue and to the east of the A38. The total study area is 11.3ha, of 
which Area A is 9.1ha (figure 2). The site is centred at NGR SO 8155 1476 and 
lies geologically on lower lias clays overlain by areas of River Severn gravels at a 
height of 1520m OD. Current land use is rough grassland. The development 
proposal consists of the construction of residential housing across the area. The 
planning application for Area A includes proposals for a corridor of Public Open 
Space at the east end of the site and noise mitigation measures along the western 
edge. These areas w not be disturbed by the proposed development.
2.2 A full deskbased archaeological assessment was undertaken by Oxford 
Archaeology Unit (1998) and should be read in conjunction with this report. 
2.3 An evaluation undertaken on the site by Oxford Archaeology Unit in 1998 
involved the excavation of 31 trenches. A substantial RomanoBritish ditch, cut 
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
into the natural clay, occurred in three of the trenches, at the western edge of Area 
A, adjacent to the A38. This feature measured approximately 3.30m4.50m wide 
and extended to a maximum depth of 1.42m. Its full extent and nature could not 
be determined within the limitations imposed by the programme of evaluation. 
3 AIMS 
3.1 The aims of the archaeological excavation were to preserve, by record, remains of 
archaeological interest.
3.2 These aims were achieved through pursuit of the following specific objectives:
i) to define and identify the nature of archaeological deposits on site, and date 
these where possible.
ii) to attempt to characterise the nature of the archaeological sequence.
iii) to recover coherent artefact, and where appropriate, ecofact and environmental 
samples. 
4 METHODOLOGY
4.1 Five trenches measuring 20m long by 2m wide, located along the projected route 
of the RomanoBritish ditch, were excavated (Figure 2). The excavation was 
undertaken using a mechanical excavator fitted with a toothless, grading bucket, 
under constant archaeological supervision. 
4.2 Deposits of nonsignificant overburden were removed to the top of archaeological 
deposits or underlying natural, whichever was encountered first. Thereafter 
cleaning and excavation was conducted by hand. The spoil tip was scanned for 
finds. 
4.3 <Node id="8394"/>No suitable contexts for environmental sampling were identified<Node id="8457"/> during the course 
of the excavation.
4.4 All site recording was undertaken in accordance with Foundations Archaeology 
Technical Manual 3 (Excavation Manual). A written, drawn and photographic 
record of the excavation was compiled in accordance with the specification.
5 NATURE OF THE RECORD
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
5.1 The stratigraphic archive for the site consists of the following elements:
Context Sheets
Record Sheets
Plans
Sections/Elevations
Black White photos
Colour slides
5.2 Following the completion of the excavation an ordered, indexed, and internally 
consistent site archive was compiled in accordance with Appendix 3 of The 
Management of Archaeological Projects (English Heritage 1991). 
6 RESULTS
6.1 The stratigraphic sequence was essentially uniform throughout and consisted of 
yellow/grey silty clay alluvial deposits sealed beneath approximately 
0.15m0.40m of light brown clay silt subsoil. The subsoil was itself sealed 
beneath approximately 0.16m0.30m of mid brown humic topsoil.
6.2 Trench 1 was orientated northnorthwest/southsoutheast and was excavated 
onto yellow/grey silty clay alluvium at an average depth of 0.46m (15.88m OD) 
from the modern ground surface. The alluvial deposits were sealed beneath a sub 
soil layer of light brown silty clay (102) 0.18m0.30m thick. This context 
contained occasional small and abraded sherds of RomanoBritish pottery and 
CBM. Overlying layer (102), context (101) consisted of a mid brown humic clay 
topsoil 0.20m0.25m thick. A land drain, aligned northwest/southeast occurred 
at the north end of the trench. Six features [115], [103], [113], [111], [108] and 
[106] were present within the trench.
6.3 Feature [115] was a shallow profile, `U' shaped linear cut aligned north
west/southeast, up to 0.22m deep by 0.80m wide. It was cut into the alluvial 
deposits and sealed beneath layer (102). The southeast end of this feature was 
extremely ephemeral in appearance. Cut [115] contained f (116), 0.22m thick, 
which consisted of a mid orange/brown, silty clay containing occasional charcoal 
flecks. <Node id="10703"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this context<Node id="10754"/>. 
6.4 Cut into [115] and sealed by layer (102), gravecut [103] comprised a suboval 
shaped pit, 1.54m long, 0.54m wide and up to 0.05m deep, aligned approximately 
northsouth. Feature [103] contained context (105); a northsouth aligned 
incomplete adult inhumation, situated in the supine position and context (104), 
0.05m thick, a dark brown, compact, siltyclay backfill. <Node id="11129"/>No artefacts or coffin 
remnants were associated with either of these contexts<Node id="11207"/>. After consultation with the 
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
County Archaeologist, the human remains were removed prior to destruction by 
the proposed development (Burial Act 1857, Section 25. Licence No. 28365).
6.5 Feature [113] was a shallow profile, irregular based `U' shaped linear cut aligned 
northeast/southwest, up to 0.29m deep by 1.80m wide. It was cut into the 
alluvial deposits and sealed beneath layer (102). The cut contained f (114), 
0.29m thick, which consisted of a mid grey/brown silty clay, containing 
occasional charcoal flecks and occasional CBM fragments. <Node id="11950"/>No dating evidence 
was recovered from this context<Node id="12001"/>.
6.6 Feature [111] was an ephemeral `U' shaped linear cut aligned approximately east/
west, up to 0.35m deep by 0.50m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits and 
sealed beneath layer (102). The cut contained f (112), 0.35m thick, which 
consisted of a mid grey/orange clay sand. This f was homogeneous throughout. 
Limited root disturbance occurred at the interface between contexts (112) and 
(102). <Node id="12408"/>No artefactual evidence or other anthropogenic indicators were recovered 
from context<Node id="12494"/> (112).
6.7 Feature [108] was a shallow `U' shaped linear cut aligned approximately 
east/west, up to 0.36m deep by 1.80m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits 
and sealed beneath layer (102). The cut contained f (109), 0.03m thick, which 
consisted of a dark grey/black silty clay lens with occasional organic component. 
<Node id="12823"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this primary context<Node id="12882"/>. Overlying lens 
(109), context (110), 0.33m thick, formed the secondary f of the cut and 
consisted of a mid grey/orange silty clay containing occasional manganese flecks. 
<Node id="13057"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this context<Node id="13108"/>. 
6.8 Cut into [108] and the alluvial deposits, [106] was sealed beneath layer (102). 
This feature comprised a steep sided `U' shaped linear cut aligned approximately 
east/west, up to 0.38m deep by 1.80m wide. Cut [106] contained context (107), 
0.38m thick, which consisted of a mid orange/brown silty clay containing 
occasional/rare charcoal and CBM flecks. <Node id="13472"/>No dating evidence was recovered from 
this context<Node id="13523"/>.
6.9 Trench 2 was orientated northnorthwest/southsoutheast and was excavated 
onto yellow/grey silty clay alluvium at an average depth of 0.49m (15.45m OD) 
from the modern ground surface. The alluvial deposits were sealed beneath a sub 
soil layer of mid brown silty clay (202) 0.15m0.28m thick. This context 
contained occasional small and abraded sherds of RomanoBritish pottery. 
Overlying layer (202), context (201) consisted of a mid brown humic clay topsoil 
0.23m0.30m thick, containing occasional CBM. A land drain, aligned north
west/southeast occurred at the south end of the trench. Two linear features [203] 
and [205] were present within the trench.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
6.10 Feature [203] was a irregularly based `U' shaped linear cut aligned approximately 
east/west, up to 0.44m deep by 2.10m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits 
and sealed beneath layer (202). This feature occurred at the north end of the 
trench. The cut contained f (204), 0.44m thick, which consisted of a mid brown 
silty clay. <Node id="14718"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this context and root 
disturbance was visible throughout<Node id="14814"/>.
6.11 Feature [205] was a flat based, shallow profile linear cut aligned approximately 
east/west, up to 0.10m deep by 1.30m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits 
and sealed beneath layer (202). This feature occurred at the south end of the 
trench and was cut by an archaeological evaluation trench (previous evaluation). 
The cut contained f (206), 0.10m thick, which consisted of a mid brown, 
compact silty clay. <Node id="15239"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this context<Node id="15290"/>.
6.12 Trench 3 was orientated north/south and was excavated onto yellow/grey silty 
clay alluvium at an average depth of 0.49m (15.26m OD) from the modern 
ground surface. The alluvial deposits were sealed beneath a sub soil layer of light 
brown silty clay (302) 0.20m0.28m thick. This context contained occasional 
CBM fragments. Overlying layer (302), context (301) consisted of a mid brown 
humic clay topsoil 0.20m0.30m thick. A land drain, aligned northwest/south
east occurred at the south end of the trench. A single linear feature [303] was 
present within the trench.
6.13 Feature [303] was a flat based, shallow profile linear cut aligned northeast/south
west, up to 0.09m deep by 0.59m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits and 
sealed beneath layer (302). This feature occurred at the north end of the trench. 
The cut contained f (304), 0.09m thick, which consisted of a light brown, plastic 
silty clay. A single RomanoBritish Dorset Black Burnished Ware pottery sherd 
and two CBM fragments were recovered from this fill.
6.14 Trench 4 was orientated north/south and was excavated onto yellow/grey silty 
clay alluvium at an average depth of 0.35m (14.98m OD) from the modern 
ground surface. The alluvial deposits were sealed beneath a sub soil layer of light 
brown silty clay (402) 0.10m0.28m thick. Overlying layer (402), context (401) 
consisted of a mid brown humic clay topsoil 0.16m0.20m thick. A land drain, 
aligned northwest/southeast occurred at the south end of the trench. A single 
linear feature [403] was present within the trench.
6.15 Feature [403] was a shallow profile linear cut aligned northeast/southwest, up to 
0.06m deep by 0.81m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits and sealed 
beneath layer (402). This feature occurred at the north end of the trench. The cut 
contained f (404), 0.06m thick, which consisted of a mid brown, mottled, sandy 
clay. A single small and abraded pottery sherd datable to the RomanoBritish 
period was recovered from this fill.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
6.16 Trench 5 was orientated northeast/southwest and was excavated onto yellow 
silty clay alluvium at an average depth of 0.54m (14.67m OD) from the modern 
ground surface. The alluvial deposits were sealed beneath a sub soil layer of light 
brown silty clay (502) 0.23m0.40m thick. This context contained occasional 
CBM fragments. Overlying layer (502), context (501) consisted of a mid brown 
humic clay topsoil 0.20m0.25m thick. An area of natural clay banding occurred 
at the south end of the trench. A single linear feature [503] was present within the 
trench.
6.17 Feature [503] was a shallow profile, `V' shaped linear cut aligned east/west, up to 
0.08m deep by 0.50m wide. It was cut into the alluvial deposits and sealed 
beneath layer (502). This feature occurred at the south end of the trench. The cut 
contained f (504), 0.08m thick, which consisted of a mid/light brown, silty clay. 
<Node id="18396"/>No artefactual data was recovered from this context<Node id="18447"/>. Limited root disturbance was 
visible throughout.
7 DISCUSSION
7.1 Linear features [113], [115], [205], [303], [403], [503] and grave cut [103] were 
extremely ephemeral and are indicative of plough truncation/disturbance 
occurring across the investigated area.
7.2 Contexts (304) and (404) both contained pottery sherds datable to the Romano
British period. Due to the ephemeral and truncated nature of cuts [303] and [403] 
and the abraded appearance of the pottery, this dating evidence may be 
residual/intrusive. 
7.3 In general, no features yielded securely stratified dating evidence.
7.4 Limited evidence of RomanoBritish activity in the area was provided by pottery 
sherds dating to this period occurring in subsoils (102) and (202).
7.5 Inhumation (105) was sealed beneath subsoil layer (102) which contained 
occasional RomanoBritish pottery sherds. Artefacts occurring in the subsoil 
horizon are, however, likely to be out of their primary contexts and therefore 
context (102) does not provide a chronologically secure terminusantequem.
7.6 Features [111], [108], [106] and [113] formed a complex of linear cuts which 
were spatially approximate and shared a similar eastwest alignment. This 
possibly represents plough marks or remnant ridge and furrow. No dating 
evidence was, however, recovered from any of these features. Only [106] and 
[108] were stratigraphically related.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
8 CONCLUSIONS
8.1 None of the excavated features yielded section profiles, maximum depths or f 
sequences comparable to those excavated in the initial site evaluation (OAU 1998, 
Fig 5: Trench 9; Section 15, Trench 10; Section 16).
8.2 Due to the lack of f descriptions (Colour, Texture, Consistency, Course 
Component) in the initial evaluation report (OAU 1998) it is not possible to 
compare these excavated components.
8.3 <Node id="20462"/>None of the excavated features yielded securely stratified RomanoBritish dating 
evidence<Node id="20551"/>.
 
8.4 The occurrence of a previous evaluation trench in Trench 2 indicates a 
discrepancy in the survey techniques utilised between the evaluation and 
subsequent excavation. 
8.5 The excavation failed to confirm and record the location, date, nature and 
anticipated extent of the previously identified RomanoBritish ditch. 
8.6 A single, incomplete adult inhumation (105) is undated.
9 BIBLIOGRAPHY
Bartlett, A. 1998. Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Report on Archaeogeophysical 
Survey. BartlettClark Consultancy. 
 
Brayne, K. (ed.) 2003. BAG03: A Report on One Skeleton. The Rudyard 
Consultancy.
Cotton, J. 1998. Archaeological Observations of Geotechnical Works off Bodiam 
Avenue, Quedgeley, Gloucester. AC Archaeology.
Institute of Field Archaeologists 1999 Standard Guidance for Archaeological 
Excavation
JSAC. 2002. A Specification for Archaeological Excavation on Land off Bodiam 
Avenue, Glouscester. John Samuels Archaeological Consultants.
 
Nichols, P. 2002. An Archaeological Evaluation on land off Bodiam Avenue, 
Quedgeley, Gloucester. Gloucester County Council Archaeology Service.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
OAU. 1998. Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Evaluation Report. 
Oxford Archaeological Unit.
10 ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
Foundations Archaeology would like to thank Kate Brayne and Sharon Clough of 
The Rudyard Consultancy, Phil Greatarex of Gloucester City Archaeology Unit 
and Jenny Young of John Samuels Archaeological Consultants.
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
11 APPENDIX 1 ­ POTTERY REPORT
SITE: BAG
The archaeological work resulted in the recovery of four very small sherds of pottery 
weighing 13g and at least one, possibly two, abraded fragments of ceramic building 
material (cbm). The assemblage was recovered from three contexts. The fragments are in 
extremely poor condition and are probably redeposited. As far as could ascertained they 
appear to date to the Roman period with at least one sherd of Dorset black burnished 
ware from (304). The single fragment from (104) could be pot or cbm and dating is not 
possible.
J R Timby
March 2003
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
Land off Bodiam Avenue, Gloucester: Archaeological Excavation
12 APPENDIX 2 ­ HUMAN BONE REPORT
© Foundations Archaeology BAG03ex
109 Albion Street, Swindon, Wilts SN15LP
Tel/Fax 08700 780 555 Email admin@foundations.co.uk
<Node id="23308"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="17" Type="Negation" StartNode="2835" EndNode="2883">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="19" Type="Negation" StartNode="3646" EndNode="3685">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="18" Type="Negation" StartNode="2886" EndNode="3007">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="21" Type="Negation" StartNode="10703" EndNode="10754">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="20" Type="Negation" StartNode="8394" EndNode="8457">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="23" Type="Negation" StartNode="11950" EndNode="12001">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="22" Type="Negation" StartNode="11129" EndNode="11207">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="25" Type="Negation" StartNode="12823" EndNode="12882">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="24" Type="Negation" StartNode="12408" EndNode="12494">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="27" Type="Negation" StartNode="13472" EndNode="13523">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="26" Type="Negation" StartNode="13057" EndNode="13108">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="29" Type="Negation" StartNode="15239" EndNode="15290">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="28" Type="Negation" StartNode="14718" EndNode="14814">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="31" Type="Negation" StartNode="20462" EndNode="20551">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="30" Type="Negation" StartNode="18396" EndNode="18447">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="23308">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
