<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/heritage1-11948.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>IFA
RE
G IS ER
E
T
D
RO
ON
NA
A
I
I
G
ST
HERITAGE NETWORKHERITAGE NETWORK
1 BELL STREET
Feltwell, Norfolk
Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525
THETHE HERITAGE NETWORKHERITAGE NETWORK LTDLTD
Registered with the Institute of Field Archaeologists as an Archaeological Organisation
Archaeological Director: David Hillelson, BA MIFA
11 F11 FURMSTONURMSTON CCOURTOURT, I, ICKNIELDCKNIELD WWAYAY, L, LETCHWORTHETCHWORTH SG6 1UJSG6 1UJ
TTELEPHONEELEPHONE: (01462) 685991 F: (01462) 685991 FAXAX: (01462) 685998: (01462) 685998
1 BELL STREET
Feltwell, Norfolk
Project Ref.: HN525
HER Ref.: 41934 FWL
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared on behalf of John Leamon, Esq
by
Geoff Saunders, BA
Report No.298
June 2005
(Revised August 2005)
© The Heritage Network Ltd
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page i
Contents
Summary........................................................................................................................................................Page i
Section 1 Introduction .................................................................................................................................................Page 1
Section 2 Fieldwork......................................................................................................................................................Page 2
Section 3 Discussion.................................................................................................................................................Page 10
Section 4 Sources Consulted.................................................................................................................................. Page 12
Section 5 Illustrations.............................................................................................................................following Page 12
The cover photograph shows Bell Street, looking west (from an undated postcard provided by Mr C. Cock ­ www.feltwell.org.uk)
Acknowledgements
The fieldwork for this project was carried out by Abigail Rothwell and Geoff Saunders, and the finds assessment
was undertaken by Helen Ashworth. The report was written and illustrated by Geoff Saunders, and edited by David
Hillelson.
The Heritage Network would like to express its thanks to John Leaman, P J Commercials; Kazimierz
Swierdzewski, Ski Property Management; Jan Allen, Norfolk HER and Andy Hutcheson, Senior Archaeologist,
Norfolk Landscape Archaeology, for their co-operation and assistance in the execution of this project.
Summary
Site name and address: 1 Bell Street, Feltwell, Norfolk
County: Norfolk District: Kings Lynn West Norfolk
Village/town: Feltwell Parish: Feltwell
Planning reference: 04/1743/O NGR: TL 715 907
Client name and address: John Leaman Esq., c/o Ski Property Management, 9 Park View, Weeting,
Brandon, Suffolk.
Nature of work: New dwellings Present land use: Commercial and Domestic
Size of affected area: c.665m2
Size of area investigated: c.32m2
Site Code: HN525 HER reference: 41934 FWL
Organisation: Heritage Network Site Director: David Hillelson
Type of work: Evaluation Archive location: Norfolk Museums Service
Start of work 26th
May 2005 Finish of work 27th
May 2005
Related SMR Nos.: N/a Periods represented: R-B, Medieval, Modern
Previous summaries/reports: N/a
Synopsis:
In order to determine the archaeological risk posed by a proposal to construct three new dwellings at 1 Bell Street,
Feltwell, the Heritage Network was commissioned by the developers to undertake a programme of archaeological
evaluation.
Two trenches were excavated measuring c.4.0 x 4.4m and 3.4 x 4.3m respectively. A series of boundary or
drainage ditches of Romano-British date were revealed in Trench 1. In Trench 2 the foundations of a 19th
century
structure, probably that depicted on the Tithe map of 1837, were revealed.
<Node id="3867"/>Although no direct evidence for pre-19th
century occupation on the site was revealed<Node id="3951"/>, the presence of a significant
amount of heavily abraded Romano-British CBM in the drainage ditches suggests the presence of at least one
substantial structure of this period in the vicinity. This may be associated with the villa located 215m to the NE, or
the late Roman occupation identified c. 115m to the N.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 1
1. Introduction
1.1 This report has been prepared at the request of Ski Property Management, acting on
behalf of John Leamon Esq, as part of the archaeological evaluation of a proposed
development site located at 1 Bell Street, Feltwell, Norfolk. Planning permission granted for
the development by the Borough Council of Kings Lynn and West Norfolk (KLBC) under
application no. 04/1743/O, has been subject to a standard archaeological condition, in
accordance with the provisions of the DETR's Planning Policy Guidance Note 16 (PPG16).
The scope of the required work followed the Brief for Archaeological Evaluation by Trial
Trenching issued by Norfolk Landscape Archaeology (NLA), acting as advisers to KLBC (ref.
AH 13/12/2004). A full specification for the work carried out was contained in the Heritage
Network's approved Project Design dated April 2005.
1.2 The site is located between Bell Street and The Beck, immediately to the east of the
parish church of St Mary's, centred on NGR TL 715 907 (see Figure 1). The present
application proposes the construction of new dwellings in three plots, the development of the
remainder of the site being currently underway, having been covered by a separate planning
application (see Figure 2).
1.3 The site lies within the historic core of Feltwell and it is considered that the adjacent
churchyard could have extended across the study area in earlier times. It is also possible that
the remains of buildings formerly existing along the Bell Street frontage could be of
archaeological interest with the potential to provide information on the medieval development
of the village.
1.4 The aim of the evaluation has been to consider the location, extent, date, character,
condition, significance and quality of any remains that are liable to be threatened by the
development, and to provide a local and regional, archaeological and historical context for
them, in accordance with the current published regional research agenda (Glazebrook 1997,
Brown and Glazebrook 2000), if they were discovered. The project is considered to have the
potential to contribute specifically to the study of settlement morphology during the medieval
and post-medieval periods.
1.5 The present report has been prepared in order to provide the planning authority with
sufficient data to allow it to consider the archaeological implications of the proposed
development, and to determine what further mitigation measures, if any, may be required.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 2
2. Fieldwork
TOPOGRAPHY AND GEOLOGY
2.1 The site comprises a narrow strip of land between Bell Street and The Beck, currently
occupied by both domestic and commercial structures. The ground level falls gradually across
the site from 8.09mOD on the Bell Street frontage to 6.02mOD on The Beck.
2.2 The underlying geology of the area consists of chalk.
ARCHAEOLOGICAL BACKGROUND
2.3 The study area is located within a well-documented archaeological landscape. The
County Sites and Monuments Record (SMR) has recorded finds of prehistoric, Roman and
medieval date from within a 500m radius of the present site.
2.4 Only limited evidence of prehistoric date has been recorded from the vicinity of the
site. A number of flint blades of late Neolithic date (SMR 24142) were found in 1987 in the
garden of 14 H Street, approximately 180m to the west. A Bronze Age pit was revealed
during excavations on the site of the Roman bath house (SMR 4921) approximately 215m to
the NNE.
2.5 Considerable evidence for Roman occupation has been identified in the immediate
vicinity of the study area. Excavations at Glebe Farm in the 1960s found part of a Roman villa
and associated bath house (SMR 4921) approximately 215m to the NNE. An archaeological
evaluation took place to the rear of The Old School, The Beck (SMR 40913) approximately
115m to the north of the present site. in October and November, 2004. This work revealed
numerous archaeological features, principally pits and ditches, though the remains of 3 walls
were also recorded. The finds dated to the 3rd
/4th
centuries AD suggesting that this site was
contemporary with the villa at Glebe Farm. Roman pottery sherds, including grey wares and
Nene Valley colour-coated wares, was also found during landscaping works approximately
280m to the northeast (SMR 16271).
2.6 The present site is located in the core of the medieval village, immediately adjacent to
St Mary's Church, which lies approximately 50m to the west (SMR 4940) and close to St
Nicholas' Church (SMR 4939) approximately 320m to the northwest. Scattered finds of
medieval date have been recorded from the immediate vicinity, including a Nuremburg jetton
(SMR 33451) approximately 270m to the northeast; medieval pottery from a nearby garden
(SMR 35256) approximately 230m to the south and an unusual Middle Saxon pin shaft (SMR
28788) approximately 480m to the northwest.
2.7 A number of undated human remains have also been recorded from the vicinity of the
study area. In 1969 several skeletons were dug up in a garden close to St Nicholas' Church
(SMR 4930) approximately 310m to the northwest. Other skeletons have been found at Manor
Farm (SMR 4931) approximately 420m to the northwest and a single inhumation was found
to the south of Bell Street, (SMR 4929) approximately 135m to the west.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 3
2.8 The Tithe Map of 1837 shows that the Bell Street frontage was built up at that time, but
the Beck frontage was open ground or garden.
2.9 The first edition Ordnance Survey of 1888 shows that the Bell Street frontage remained
built up, and the hall which occupies the eastern half of the present Beck frontage had been
built by that time.
METHODOLOGY
2.10 All work was carried out in accordance with the approved Project Design, current
health and safety legislation, and IFA standards.
2.11 The trenches were located by triangulation from known points using fibreglass tape
measures.
2.12 Two trenches were opened using a tracked mini-digger fitted with a 1.3m wide
toothless bucket, under close archaeological supervision (see Figure 2). Spoil from the
machining was inspected for archaeological artefacts. Trenches were machined to the first
significant archaeological horizon.
2.13 The trenches were cleaned by hand, and all potential archaeological features and
deposits were sampled to ascertain their nature, depth, date, and quality of preservation.
2.14 All identified contexts were photographed and recorded using the appropriate pro-
forma. Scaled plans and sections were drawn on drafting film at scales of 1:10 and 1:50.
RESULTS
Trench 1 (see Figure 3)
2.15 Trench 1 was located on The Beck frontage in the northern half of the site and was
aligned approximately north-west to south-east. The trench measured 4.0 x 4.4m and was
excavated to a maximum depth of 1.40m.
2.16 The stratigraphy in this trench consisted of three layers above the natural geology. A
layer of loose, dark brown (10YR 3/3), silty clay topsoil lay over a firm, dark yellowish
brown (10YR 3/4), silty clay subsoil. Beneath this a layer of firm, light grey (10YR 7/1),
waterborne silt (108) was observed over the natural chalk geology.
2.17 The trench contained two service trenches for a live water main and sewer pipe
respectively. The presence of these services limited the area in the trench in which the full
depth of overburden could be removed.
2.18 Linear feature [101] was observed cutting into the natural chalk, orientated N ­ S
towards the south-east half of the trench. This feature was greater than 0.70m wide and
approximately 0.29m deep, with steep straight sides and a narrow but flat base. <Node id="12084"/>The primary
plastic, grey, chalky clay f (102) yielded no datable artefacts<Node id="12159"/>. The secondary plastic, dark
grey, silty clay f (103) yielded a fragment of opus signinum, several fragments of Romano-
British CBM, and medieval peg tile. The feature may represent a boundary or drainage ditch,
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 4
the abraded and fragmentary nature of the material recovered suggests it may have been
bought onto the site by water flowing along the ditch.
2.19 Linear feature [104] was observed cut into the natural chalk, orientated NE ­ SW
across centre of the trench. The feature was 0.85m wide and approximately 0.65m deep, with
steep very slightly convex sides and a flat base. The solitary firm plastic, dark grey, slightly
silty clay f yielded a single small, abraded, fragment of Romano-British pottery, along with
several heavily abraded fragments of potentially Romano-British CBM. Several fragments of
mussel shell were also observed but were not retrievable due to their very fragmentary nature.
The feature may represent a boundary or drainage ditch, the abraded and fragmentary nature
of the material recovered suggests it may have been bought onto the site by water flowing
along the ditch. This feature has a junction with ditch [101], it was not possible to establish a
stratigraphic relationship between the two features due to the similarity of the fills.
2.20 Linear feature [106] was observed cut into the natural chalk, orientated NE ­ SW
across the north-west half of the trench. The feature was greater in width than 0.65m and
approximately 0.40m deep, with a steep concave south-east side and a steep north-west side
with one step. The base of the feature was slightly rounded. The solitary plastic, greyish
brown, silty clay f yielded a fragment of opus signinum, and Romano-British CBM. The
feature may represent a boundary or drainage ditch, the abraded and fragmentary nature of the
material recovered suggesting that it may have been bought onto the site by water flowing
along the ditch.
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
101 Cut Linear cut feature with a steep straight sides and a narrow
flat base, aligned N to S. Boundary or drainage ditch.
Length: 1.53m+
Width: 0.70m
Depth: 0.29m
102 F Plastic, grey (2.5Y 5/1), chalky clay with very occasional
small stones. Primary f of [101].
Length: 1.53m+
Width: 0.70m
Depth: 0.16m
103 F Plastic, dark grey (2.5Y 4/1), silty clay with very
occasional large stones. Secondary f of [101].
Length: 1.53m+
Width: 0.70m
Depth: 0.13m
104 Cut Linear cut feature with steep very slightly convex sides
and a flat base, aligned NE ­ SW. Boundary or drainage
ditch.
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.85m
Depth: 0.65m
105 F Firm plastic, dark grey (2.5Y 4/1), slightly silty clay with
frequent chalk and charcoal flecks and moderate small
sub-rounded stones. F of [104].
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.85m
Depth: 0.65m
106 Cut Linear cut feature with a steep slightly concave SE side
and a steep NW side with one step. Slightly rounded base,
aligned NE ­ SW. Boundary or drainage ditch.
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.65m+
Depth: 0.40m
107 F Plastic, greyish brown (2.5Y 5/2), silty clay with frequent
chalk and charcoal flecks and moderate large stones and
flints. F of [106].
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.65m+
Depth: 0.40m
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 5
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
108 Layer/
deposit
Firm, light grey (10YR 7/1), waterborne silt. Deposit
which sits over and seals the three ditches observed in this
trench.
0.50m thick
109 F Number assigned to fills of ditches [101] [104]
observed in north-east trench section. Same as (103) and
(105).
-
Trench 2 (see Figures 2 3)
2.21 Trench 2 was located on the Bell Street frontage in the southern half of the site and was
aligned approximately north-east to south-west. The trench measured 3.4 x 4.3m and was
excavated to a maximum depth of 1.44m.
2.22 The stratigraphy in this trench consisted of a layer of modern shingle and aggregate
laid directly onto the natural chalk. In the north-west end of the trench the shingle had been
laid directly onto the concrete footing and surviving two courses of a modern boundary wall
[207].
2.23 Several elements of a former structure [206] on the Bell Street frontage were observed
in the base of the trench. These elements include foundation cut [201], brick wall foundation
[203], clunch wall foundation [204], and brick floor [205]. The size of the structure was
unclear as it extended beyond the south-east and south-west trench limits and had been
truncated by modern wall and footing [207] on the north-west side. A sondage excavated
through brick floor [205], demonstrated that disturbance associated with the structure
continued to a depth of approximately 1.40m. The brick used in the footings, along with CBM
fragments recovered from the f of the foundation cut, suggest a 19th
century date for the
structure. The structure is likely to have heavily disturbed or destroyed earlier archaeological
evidence in this part of the site.
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
201 Cut Foundation cut for structure [206], steep straight sides and
a flat base.
Length: 2.30m+
Width: 1.25m+
Depth: 0.24m
202 F Loose, brown (7.5YR 5/3), mixed silt and chalk fragments
with occasional small flints.. F of [201].
Length: 2.30m+
Width: 1.25m+
Depth: 0.24m
203 Wall Brick wall foundation. The foundation is two courses
thick with a substantial cavity between the courses,
aligned NW ­SE.
Length: 1.25m+
Width: 0.75m
Depth: 0.58m
204 Wall Wall foundation constructed of large blocks of chalk,
alignment turns at a right angle from NE ­ SW to NW ­
SE.
Length: 2.95m+
Width: 0.95m
Depth: 0.58m
205 Brick
floor
Brick floor of structure [206]. Length: 1.80m+
Width: 0.95m+
Depth: 0.08m
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 6
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
206 Structure Number assigned to all the elements of the structure. Length: 3.00m+
Width: 2.50m+
Depth: 1.40m
207 Wall Modern boundary wall and concrete foundation. Length: 4.30m+
Width: 0.95m
FINDS CONCORDANCE
Pottery CBM An.bone Shell Fe object Stone Op Sig
Ctxt Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No.
103 275 13 40 4 30 1
105 5 1 540 25 90 7 495 2 55 3
107 205 5 115 7 45 1
108 25 1 450 2 360 6 10 4
Tr1 U/S 135 4 535 10 80 5 35 1
202 200 2 320 20 30 3 10 2
203 5 1 205 2
Beneath 205 145 3
Total 170 7 2205 57 1150 52 40 7 250 5 495 2 130 5
ARTEFACTS
Pottery
2.24 A total of 7 pottery sherds, weighing 170g, was recovered from 1 unstratified and 3
stratified contexts during the present investigation. The pottery ranged in date from the
Roman period to the modern period. The assemblage consists mostly of small, abraded,
undiagnostic bodysherds.
2.25 The earliest pottery recovered consisted of a single small, abraded, undiagnostic,
Romano-British bodysherd. This was recovered from the f of ditch [104]. Despite several
fragments of Romano-British CBM and Opus Signinum being recovered, this was the only
Romano-British pottery observed during the fieldwork.
2.26 <Node id="19263"/>No evidence of Anglo-Saxon pottery<Node id="19297"/> was recovered indicating a possible hiatus in
activity in the area between the Romano-British period and the early Medieval period.
Alluvial deposit (108) over the ditches observed in Trench 1 yielded a single, abraded,
undiagnostic bodysherd probably of medieval date, the sherd may form part of a shallow dish.
Part of a jug handle of 12th
-13th
century date was also recovered unstratified from Trench 1.
2.27 Victorian and modern activity on the site was indicated by several sherds of white and
brown glazed pottery, recovered unstratified from Trench 1 and from contexts associated with
structure [206].
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 7
2.28 The small and abraded nature of the sherds indicate that this material was not in its
primary place of deposition. The small size of the assemblage does not suggest occupation on
the site, but does indicate activity in the vicinity of the site during both the Roman and
Medieval periods.
Recommendations
2.29 Given the small size of the assemblage, the abraded nature of the sherds, and that the
material is unlikely to be in its primary place of deposition, no further work is proposed on
this assemblage.
Ceramic Building Material (CBM)
2.30 A total of 57 CBM fragments, weighing 2205g, was collected from 5 stratified and 1
unstratified contexts during the present investigations. The bulk of the assemblage consisted
of small and heavily abraded undiagnostic fragments of Romano-British date.
2.31 The majority of the abraded and undiagnostic material recovered from the three ditches
within Trench 1 has tentatively been dated to the Romano-British period, the presence of
Romano-British pottery and opus signinum makes this the most likely date. A fragment of
Medieval peg tile recovered from f (103) in ditch [101] is likely to be intrusive. Further
Romano-British CBM fragments were recovered from the alluvial deposit (108) which sealed
the ditches.
2.32 A further fragment of redeposited heavily abraded Romano-British CBM was
recovered from the f of foundation cut [201] in Trench 2. This context also yielded a
modern fragment of burnt brick.
2.33 The Romano-British material, though heavily abraded, is present in a significant
enough quantity to indicate a structure of this date in the vicinity of the site. The abraded
nature of the material indicates that it is not in its primary place of deposition, indicating the
proximity of the Romano-British activity may not be close. <Node id="21787"/>The lack of equally significant
amounts of Romano-British pottery may indicate that the structure was not used for domestic
occupation<Node id="21921"/>.
Recommendations
2.34 The majority of the assemblage consists of small, heavily abraded fragments which are
unlikely to be in their primary place of deposition. On this basis no further work is proposed
on this material.
Iron Objects
2.35 A total of 5 iron objects, weighing 250g, was recovered from 2 stratified and 1
unstratified contexts during the present investigations.
2.36 A single object, consisting of two highly corroded strips of iron riveted together,
possibly representing a pair of scissors or similar item, measuring approximately 93mm by
60mm by a maximum depth of 8mm, was recovered unstratified in Trench 1.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 8
2.37 A small semi-circular disc of corroded iron, possibly part of a coin, token, or button,
with a diameter of 22mm and a depth of 1mm, was recovered from foundation cut f (202)
which has been dated to the 19th
century. A small curving strip of iron, possibly a hook,
measuring 33mm by 28mm by a maximum depth of 9mm, was recovered from the same
context.
2.38 A flat heavily corroded curving strip of iron, possibly part of a plough blade,
measuring 153mm by 71mm by a maximum depth of 9mm, was recovered from within wall
foundation [203]. A heavily corroded iron nail, measuring 77mm long with a diameter at the
head of 12mm, was recovered from the same context.
Recommendations
2.39 No further work is proposed on this material.
Stone
2.40 A total of 2 pieces of stone, weighing 495g, were recovered from 1 stratified context
during the investigation. The two small fragments, which both show signs of being worked,
were recovered from f (105) in ditch [104]. The CBM recovered from this f indicates that
it is likely that the stone may also have been used in a structure.
Recommendations
2.41 Given its small size and undiagnostic nature, no further work is proposed on this
assemblage.
Opus Signinum
2.42 A total of 5 fragments of opus signinum, weighing 130g, was collected from 3
stratified contexts. The fragments are small and abraded and were collected from the fills of
the three ditches observed in Trench 1.
2.43 The presence of opus signinum, along with the Romano-British CBM recovered from
the same features, gives further indication of at least one substantial structure of this period in
the vicinity of the site.
Recommendations
2.44 Given the small size of the assemblage no further work is recommended.
ECOFACTS
Animal bone
2.45 A total of 52 animal bone fragments, weighing 1150g, was collected from 6 stratified
and 1 unstratified contexts. Most of the bone recovered, is in poor condition and is
fragmentary in nature.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 9
2.46 Species represented include larger animals such as cattle or horse, medium-sized
animals such as sheep, goat and pig, as well as smaller fowl such as chicken or duck.
Recommendations
2.47 The incomplete nature of the bone fragments means that further analysis is unlikely to
yield significant information.
Shell
2.48 A total of 7 shells, weighing 40g, was collected from 2 stratified and 1 contexts. The
material consisted of oyster and mussel shells. The majority of the shells are poorly preserved
and fragmentary in nature.
2.49 The assemblage was recovered from the light grey alluvial deposit (108) above the
ditches in Trench 1 and from the f (202) of the foundation cut [201] in Trench 2. Further
shells were present in the fills of the ditches in Trench 1.
Recommendations
2.50 Given the fragmentary nature and small size of the assemblage, no further work is
proposed on this material.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 10
3. Discussion
3.1 Considerable evidence for Romano-British settlement has been recorded from the
vicinity of the present site. A villa and associated bath house (SMR 4921) was excavated at
Glebe Farm, approximately 215m to the northeast in the 1960s. Recent archaeological
evaluation to the rear of The Old School House, The Beck, (SMR 40913) approximately
115m to the north, has revealed evidence for late Roman occupation. Numerous features,
chiefly pits and ditches, were recorded, which contained finds dated to the 3rd
/ 4th
centuries
AD.
3.2 The present evaluation revealed three ditches, [101], [104], and [106]. Later activity on
the site is demonstrated by the foundations of structure [206].
3.3 Ditches [101], [104], and [106] all had similar characteristics and were located within
close proximity to each other. They are likely to represent a series of boundary or drainage
ditches. Waterborne alluvial deposit [108] sealed all three ditches, suggesting that the area
suffered with flooding in the past. This emphasises the likelihood the ditches had a drainage
function. All three of the ditches produced a significant amount of heavily abraded Romano-
British CBM, which, together with the opus signinum recovered, indicates the possible
presence of at least one substantial Romano-British structure in the vicinity.
3.4 The depth of overburden present in Trench 1 has preserved the ditches despite the
presence of a live water main and a sewer pipe.
3.5 The foundations for a structure [206] along with its brick floor [205] observed in
Trench 2 are likely to be the remains of a small house or terrace of cottages on the Bell Street
frontage. This frontage was certainly built up by the mid-19th
century and may have been
occupied earlier. It is shown on the Tithe map of 1837 and the first edition of the Ordnance
Survey, and also on early photographs of Bell Street. The bricks recorded in the evaluation
trench suggest a 19th
century date for the structure.
3.6 A sondage excavated in Trench 2 demonstrated that the disturbance caused by the
structure, along with modern boundary wall [207], has removed any archaeological evidence
of earlier activity on the plot.
Conclusions
3.7 Although the trench was small and highly disturbed by services, the archaeological
evaluation has demonstrated the presence of boundary and drainage features of Romano-
British date within the current study area.
3.8 No direct occupation evidence was recorded although finds of Romano-British ceramic
building material and opus signinum were collected from the fills of all three ditches,
indicating that there may have been a substantial structure in the vicinity of the site. Certainly,
a number of pits and ditches of a similar date were recorded during evaluation of The Old
School site to the north and significant Roman occupation evidence exists within 500m of the
study area. As the finds assemblage was badly abraded, however, and very few pottery sherds
or other domestic finds, such as animal bone or marine shell, were collected, it is suggested
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 11
that these may represent deliberate backfilling of the ditches, rather than the presence of a
building.
3.9 Earlier stratigraphy on the site in the area of the Bell Street frontage has been destroyed
by the foundations of a 19th
century structure.
3.10 <Node id="29030"/>Although no direct evidence of occupation on the site prior to the late post-medieval
period was observed<Node id="29135"/> in the course of the evaluation, there remains a possibility that the
development of the site could disturb features and deposits of Roman date. These could
contribute to our understanding of the development of rural settlement during the Roman
period and offer a limited opportunity to explore further the research topics for the Romano-
British period defined in the regional research agenda (Brown and Glazebrook 2000, 19-20).
It is not considered likely that such remains would be of a quality to warrant preservation in
situ.
CONFIDENCE RATING
3.11 During the course of the fieldwork, the conditions were generally acceptable for the
identification of potential features and deposits, and for their investigation.
3.12 There are no further circumstances which would lead to a confidence rating for the
present evaluation which is less than High.
1 Bell Street, Feltwell Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN525\report.doc Page 12
4. Sources Consulted
Archives
Norfolk County HER
Bibliography
Brown, N. Glazebrook, J. 2000. Research and Archaeology: a Framework for the Eastern
Counties, 2. research agenda and strategy. East Anglian Archaeology, Occ.Paper no.8.
Hillelson, D. 2004. 1 Bell Street, Feltwell, Norfolk. Project Design: Archaeological
Evaluation. Heritage Network, April 2005.
Hutcheson, A.R.J. 2004, Brief for Archaeological Evaluation by Trial Trenching at 1 Bell
Street, Feltwell, Norfolk. Norfolk Landscape Archaeology.
Web Sites
http://ads.ahds.ac.uk Archaeology Data Service
www.feltwell.org.uk Feltwell Tithe Map, 1837
www.old-maps.co.uk OS First edition 1888 (571448, 290680)
5. Illustrations
Figure 1............................................................................... Site location
Figure 2..................................................................................Site layout
Figure 3..........................................................Trench plans and sections
Figure 4......................................................................... Feature sections
St Mary's
Church
War Meml
Church
Sun
Sch
Hall Hall
THE BECK
BELL STREET
BM
7.92m
907
908
715 716TL
Site location
HN525
Reproduced from OS mapping with the permission of the controller of Her Majesty's Stationery Office, Licence no.AL100014861
Hunstanton
Feltwell
King's Lynn
1 Bell Street, FeltwellTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD
Scale 1:1250
Figure 1
Norwich
Plot 1
Plot 2
Plot 3
Proposed new build
Tr1
Tr2
Development started
Scale 1:500
Figure 2
Trench location
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD HN5251 Bell Street, Feltwell
Reproduced from OS mapping with the permission of the controller of Her Majesty's Stationery Office, Licence no.AL52036A
Scale 1:75
Figure 3
Trench plans and sections
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 1 Bell Street, Feltwell HN525
NW SE
NW SE
Live Water Main
Live Sewer
Southwest facing section of Trench 1
Plan of Trench 2
Southwest facing section of Trench 2
Plan of Trench 1
0 3m
Topsoil
Subsoil
(108)
(109)
(108)
Natural
Concrete
Modern shingle
Natural
207
201
Clunch
wall 204
Brick
floor 205
Brick
wall 203
Sondage
106 104
101
8.06
7.51
7.63
7.37
7.63
8.28
8.21
8.21
8.13
6.84
6.02
5.68
5.10
5.67
4.74
4.43
4.73
4.34
4.79
4.65
5.00
6.02
8.17m 8.28m
5.99m
6.14m
Natural
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 1 Bell Street, Feltwell HN525
Feature sections
Scale 1:10
Figure 4
North facing section through ditch [101]
E W
(103)
(102)
101
Northeast facing section through ditch [104]
Northeast facing section through ditch [106]
North facing section through [201]
SE
NW
SE NW
SW NE
104
106
201
(105)
(202)
(107)
0 50cms
7.63m
4.74m
4.73m
4.79m
<Node id="32778"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="3867" EndNode="3951">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="3" Type="Negation" StartNode="19263" EndNode="19297">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="21787" EndNode="21921">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="5" Type="Negation" StartNode="29030" EndNode="29135">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="12084" EndNode="12159">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="32778">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
