<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/heritage1-10767.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>IFA
RE
G IS ER
E
T
D
RO
ON
NA
A
I
I
G
ST
HERITAGE NETWORKHERITAGE NETWORK
10 NORTHBRIDGE STREET
Shefford, Beds.
Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454
THETHE HERITAGE NETWORKHERITAGE NETWORK LTDLTD
Registered with the Institute of Field Archaeologists as an Archaeological Organisation
Archaeological Director: David Hillelson, BA MIFA
1111 FFURMSTONURMSTON CCOURTOURT,, IICKNIELDCKNIELD WWAYAY, L, LETCHWORTHETCHWORTH SG6 1UJSG6 1UJ
TTELEPHONEELEPHONE: (01462) 685991 F: (01462) 685991 FAXAX: (01462) 685998: (01462) 685998
Land to the rear of
10 NORTHBRIDGE STREET
Shefford, Beds.
HN454
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared on behalf of Lauren Homes Ltd
by
Chris Turner, BSc and Geoff Saunders, BA
Report No.229
May 2004
© The Heritage Network Ltd
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page i
Contents
Summary........................................................................................................................................................Page i
Section 1 Introduction .................................................................................................................................................Page 1
Section 2 Fieldwork......................................................................................................................................................Page 2
Section 3 Discussion.................................................................................................................................................Page 15
Section 4 Bibliography............................................................................................................................................ Page 16
Section 5 Illustrations..............................................................................................................................following Page 16
Acknowledgements
The fieldwork for this project was carried out by Karin Semmelmann, Chris Turner, Geoff Saunders, and David
Kaye. Illustrations were prepared by Karin Semmelmann and Chris Turner, and the report was edited by David
Hillelson.
The Heritage Network would like to express its thanks to Terry Elliot, Lauren Homes Ltd; and the staff of the
Heritage and Environment Section, Bedfordshire County Council, for their co-operation and assistance in the
execution of this project.
Summary
Site name and address: Land to the rear of 10 Northbridge Street, Shefford, Bedfordshire
County: Bedfordshire District: Mid Bedfordshire
Village/town: Shefford Parish: Shefford
Planning reference: 03/1160 NGR: TL 1438 3920
Client name and address: Lauren Homes Ltd, `Chequers', 28 New Road, Clifton, Shefford, Bedfordshire
Nature of work: New Dwellings Present land use: Former Laundry
Size of affected area: c.1225m2
Size of area investigated: c.102m2
Site Code: HN454 Other reference: N/a
Organisation: Heritage Network Site Director: David Hillelson
Type of work: Evaluation Archive location: Bedford Museum
Start of work 16th
March 2004 Finish of work 26th
March 2004
Related SMR Nos.: N/a Periods represented: Med/post-med/modern
Previous summaries/reports: N/a
Synopsis: In response to an archaeological condition on the planning permission for four new dwellings on land to
the rear of 10 Northbridge Street, Shefford, Bedfordshire, the Heritage Network was commissioned by Lauren
Homes Ltd to undertake an archaeological evaluation of the site.
Four trial trenches were opened across the proposed development area. These demonstrated that the site lay within
the flood plain of the rivers Flit and Ivel. All the trenches were waterlogged at the lower levels, and the stratigraphy
was indicative of repeated flooding.
Despite the presence of Roman activity in the vicinity of the site, no evidence dating to this period was identified in
the course of the evaluation. Artefacts dating to the 12th
-14th
century were found on the site, but their density and
the nature of their deposition, suggests that the centre of medieval activity lay outside of the boundaries of the site.
A post setting made up from interlaced cattle horn cores and a horse mandible was uncovered on the eastern side of
the site. This would have been intended as a good luck charm placed in or near to a building foundation, probably
of late post-medieval date.
It is likely that the focus of early settlement, as today, lay on higher ground to the north and west of the present site
and outside of the flood plain formed by the confluence of the two rivers.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 1
1. Introduction
1.1 This report has been prepared on behalf of Lauren Homes Ltd as part of an
archaeological evaluation of a proposed development on land to the rear of 10 Northbridge
Street, Shefford, Bedfordshire. The planning permission for the development (ref. 03/1160)
controlled by the Mid Beds District Council, had been granted subject to a standard
archaeological condition requiring the implementation of a programme of archaeological
work, in accordance with the provisions of the DETR's Planning Policy Guidance Note 16
(PPG16). The scope of the works had been set out in a Brief for a Programme of
Archaeological Investigation and a Brief for an Archaeological Field Evaluation both dated
9th
February 2004 and prepared by the County Archaeological Officer (CAO) of Bedfordshire
County Council, acting as adviser to the planning authority. The specification for the work
carried out is contained in the Heritage Network's approved Project Design dated February
2004.
1.2 The site is located on the east side of Northbridge Street, close to the junction with the
High Street, and just to the west of the confluence of the rivers Ivel and Flit, centred on NGR
TL 1438 3920 (see Figure 1). The frontage of the site is occupied by a listed building (no.10
Northbridge Street) which is to be retained. The rear of the site was occupied by the former
Shefford Hand Laundry which was demolished prior to the works starting. The development
proposes the construction of four dwellings with gardens, in a terrace of three and one
detached. The existing access w be retained with some alterations. The area affected by the
development is approximately 1225m2
in size including the access.
1.3 Lying in the medieval core of Shefford, there was considered to be a high probability
that remains of this date would be affected by the development. Roman activity has also been
identified within 80m of the site.
1.4 The aim of the evaluation has been to consider the location, extent, date, character,
condition, significance and quality of any remains that may be threatened by the development,
and to provide a local and regional, archaeological and historical context for them, in
accordance with the current published regional research agenda (Glazebrook 1997, Brown
and Glazebrook 2000).
1.5 The present report has been prepared to provide the planning authority with sufficient
data to allow it to consider the archaeological implications of the proposed development, and
to determine what further mitigation measures, if any, may be required.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 2
2. Fieldwork
TOPOGRAPHY AND GEOLOGY
2.1 The site lies at c.38m AOD, on land which falls gradually to the north-east, towards the
river Flit c.175m away.
2.2 The underlying geology is mixed reddish brown sand and gravel.
METHODOLOGY
3.2 During machining, Trenches 3 and 5 defined in the Project Design were conjoined to
make one trench and recorded as Trench 3.
3.3 All other work was carried out in accordance with the approved Project Design,
current health and safety guidelines, and IFA standards.
3.4 Trenches were set out using fibreglass tape measures by triangulation from known
points.
3.5 Four trenches were opened using a 2-tonne tracked 360o
mini-excavator fitted with a
1.5m wide toothless bucket, under close archaeological supervision (see Figure 2). Spoil from
the machining was inspected for archaeological artefacts.
3.6 The trenches were machined in two stages:
· Stage 1: the trenches were machined to the first significant archaeological horizon
where features were clearly visible cut through floodplain deposits (see Figure 3).
· Stage 2: further machining was carried out through the floodplain deposits in order
to identify any possible earlier horizons of activity (see Figure 4).
3.7 The trenches were cleaned by hand, and within limits of health and safety regulations
all potential archaeological features and deposits were sampled to ascertain their nature,
depth, date, and quality of preservation.
3.8 All identified contexts were photographed and recorded using the appropriate pro-
forma. Scaled plans and sections were drawn on drafting film at scales of 1:10 and 1:20.
3.9 Trenches were located relative to the plot boundaries using an electronic theodolite.
RESULTS
Site Stratigraphy
3.10 The stratigraphy across the site varied according to whether the trench was located on
the inside or the outside of the footprint of the former Shefford Hand Laundry.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 3
3.11 On the inside of the laundry footprint the stratigraphy consisted of a modern demolition
layer of dark grey silt with frequent ceramic building material (CBM) fragments overlying
mixed layers of redeposited natural sand. These layers of redeposited sand probably represent
levelling layers put down prior to the construction of the laundry. Beneath the levelling
deposits a layer of flood deposits was encountered below which lay the undisturbed natural
formed of reddish brown sandy gravel.
3.12 On the outside of the laundry footprint the stratigraphy consisted of a modern
demolition layer of dark grey silt with frequent CBM fragments overlying a layer of mid
greyish brown sandy silt overburden. Beneath the overburden a dark grey sandy silt flood
deposit was encountered below which lay a mottled greyish green sandy clayey silt which
may represent an area of permanently waterlogged and marshy ground associated with the
floodplain of the rivers Flit and Ivel. Beneath this lay the undisturbed natural formed of
reddish brown sandy gravel.
Trench 1
3.13 Trench 1 was located across the southwest end of the proposed terrace of three
dwellings and the new access route. The trench measured 1.70 x 15.45m, and 1.30m in depth,
and was aligned northwest to southeast. The stratigraphy demonstrated extensive disturbance
from the laundry building.
Stage 1 machining
3.14 Four possible features were identified during this phase (108, 101/109, 103, 110 and
111). In addition, a large levelling layer of redeposited sandy gravels from the construction of
the laundry was exposed along the eastern baulk at this depth.
3.15 Features [110], [109/101] and [111] form a post-medieval soakaway, which may pre
date the recently demolished laundry building.
3.16 Running across the trench was an indistinct linear of disturbed cobbles [108],
approximately 0.60m wide. This may be the lower remains of a wall; pottery recovered from
this feature suggests a medieval date. The presence of post-medieval/modern disturbance at
this level in the trench indicates that any potential medieval remains on the site would have
been truncated by later activity, particularly the construction of the laundry building.
3.17 Feature [103] was a small sub-circular post-medieval pit (see Figure 5a). Of all the
features in Trench 1, only [103] was also observed following the second stage machining.
Stage 2 machining
3.18 Two features, [103] and [105], were encountered in the trench at this level.
3.19 Horncore, and fragments of CBM were recovered from the base of pit [103].
3.20 To the north of feature [103] was a small `U' shaped gully [105], running across the
trench (see Figure 5a). It is possible that this feature is a continuation of gully [203], identified
in Trench 2.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 4
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
101 Cut Oval shaped cut feature with sloping sides and a flat base,
aligned northwest to southeast. Small post-medieval pit
(same as [109]
Length: 0.66m
Width: 0.41m
Depth: 0.10m
102 F Mixed rubble infill, with brick and clay pipe, of post-
medieval pit. F of [101].
Length: 0.66m
Width: 0.41m
Depth: 0.10m
103 Cut Sub-circular cut feature with steep concave sides and a
slightly rounded base, aligned north to south. Small pit.
Length: 0.58m
Width: 0.48m
Depth: 0.17m
104 F F of [103], contained frequent fragments of horn core. Length: 0.58m
Width: 0.48m
Depth: 0.17m
105 Cut Cut of linear feature, with concave sides and a rounded
base, aligned northeast to southwest. Shallow gully.
Length: 1.70m+
Width: 0.43m
Depth: 0.22m
106 F Secondary f of shallow gully [105] Length: 1.70m+
Width: 0.43m
Depth: 0.18m
107 F Primary f of shallow gully [105] Length: 0.51m+
Width: 0.21m
Depth: 0.04m
108 Structure Loose alignment of rounded cobbles, may represent the
remains of a wall.
Length: 1.70m+
Width: 0.60m
109 Feature Same as [101] Length: 0.66m
Width: 0.41m
Depth: 0.10m
110 Feature Unexcavated sub-circular feature of mid brown clay. Diameter: 1.10m
111 Feature Unexcavated indistinct linear feature of light green silty
clay aligned north to south. Appears to run into [110],
probable drainage gully running into a soakaway.
Width: 0.45m
112 Layer Dark grey silt and CBM rubble. Demolition layer. 0.15m thick
113 Layer Redeposited yellowish brown sand. Levelling layer. 0.30m thick
114 Layer Redeposited reddish brown compact sand with flat stones.
Levelling layer.
0.50m thick
115 Layer Mid grey clayey sandy silt with sub-rounded stones. 0.30m thick
116 Layer Dark grey sandy silt with frequent CBM inclusions. 0.70m thick
117 Layer Mid grey sandy silt. Flood deposit. 0.60m thick
118 Layer Reddish brown sandy gravel. Natural geology. -
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 5
Trench 2
3.21 Trench 2 was located along the proposed new access road into the site. It measured
1.50 x 12.00m, was 1.30m in depth, and was aligned approximately north to south.
Stage 1 machining
3.22 One possible feature, [201], was identified during this stage (see Figure 5a). This was
a sub-circular post-medieval pit, which was also observed following the second stage
machining. Pottery recovered from this feature suggests an 18th
century date.
Stage 2 machining
3.23 Three features, [201], [203] and [205], were encountered in the trench at this level.
3.24 Pit [201] was observed during the first stage machining.
3.25 A small gully [203] ran across the southern end of the trench and turned eastwards
towards Trench 1 (see Figure 5a). This appears to be part of gully [105], observed in Trench
1. This type of gully may have provided simple drainage to a yard area . Alternatively it could
demarcate a late medieval plot division, turning away from the waterlogged areas to the west.
3.26 A large square cut cess pit, [205], was recorded in the middle of this trench (see Figure
5b). The cess in this pit was sealed by f (207). Two sherds of pottery suggest a medieval
date for this feature. The depth of the pit and the high water table prevented the full
excavation of this feature.
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
201 Cut Sub-circular cut feature with steep sides undercutting in
places and a flat base, aligned north to south. Small post-
medieval pit.
Length: 0.80m
Width: 0.70m
Depth: 0.18m
202 F Dark yellowish brown clayey sandy silt with CBM and
flint inclusions. F of small pit [201].
Length: 0.80m
Width: 0.70m
Depth: 0.18m
203 Cut Linear cut feature with moderately steep slightly concave
sides and a slightly rounded base, aligned northwest to
southeast, turning to run east to west. Possible natural
channel.
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.49m
Depth: 0.12m
204 F Light brownish grey silty clay with frequent sub-rounded
stones. F of [203].
Length: 1.30m+
Width: 0.49m
Depth: 0.12m
205 Cut Sub-square cut feature with very steep sides undercutting
in places, aligned southwest to northeast. Cess pit.
Length: 2.40m+
Width: 1.20m+
Depth: 0.41m+
206 F Greyish blue clayey silt with moderate angular flints. Cess
f of pit [205].
Length: 2.40m+
Width: 1.20m+
Depth: 0.38m+
207 F Dark reddish brown silty sand with occasion angular
stones. Upper f of cess pit, probably laid down to seal
Length: 2.40m+
Width: 1.20m+
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 6
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
the pit at the end of its use. Depth: 0.11m
208 Layer Dark grey silt and CBM rubble. Demolition layer. 0.30m thick
209 Layer Redeposited reddish yellow sand. Levelling layer. 0.25m thick
210 Layer Dark grey sandy silt with frequent CBM fragments. 0.40m thick
211 Layer Dark grey sandy silt. 0.45m thick
212 Layer Light to mid grey sandy silt. Flood deposit. 0.30m thick
213 Layer Reddish brown sandy gravel. Natural geology. -
Trench 3
3.27 Trench 3 was located to run along the axis of the proposed terrace of three new
dwellings and across the parking area in the northeast corner of the site. The trench measured
1.50 x 25.30m, was 1.30m in depth, and was aligned southwest to northeast before turning to
run approximately north to south.
3.28 Apart from 4m in the northeastern corner of the trench, the stratigraphy was highly
disturbed by the footprint of the former laundry building.
Stage 1 machining
3.29 During this stage of machining four potential features were observed. All of them
formed part of the post-medieval disturbance layers associated with the laundry building. The
top of the animal bone in pit [301] was also observed at this level.
Stage 2 machining
3.30 Three features, [301], [303] and [305], were encountered in the trench at this level.
3.31 The trench was dominated by a large area of dark brown silty sand (304) within cut
[303]. This area covered 9m of the trench's length and extended east and westwards beyond
the trench sides. The location of this deposit coincides with disturbance caused by the
footprint of the former laundry building and may represent runoff from the laundry's
activities.
3.32 The edges of pit [301] were poorly defined, but it was cut into the f of [303]. This
feature contained a rough wooden post which was supported by a mesh of 13 horn cores and a
horse mandible. The horn core was arranged in a cage formation with the mandible lying flat
in the centre. Upon this was the fragment of oak post.
· Similar settings of horn cores in association with horse skulls have been documented
elsewhere. They have generally been found placed at the corners of buildings, or
beneath gateposts, as a good luck charm intended to ward off evil spirits.
3.33 A medieval cess pit [305] was excavated at the western end of trench. This feature was
similar in nature to cess pit [205] in Trench 2. The main cess deposit (306) was sealed by
brown clay silt (307). On the side of the pit, a dump of redeposited sandy natural (308), was
observed. Late medieval green glazed pottery was recovered from the cess deposit.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 7
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
301 Cut Sub-circular cut feature with steep sides and a rounded
base, aligned northwest to southeast. Small pit.
Length:0.80 M
Width: 0.60m
Depth: 0.35m
302 F Dark greyish brown clayey silt, contained large amount of
horn core, two complete jaw bones from a horse, and a
large fragment of an oak post. F of pit [301].
Length:0.80 M+
Width: 0.60m
Depth: 0.35m
303 Cut Large cut feature of indeterminate shape, with steep
straight sides.
Length: 1.24m+
Width: 1.08m+
Depth: 0.17m+
304 F Dark brown silty sand. Upper f of [303] Length: 1.24m+
Width: 1.08m+
Depth: 0.17m+
305 Cut Sub-circular cut feature with moderately steep concave
sides, aligned northwest to southeast. Post-medieval cess
pit.
Length: 1m+
Width: 1.10m
Depth: 0.30m
306 F Blue Grey cess f of pit [305], sealing cess. Length: 1m+
Width: 1.10m
Depth: 0.30m+
307 F Brown silty clay f of pit [305]. Length: 1m+
Width: 1.10m
Depth: 0.12m
308 F Yellowish brown sand, f of pit [305]. Redeposited
natural.
Length: 1m+
Width: 1.10m
Depth: 0.15m
309 Layer Dark grey silt and CBM rubble. Demolition layer. 0.20m thick
310 Layer Brown sandy silt with CBM fragments. Levelling layer. 0.30m thick
311 Layer Dark grey sandy silt. 0.25m thick
312 Layer Reddish brown sandy silt 0.33m thick
313 Layer Grey sandy silt. Flood deposit. 0.35m thick
314 F Redeposited natural sand. F of large cess pit [303]. Length: 8.20m+
Width: 1.60m+
Depth: 0.30m+
315 F Mixed brownish grey sandy silt. F of large cess pit
[303]
Length: 8.20m+
Width: 1.60m+
Depth: 0.60m+
316 Layer Dark grey sandy silt with CBM fragments. Overburden 0.50m thick
317 Layer Dark grey sandy silt. Overburden. 0.30m thick
318 Layer Mid grey sandy silt. Flood deposit 0.55m thick
319 Layer Reddish brown sandy gravel. Natural geology. -
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 8
Trench 4
3.34 Trench 4 was located to run along the access of the proposed detached single dwelling
in the south east corner of the site. The trench measured 1.50 x 13.20m, was 1.30m in depth,
and was aligned approximately northeast to southwest.
3.35 The southeastern baulk of this trench showed undisturbed floodplain stratigraphy
which was also observed in the northeastern end of Trench 3.
Stage 1 machining
3.36 A possible post-medieval pit, [403], was observed directly below the foundation line of
the footprint of the former laundry building.
3.37 Unstratified medieval pottery was recovered from the flood deposits at the eastern end
of this trench.
Stage 2 machining
3.38 Pit [403] was st visible in the trench at this level.
3.39 It is likely that gullies [401] and [402] may be part of the same feature with a patch of
redeposited natural separating them. Nevertheless, both appear to relate to the large
contamination deposit, (304), in Trench 3. It is likely that these two features represent
drainage for that deposit.
Recorded contexts
Context Type Description Dimensions (m)
401 Feature Unexcavated linear feature, Mid greyish brown clay silt.
(below water table making excavation impossible)
Length: 1.5m+
402 Feature Unexcavated linear feature, Mid greyish brown clay silt.
(below water table making excavation impossible).
Length: 1.5m+
403 Feature Unexcavated sub-circular feature, reddish grey brown
post medieval (below the water table making excavation
impossible).
Length: 1m+
Width: 1.40m
404 Layer Dark grey silt and CBM rubble. Demolition layer. 0.10m thick
405 Layer Mid greyish brown sandy silt with CBM fragments.
Overburden.
0.50m thick
406 Layer Dark grey sandy silt. Flood deposit. 0.25m thick
407 Layer Mottled greyish green sandy clayey silt. Possible former
marshy ground.
0.30m thick
408 Layer Reddish brown sandy gravel. Natural geology. -
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 9
FINDS CONCORDANCE
Pottery CBM An.bone Fe.object Daub Stone Shell Other* Comments
Ctxt No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. No. Wt. Comments
102 6 1020 27 185 2 2 1 10 4 15 *Clay Pipe
104 1 5 10 105 36 110 1 2 3 35 1 1
106 1 20 2 95 1 2 3 155
107 1 20
108 2 4 1 15
Tr1
U/S
3 95 9 440 2 20
202 4 15 14 325 2 35 2 10 4 85 3 5
206 2 35 8 210 *Wood
302 1 3 3 925 198 5845 1 10 1 320 1 5 1 1 *Charcoal
302 1 4715 *Wood
306 5 55 1 70 7 55 *Wood
307 2 45
308 1 10 6 100 *Wood
Tr3
U/S
1 10 1 25 4 115 2 5 *Clay Pipe
Tr4
U/S
3 65 1 55 *Slag
Total 23 307 36 2540 278 6712 7 145 5 14 13 625 5 11 30 5156
ARTEFACT ASSESSMENTS
Pottery
3.40 A total of 23 sherds of pottery, weighing 307g, was recovered during the evaluation.
The bulk of this material comprised undiagnostic greyware bodysherds of 12th
to 14th
century
date, which were residual in later contexts.
3.41 A small number of other fabrics were represented, including four sherds of late
medieval green-glazed ware from context (306) and two sherds of early medieval calcite-
gritted ware from context (206).
3.42 <Node id="24242"/>Post-medieval pottery was surprisingly absent from the assemblage<Node id="24307"/>. Only two sherds
that could be dated to this period were present, both from context (202). These comprised part
of a small brown-glazed cup handle, of possible 18th
century date, and an unglazed bodysherd
that cannot be closely dated.
Recommendations
3.43 Although most of the pottery recovered from the present site dates to the medieval
period, it was recovered from the fills of demonstrably later features. Given that this material
is residual and comprises mostly undiagnostic bodysherds no further work is proposed on this
assemblage.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 10
Ceramic Building Materials
3.44 A total of 36 pieces of brick and tile, weighing 2540g, was recovered during the
evaluation. The material varied between large unabraded pieces and smaller broken
fragments.
3.45 The bulk of this material is represented by peg tile fragments of 18th
-19th
century date.
A small number of early post-medieval tile fragments are also present, including 1 piece from
context (306). Two large brick pieces were also recovered from context (101).
Recommendations
3.46 The present assemblage may have been imported on to the site as backf for the pits.
On this basis no further work is proposed on this material.
Iron Objects
3.47 A total of 7 iron objects, weighing 145g, was recovered during the evaluation. The only
identifiable objects were three nails, two of which were unstratified in Trench 1 and one was
from context (302) in feature [301].
Recommendations
3.48 Given the fragmentary nature of this material, no further work is proposed on this
assemblage.
Daub
3.49 A total of 5 pieces of daub, weighing 14g, were recovered during the evaluation.
Recommendations
3.50 This assemblage consisted of tiny, abraded fragments, that could have been imported
on to the site. On this basis no further work is proposed on this material.
Stone
3.51 A total of 13 pieces of stone, weighing 625g, were recovered during the evaluation.
Much of the assemblage consists of unworked pieces of naturally occurring ironstone.
Recommendations
3.52 As the stone from the site consists of unworked fragments, no further work is proposed
on this material.
Clay Pipe
3.53 A total of 6 pieces of clay pipe, weighing 20g, was recovered during the evaluation.
The fragments, from f (102) in pit [101], and unstratified in trench 3, were all stem
fragments.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 11
Recommendations
3.54 This material was represented by a small number of undiagnostic clay pipe stems. On
this basis, no further work is proposed on this material.
ECOFACTS
Animal Bone
3.55 A total of 278 pieces of animal bone, weighing 6712g, were recovered during the
present evaluation. The majority of the assemblage is made up of horn core, including both
complete examples and broken fragments.
3.56 The lower mandible of horse and fragments of 13 bovine horn cores came from post pit
[301]. The horn cores were arranged to cradle the mandible which was positioned flat
supporting the wooden post fragment. Pit [103] contained the only other fragment horn core
encountered on the site.
3.57 The rest of the bone assemblage was indicative of normal domestic rubbish with small
quantities of butchered bovine rib, tarsal and sheep/goat long bones.
3.58 <Node id="27652"/>There was no indication of industrial processes<Node id="27699"/> utilising these species on site.
Recommendations
3.59 The assemblage is well preserved but fragmentary. On this basis no further work is
proposed on this material.
Oyster Shell
3.60 A total of 5 fragments of oyster shell, weighing 11g, were recovered during the
evaluation.
Recommendations
3.61 Oyster shell is common on urban sites of medieval and post-medieval date. Given the
small size of this assemblage, no further work is proposed on this material.
Wood
3.62 A total of 22 pieces of wood, weighing 5080g, were recovered during the present
evaluation.
3.63 A single piece, weighing 4715g, was recovered from f (302) in pit [301]. This has
been identified as part of an oak post, measuring 0.27m in length, 0.21m in width and 0.14m
in depth. It appeared to have been cut on one side, but was broken on the other.
3.64 A number of smaller pieces were recovered from contexts (206), (306) and (308).
Several of these appear to have been roughly worked and may have formed pegs. Two pieces
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 12
from context (308) had angled cuts at one end and one piece from (206) had a straight cut at
one end.
Recommendations
3.65 Apart from the post setting in (302), most of this material appears to have been used as
part of the backf for the large cess pits, and therefore is out of context. On this basis no
further work is proposed on this assemblage.
Charcoal
3.66 A single fragment of charcoal, weighing 1g, was recovered from f (302) in feature
[301] during the evaluation.
Recommendations
3.67 Given the small size of the assemblage no further work is proposed on this material.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 13
4. Discussion
4.2 The site's location, close to the confluence of the rivers Ivel and Flit, raised the
possibility that it might have provided a focus for commercial or trading activities associated
with river transport. The evaluation has demonstrated that the site lay within the flood plain of
the two rivers and no evidence was found for it having been built up, or for the construction of
wooden walkways or wharves. All the trenches were waterlogged at the lower levels, and the
stratigraphy was indicative of repeated flooding.
4.3 Despite the presence of Roman activity in the vicinity of the site, <Node id="30060"/>no evidence dating to
this period was identified in the course of the evaluation<Node id="30140"/>.
4.4 Artefacts dating to the 12th
-14th
century were found on the site, but their density and the
nature of their deposition, suggests that the centre of medieval activity lay outside of the
boundaries of the present site. It is possible that these finds were washed onto to the site by
river flooding and that they originated upstream.
4.5 The presence of post setting [302], with its connection to superstitious beliefs, suggests
that there was a timber structure at the eastern end of the site that predated the laundry
building. This would not be an unexpected location for a stable block, barn or outhouse,
although <Node id="30762"/>no other traces of such a structure were observed<Node id="30811"/>, and the 1885 Ordnance Survey (6-
inch series) is inconclusive.
4.6 It is likely that the focus of early settlement, as today, lay on higher ground to the north
and west of the present site and outside of the flood plain formed by the confluence of the two
rivers.
Conclusions
4.7 The archaeological evaluation has demonstrated that the site has been heavily disturbed
by the former Shefford Hand Laundry and its associated drainage and services.
4.8 Finds of wooden pegs (tree-nails), and a ritual post setting suggest the presence of a
timber framed building at the east end of the site, probably post-medieval in date, predating
the recently demolished laundry building.
4.9 The site lies at the edge of the combined flood plain of the rivers Ivel and Flit and as
such would have been unsuitable for settlement.
CONFIDENCE RATING
4.10 The weather during the course of the evaluation was poor with high rainfall. This
combined with a high water table to cause flooding in the trial trenches and make
archaeological investigation difficult. Despite these conditions, it is considered that an
adequate opportunity was gained to assess the archaeological potential of the site, and the
evaluation can be considered to have a moderate to high confidence rating.
10 Northbridge Street, Shefford Archaeological Evaluation Report
HN454\report.doc Page 14
5. Bibliography
Hillelson, D. 2004. 10 Northbridge Street, Shefford, Beds. Project Design: Archaeological
Evaluation. Heritage Network, February 2004.
Bedfordshire CC. 2004, Brief for an Archaeological Field Evaluation on Land at 10
Northbridge Street, Shefford, Bedfordshire . Heritage and Environment Section, BCC.
Ordnance Survey, 1885, County Series, 1st
edition, 1: 10,560 (Courtesy Landmark
Information Group Ltd.)
6. Illustrations
Figure 1............................................................................... Site location
Figure 2.............................................................................Trench layout
Figure 3...................................................................First machined level
Figure 4.............................................................. Second machined level
Figure 5a .............................................................. Plans and sections (1)
Figure 5b.............................................................. Plans and sections (2)
Figure 6...........................................................................Trench profiles
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD
Site Location
10 Northbridge St. Shefford HN454
Reproduced from the Ordnance Survey with the permission of the controller of Her Majesty's Stationery Office, Licence no.AL100014861
Scale 1:1250
Figure 1
Bedford
Luton
Dunstable
BEDFORDSHIRE
SHEFFORD
Limitofsiteclearance
0 10m
Trench1
Trench2
Trench 3
Trench 4
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD Land at 10 Northbridge Street, Shefford HN454
Scale 1:400
Figure 2
Trench layout
109
Animal bone
110
111
108
103
201
Pottery sherd
403
Scale 1:250
Figure 3
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 10 Northbridge St. Shefford HN454
0 10m
First machined level
103
105
201
301
205
203
303
305
403
402
401
304
Scale 1:250
Figure 4
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 10 Northbridge St. Shefford HN454
0 10m
Second machined level
103
104 103
Plan profile of [103]
105
105
105
106
107
S N
Plan east facing section of [105]
203
204
Plan south-east facing section of [203]
Plan south-west facing section of [201]
201 202
CBM
Flint
203
204
SW NE
201
NW SE
Scale 1:20
Figure 5a
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 10 Northbridge St. Shefford HN454
0 50cm
Feature plans sections (1)
Plan north-east facing section of [205]
205
206
207
205
206
207
SE NW
Start of sand
303
SW NE
303
Plan south-east facing section of [303]
Scale 1:20
Figure 5b
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 10 Northbridge St. Shefford HN454
0 50cm
Feature plans sections (2)
N S
210
211
212
209
208
113
114
117
116
112
115
N S
404
405
406
407
EW
West facing section of Trench 2
West facing section of Trench 1
South facing section of Trench 4
309
316
317
318
310
311
314
312
313
315
W ESouth facing section of Trench 3
303
303
THE HERITAGE NETWORK LTDTHE HERITAGE NETWORK LTD 10 Northbridge Street, Shefford HN454
Trench profiles
Scale 1:100
Figure 6
3m0
<Node id="35150"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="30762" EndNode="30811">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="24242" EndNode="24307">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="2" Type="Negation" StartNode="30060" EndNode="30140">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="3" Type="Negation" StartNode="27652" EndNode="27699">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="35150">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
