<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/wessexar1-25626_1.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>Wessex Archaeology
March 2007Ref: 65440.01
Land West Of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St. Ives
Cambridgeshire
Archaeological Evaluation Report
CHER Event Number ECB2530
Land West of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St Ives
Cambridgeshire
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Prepared on behalf of:
CgMs Consulting
Morley House
26 Holborn Viaduct
London
EC1A 2AT
By:
Wessex Archaeology
Portway House
Old Sarum Park
Salisbury
Wiltshire
SP4 6EB
Report reference: 65440.01
CHER Event Number ECB2530
March 2007
© Wessex Archaeology Limited 2007 all rights reserved
Wessex Archaeology Limited is a Registered Charity No. 287786
Land West of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St Ives
Cambridgeshire
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Contents
Summary ............................................................................................................ iii
Acknowledgements.............................................................................................iv
1 PROJECT BACKGROUND ..............................................................................1
1.1 Introduction................................................................................................1
1.2 Site Location, Use and Geology ................................................................1
2 ARCHAEOLOGICAL/HISTORICAL BACKGROUND...............................2
2.1 Archaeological and Historical Background.............................................2
3 AIMS OF THE FIELDWORK PROGRAMME..............................................3
3.1 Objectives....................................................................................................3
3.2 Research Framework.................................................................................3
4 METHODOLOGY..............................................................................................3
4.1 Fieldwork....................................................................................................3
5 RESULTS.............................................................................................................4
5.1 Introduction................................................................................................4
5.2 Soil Profile...................................................................................................5
5.3 Geophysical Anomalies and Negative Features.......................................5
5.4 Archaeological features .............................................................................5
6 FINDS ...................................................................................................................6
6.1 General........................................................................................................6
6.2 Worked and Burnt Flint............................................................................6
6.3 Human Bone...............................................................................................7
7 ENVIRONMENTAL...........................................................................................7
7.1 Introduction................................................................................................7
7.2 Charred Plant Remains and Charcoals ...................................................7
8 DISCUSSION.......................................................................................................9
9 REFERENCES ..................................................................................................10
APPENDIX 1 TRENCH SUMMARY TABLES......................................................11
Figures
Figure 1: Site and trench location with geophysical survey
Tables
Table 1: All finds by context
Table 2: Assessment of the charred plant remains and charcoal
List of plates
Plate 1: Cremation pit 303
Plate 2: Ditch 2107
Front cover: Trench 17
Back cover: South-east of Site during machining
ii
Land West of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St Ives
Cambridgeshire
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Summary
Wessex Archaeology was commissioned by CgMs Consulting on behalf of George
Wimpey, South Midlands to undertake an archaeological field evaluation of 3ha of
land adjacent to Houghton Road and located to the west of Orchard House, St. Ives,
Cambridgeshire, National Grid Reference 529925 272365.
The area either side of the Houghton Road has previously produced numerous
findspots of prehistoric worked flint. In the mid-19th
century, evidence of an early
Romano-British cremation cemetery, with an impressive array of finds, was found to
the southwest of the Site, although the precise location remains unknown.
The Site is proposed for residential development, for which outline planning
permission has been granted. A condition of the planning consent (Condition 14)
requires the implementation of a programme of archaeological assessment to be
undertaken to inform the determination of a future detailed planning application.
An initial geophysical survey of the Site was arranged by CgMs and was undertaken
in advance of the evaluation. The results of the survey identified a number of
anomalies, which indicated that the Site had the potential to contain archaeological
features. The results of the geophysical survey were used to locate evaluation trenches
to ensure areas of potential archaeological significance were targeted and fully
assessed.
The evaluation was undertaken in late February and early March 2007 and comprised
the machine excavation of 22 trial trenches, each approximately 30m by 1.8m in size.
<Node id="5519"/>The majority of the trenches contained no archaeological remains<Node id="5583"/>. Two shallow
undated ditches were identified in three trenches (Trenches 14, 21 and 23) and a series
of burnt tree throws were noted (Trenches 18, 20 and 21). Extensive evidence was
found across the Site for medieval/Post-medieval ridge and furrow, which broadly
runs across the site, east to west.
One trench (Trench 3) was found to contain significant archaeology, in the form of a
pit containing an undated cremation burial (303), which was truncated by the
medieval/Post-medieval ridge and furrow. Additional trenching radiating from this
feature did not identify any further archaeological features in the immediate area.
iii
Land West of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St Ives
Archaeological Evaluation Report
Acknowledgements
Wessex Archaeology would like to thank Rob Bourn of CgMs Consulting for
commissioning the work. Wessex Archaeology would also like to acknowledge the
help and assistance of Kasia Gdaniec, who monitored the evaluation on behalf of
Cambridgeshire County Council during the course of the fieldwork.
The project was managed on behalf of Wessex Archaeology by Andy Manning. The
fieldwork was directed in the field by Jamie Wright, assisted by Barry Hennessy,
Charlotte Coles and Patrice de Rijk. The report was prepared by Jamie Wright and
Andy Manning, with the illustrations prepared by Linda Coleman. The environmental
processing was undertaken by Laura Catlin, the bulk samples were assessed by Dr
Chris J. Stevens and Sarah F. Wyles. The charcoal and the requirements for
radiocarbon dating were assessed by Dr Catherine Chisham and the cremated remains
were assessed by Jackie McKinley. The finds were assessed by Rachel Seager Smith.
iv
Land West of Orchard House
Houghton Road
St Ives
Cambridgeshire
Archaeological Evaluation Report
1 PROJECT BACKGROUND
1.1 Introduction
1.1.1 Wessex Archaeology was commissioned by CgMs Consulting on behalf of
George Wimpey, South Midlands to undertake an archaeological field
evaluation by trial trenching at land west of Orchard House, Houghton Road,
St. Ives, Cambridgeshire (hereafter `the Site').
1.1.2 The Site comprises a rectangular plot of farmland and measures
approximately 215m by 140m in size, an area of 3ha. The Site is centred on
National Grid Reference 529925 272365 (Figure 1).
1.1.3 Outline planning permission (Planning Application H/04/02199/OUT) has
been granted for residential development of the Site. A condition of the
planning consent (Condition 14) requires the implementation of a programme
of archaeological work, in accordance with a Written Scheme of
Investigation (WSI), to be approved in writing by the Local Planning
Authority, in advance of any archaeological fieldwork.
1.1.4 A Design Brief for Archaeological Evaluation was prepared by
Cambridgeshire Archaeology Planning Countryside Advice (CAPCA
2007).
1.1.5 An initial geophysical survey of the Site was arranged by CgMs and was
undertaken in advance of the evaluation. The results of the survey were used
to target evaluation trenches to ensure areas of identified, or potential,
archaeological significance were fully assessed.
1.1.6 A Project Design setting out the strategy and methodology by which Wessex
Archaeology would implement the programme of archaeological evaluation
was submitted to, and approved by the Senior Archaeologist with CAPCA,
acting on behalf of the Local Planning Authority, prior to the commencement
of the field evaluation programme.
1.2 Site Location, Use and Geology
1.2.1 The Site comprises a sub-rectangular section of farmland, bounded by
Houghton Road to the south, residential housing to the east, farmland to the
west and playing fields to the north. (Figure 1).
1
1.2.2 At the time of the evaluation the Site comprised pasture land. The western
half of the Site was fairly flat, lying at a height of 33m above Ordnance
Datum (aOD) with a gentle downwards slope towards the eastern boundary,
which lay at a height of 30.30m aOD.
1.2.3 The Site is located on Upper Jurassic Ampth Clay, capped by Quaternary
Boulder Clay (Geological Survey of Great Britain 1975). Lying
approximately 1km to the south of the Site is the Great Ouse River. A narrow
exposure of Oxford Clay and Corallian Beds is mapped between the Site and
the River, which is fringed by 1st
and 2nd
Terrace gravels.
2 ARCHAEOLOGICAL/HISTORICAL BACKGROUND
2.1 Archaeological and Historical Background
2.1.1 The Cambridgeshire Historic Environment Record (CHER) contains a total
of 13 recorded archaeological findspots or sites, either on the Site or within
750m of the Site boundaries. A summary of the results is included below.
2.1.2 The majority of these recorded sites (8 in all) are prehistoric in date and
comprise small Mesolithic (8500-4000BC) or Neolithic flint scatters (4000-
2400BC), which are located in a broad band to the west and especially to the
south of the Site. This material is likely to be related to prehistoric activity,
focused on the gravel terraces of the Great Ouse.
Mesolithic
2.1.3 A microburin was found at Houghton Farm, 350m to the west of the Site, and
worked flints adjacent to St Ives Thicket, 400m to the south of the Site.
Neolithic
2.1.4 A worked flake was recovered from The Hayards, 750m to the west of the
Site, and a flint blade Houghton Hill, 300m to the west of the Site. Small
scatters of between two and nine flints are recorded at Houghton Grange,
400m to the southwest of the Site, The Grange 200m to the south-west and
two scatters adjacent to St Ives Thicket, 400m to the south of the Site. These
scatters have included arrowheads, scrapers, awls, burins and waste flakes.
Romano-British
2.1.5 A small number of findspots and sites of this period are known (five in total).
2.1.6 A small number of scattered artefacts, including coins, pottery and
metalwork have been found at Houghton H Farm, 450m to the west of the
Site, and pottery and metalwork were also recovered from St Ives Thicket,
350-700m to the south of the Site. Within the eastern area of the Site itself, a
small piece of bronze metal work was recorded as being recovered from a
builder's trench.
Medieval/post medieval
2.1.7 <Node id="11686"/>Although no later finds are recorded on the CHER<Node id="11734"/>, surviving traces of likely
medieval and post medieval ridge and furrow cultivation is clearly evident in
2
fields surrounding the Site, associated with the settlement at Houghton,
which dates from the early medieval period.
3 AIMS OF THE FIELDWORK PROGRAMME
3.1 Objectives
3.1.1 The objectives of the evaluation were to;
· clarify the presence/absence and extent of any buried archaeological
remains within the Site that may be threatened by development
· identify, within the constraints of the evaluation, the date, character,
condition and depth of any surviving remains within the Site.
· assess the degree of existing impacts to sub-surface horizons and to
document the extent of archaeological survival of buried deposits.
3.2 Research Framework
3.2.1 The recorded CHER sites and findspots highlight the potential for early
prehistoric flint scatters, Early Romano-British burials and possible
settlement and medieval/Post medieval cultivation.
3.2.2 The principal themes to be examined by the evaluation were;
· to test the northwards extent of the early flint scatters, which are
presently mainly recorded to the south of the Houghton Road
· to investigate whether the Romano-British cemetery extends further to
the north of the Houghton Road and/or evidence to support the
presence of additional cemeteries or associated settlement
· to investigate the extent and preservation of medieval/post medieval
cultivation within the Site
· to facilitate judgements on the status of the archaeological resource and
allow the formulation of an appropriate response ('a mitigation
strategy') to the impact of the proposed development on any surviving
archaeological remains, if required.
3.2.3 The evaluation was carried out in accordance with the relevant guidance
given in the Institute of Field Archaeologist's Standard and Guidance for
Archaeological Field Evaluation (revised 1999).
4 METHODOLOGY
4.1 Fieldwork
General
4.1.1 The evaluation comprised the excavation of an initial 22 trial trenches, each
measuring 30m by 1.8m and representing a 5% sample of the available 3ha
Site (Figure 1). The trenches were targeted on anomalies identified by the
geophysical survey, undertaken in advance of the evaluation (Stratascan
3
2007). Following comments from the Senior Archaeologist with CAPCA, a
number of changes in the trench arrangement were made.
4.1.2 The trenches were surveyed by Global Positioning System to ensure that the
trenches were accurately located on areas of archaeological potential and tied
into the OS National Grid.
4.1.3 All trenches were stripped using a mechanical excavator, under constant
archaeological supervision. All overburden was removed to the top of the
natural geology or the top of the archaeological deposits, whichever was
higher.
4.1.4 All recording was on Wessex Archaeology pro forma sheets in accordance
with Wessex Archaeology guidelines for fieldwork recording. A full
photographic record was kept comprising black and white negatives, colour
transparencies and digital images. All site drawings were at an appropriate
scale, typically 1:10 for sections and 1:20 for plans.
4.1.5 One trench (Trench 3) was identified as containing a likely human cremation
burial. The remains were completely excavated in accordance with the
standards set out in the IFA Technical Paper 13, Excavation and post-
excavation treatment of cremated and inhumed remains under licence (Ref
07-0029), obtained in advance from the Department of Constitutional
Affairs.
4.1.6 Following on-site consultation with the Senior Archaeologist with CAPCA,
additional trenching was undertaken, radiating from the cremation burial, to
locate any further such features. The fieldwork was undertaken between 26th
February and 6th
March 2007.
5 RESULTS
5.1 Introduction
5.1.1 The evaluation found <Node id="15542"/>no evidence for significant archaeological features<Node id="15593"/>,
with the exception of a single undated cremation burial (303) within the
eastern area of the Site and a pattern of medieval/Post-medieval ridge and
furrow running east-west throughout the extent of the Site.
5.1.2 Context numbers referred to in this report were trench specific and consisted
of the trench number followed by two digits, so that e.g. context 103 was
located in Trench 1 and 310 in Trench 3.
5.1.3 A trench summary of the contexts recorded within each trench is contained in
Appendix 1.
4
5.2 Soil Profile
5.2.1 Geological deposits were encountered immediately below topsoil.
5.2.2 Solid geology (Ampth Clays) was not encountered but the drift (Boulder
Clay) was. This highly calcareous clay was generally covered by presumed
periglacial deposits - a c. 0.2m depth of silty clay with varying proportions of
inclusions and colours and sometimes with 0.2m wide bands of coarse sandy
clay. Cut into the natural clays were furrows of medieval or post medieval
ploughing. The furrows were 0.7m wide and c. 7m apart.
5.2.3 Ceramic field drains and mole plough scars were frequently encountered
during machining, reinforcing the initial impressions of a waterlogged soil.
5.3 Geophysical Anomalies and Negative Features
5.3.1 A comparison of features exposed by machining and the geophysical
anomalies shows that the non-intrusive survey had accurately predicted the
ridge and furrow which was recorded in most of the trenches.
5.3.2 A linear anomaly in the south-west of the Site was present in Trenches 21
and 23, extending further to the south than on the original plot. A second
short linear anomaly coincided with a burnt tree throw in the eastern end of
Trench 18. Only one of the anomalies interpreted as possible pits was
positively uncovered (in Trench 20) and was identified as a burnt tree throw.
5.3.3 The southern edge of the large oval anomaly to the west of centre of the Site
was targeted in Trench 18, but only an unusually dense patch of gravel was
present. The square anomaly in the southwest of the Site was investigated in
Trench 21 and was found to be the result of modern disturbance.
5.4 Archaeological features
5.4.1 An undated cremation burial, two undated shallow ditches, a small number of
tree throws and the widespread remains of ridge and furrow were the only
archaeological features observed.
Cremation Burial 303
5.4.2 A subcircular shallow pit, 303, 0.56m in diameter and only 0.06m in depth,
containing abundant charcoal, burnt bone and burnt or fired clay was
uncovered in the northwestern end of Trench 3, located close to the eastern
boundary of the Site (Plate 1). Due to charcoal staining of the natural clay,
into which the pit had been cut, the pit was excavated to a total depth of
0.17m, to ensure the complete removal of the fill.
5.4.3 The upper 0.06m of the pit fill, 304, contained the majority of the artefacts
and ecofacts. The same materials were also in what appeared to be the upper
part of the natural clay but in vastly reduced quantities. It now appears that
drying and shrinking of the natural clay had allowed material to move
downwards from the pit fill, leading to contamination of the underlying
natural clay. The cremation deposit was excavated in quadrants by layer and
5
was 100% sampled. The pit appears to have been truncated by the ridge and
furrow ploughing.
Ditch 2107/2304
5.4.4 A shallow ditch 2107/2304, at least 25m in length, 0.80m in width and 0.30m
in depth, was uncovered running north-south through Trenches 21 and 23
(Plate 2). <Node id="19110"/>No artefacts were recovered<Node id="19137"/>.
Ditch 1403
5.4.5 Aligned northwest to southeast and exposed for a length of 4m this ditch was
0.6m wide and 0.25m deep at the level of machining. It contained a single,
f and contained no dating evidence.
Tree Throws
5.4.6 Tree throws that had been subsequently burnt were present in Trenches 18,
20 and 21. Tree throws in Trenches 18 and 20 (1803 and 2003) were both
classic examples with a crescent shape and concave to the east or north-east.
Both tree throws showed strong evidence of burning with black and red fills
on the surface that feathered off into in situ natural clays. No dating material
was recovered from any of the tree throws.
5.4.7 In Trench 21 there were two small features (2103 and 2105) containing
charcoal, which have been interpreted as three throws. <Node id="19916"/>There was no
scorching of the natural clays<Node id="19959"/> and the episodes of burning must have been
short lived. Feature 2103 was slightly larger than 2105 at 0.4m by 0.65m and
0.15m deep. Both features contained common charcoal but <Node id="20136"/>no other artefacts<Node id="20154"/>.
6 FINDS
6.1 General
6.1.1 A small quantity of finds was recovered during the evaluation, deriving from
four stratified and five unstratified contexts within eight trenches. The
assemblage (quantified by context in Table 1) consists largely of worked
flint, with minor occurrences of modern pottery (unstratified in trench 4);
burnt, unworked flint, and small amounts of fired clay and cremated human
bone.
6.2 Worked and Burnt Flint
6.2.1 The worked flint comprises flake and core material; one core (unstratified)
may have been reused as a hammerstone. There are no other tools or utilised
pieces. Most pieces are edge damaged, and the degree of patination varies. In
the absence of diagnostic pieces this small group cannot be closely dated;
<Node id="20900"/>none was found in stratified contexts<Node id="20937"/>.
6.2.2 The burnt flint is of unknown date, as are the small quantities of fired clay
and cremated bone recovered from pit 303.
6
6.3 Human Bone
6.3.1 The cremated human bone was found unurned, and only small quantities are
represented (a total of 320g, most of which came from the pit fill, 304). The
bone, which represents the remains of an adult, is in fragmentary condition,
well oxidised, and little trabecular bone survives. Pit 303 was excavated in
quadrants and the soil sieved for total bone recovery; the distribution of bone
quantity across the quadrants appears fairly consistent, but a high proportion
of skull vault fragments were noted in one quadrant.
6.3.2 Further analysis of the bone would be needed to confirm details of age and
sex (if condition of the bone allows), and allowing comment on pyre
technology, as well as examining the bone distribution in more detail, in
order to highlight possible patterning, and therefore aspects of funerary
ritual.
Table 1: All finds by context (number / weight in grammes)
Tr Context
Worked
Flint
Burnt
Flint
Fired
Clay
Human
Bone Pottery
- unstrat. 1/115
3 304 250g 315g
3 305 5g
4 unstrat. 1/18 1/7
5 unstrat. 1/121
6 unstrat. 3/107
8 unstrat. 1/132
18 1804 1/7
20 2004 6/38
TOTAL 7/493 7/45 250g 320g 1/7
7 ENVIRONMENTAL
7.1 Introduction
7.1.1 Ten samples were taken from quadranted spits of the cremation deposit (304)
in Pit 303 and the underlying natural deposit (305) to retrieve any charred
plant remains and wood charcoal and datable finds as well as cremated bone.
7.2 Charred Plant Remains and Charcoals
7.2.1 Bulk samples were processed by standard flotation methods; the flot retained
on a 0.5 mm mesh, residues fractionated into 4mm, 2mm and 1mm fractions
and dried. The coarse fractions ( 4 mm) were sorted, weighed and discarded.
Flots were scanned under a x10 ­ x40 stereo-binocular microscope and the
presence of charred remains quantified (Table 2) to record the preservation
and nature of the charred plant and charcoal remains. Preliminary
identifications of dominant or important taxa are noted below, following the
nomenclature of Stace (1997).
7.2.2 The flots were generally larger than average, but contained a high number of
roots (up to 80%) and probable modern seeds that may be indicative of
7
stratigraphic movement, reworking or the degree of contamination by later
intrusive elements. Charred material comprised varying degrees of
preservation.
Charred plant remains
7.2.3 Very little charred material was retrieved from the samples. Three samples
produced charred grain fragments; the indeterminate grain fragment and
possible barley (Hordeum vulgare) grain were poorly preserved, whereas the
free-threshing wheat (Triticum aestivum) grain was in better condition.
7.2.4 However as this grain is more common from Saxon and later sites, it is likely
that it is intrusive material, particularly as the flot consisted of 80% roots.
The weed seeds recorded in the samples were mainly goosefoots
(Chenopodium sp.) and one seed of speedwell (Veronica sp.). They were all
considered likely to be modern intrusive seeds.
Charcoal
7.2.5 Charcoal was noted from the flots of the bulk samples and is recorded in
Table 2. Very little charcoal of greater than 4mm was recorded. The charcoal
was mainly mature wood fragments.
7.2.6 The charcoal was relatively plentiful from the feature as a whole. However, it
occurs at a shallow depth and the degree of rooting (and by inference
bioturbation) is exceptionally high. There is a high possibility therefore of
contamination of the sample with older or indeed more recent material.
7.2.7 Although the wood charcoal is physically dateable, it is not recommended
that radiocarbon dating be attempted due to this risk of contamination, the
date gained may not relate to the date of cremation. The actual cremated
bone is small in terms of volume and individual fragment size and is also not
well-suited to dating.
8
Table 2: Assessment of the charred plant remains and charcoal
Flot Residue
Feature
type/no
Context Sample size
litres
flot size
ml
Grain Chaff Charred
other
Seeds Charcoal
 4mm
Other Charcoal
 4mm
Cremation Pit 303
Surface 304 1 1 25 60
- - A Chenopodium
(Prob. modern)
C - -
Surface 304 3 10 80 40
- - A* Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
C - -
NE Quad 304 4 2 15 70
- - B Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
C Valloni
a (C)
-
NW Quad 304 5 2 20 75
- - B Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
C Valloni
a (C)
-
SE Quad 304 6 2.5 50 50
C - B 1 x ?Barley
grain
Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
B Valloni
a (C)
-
SW Quad 304 7 2 50 65
- - B Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
C -
NE Quad 305 8 1 10 80
- - C Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
- -
NW Quad 305 9 3 15 80
C - C 1 x
indeterminate
grain
Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
- Valloni
a (C)
-
SE Quad 305 10 3 25 80
C - C 1 x free-
threshing wheat
grain
Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
C Valloni
a (C)
-
SW Quad 305 11 3 20 80
- - C Chenopodium
(Prob. modern
- - -
KEY: A** = exceptional, A* = 30+ items, A = 10 items, B = 9 - 5 items, C = 5 items Analysis: C =
charcoal, P = plant, C14 = radiocarbon suggestions
NOTE: 1flot is total, but flot in superscript = % of rooty material.
8 DISCUSSION
8.1.1 The majority of the evaluation trenches identified no evidence for significant
archaeological remains. The evaluation identified a widespread pattern of
ridge and furrow, which runs east to west and covers the entire Site. In
addition, two shallow undated ditches were identified in three trenches
(Trenches 14, 21 and 23) and a series of burnt tree throws were also noted
(Trenches 18, 20 and 21), although none of these features contained any
datable evidence.
8.1.2 The only significant archaeological feature found was cremation burial
within Pit 303, at the eastern edge of the Site. <Node id="26653"/>No datable material was found
with the cremated remains<Node id="26708"/>, which appear to have been heavily truncated by
later medieval/Post-medieval ploughing. Additional trenching radiating from
this pit did not identify any further archaeological features in the immediate
area.
9
8.1.3 In relation to previously recorded findspots, the cremation burial was found
close to the location of the fragment of Romano-British copper alloy
recovered from a builder's trench at the eastern edge of the Site. However,
the cremated deposit, due to modern contamination, has little potential to
provide an accurate radiocarbon date, which would have enabled the burial to
be put into context.
8.1.4 The cremation burial itself could be related to the early Romano-British
cremation cemetery found in the mid 19th century, although the precise
location of this cemetery is unclear. While it is possible that the Site could
have contained further cremation burials- subsequently removed by later
ploughing- <Node id="27633"/>no evidence for residual Romano-British finds<Node id="27678"/> or scattered bone
and charcoal deposits was observed across the Site. On the available
evidence, the cremation burial appears to have been either an isolated burial
or a possible outlier of the main cemetery.<Node id="27887"/> In addition, no evidence at all was
found to suggest settlement<Node id="27951"/>, which antiquarian references associated with the
cemetery.
8.1.5 A small quantity of residual worked and burnt flint was recovered across the
Site, largely collected as unstratified material. All the worked flint (core and
flakes) is undatable, but is st consistent with the previously recorded small
scatters of Mesolithic and Neolithic worked flint, which has been regularly
found in the vicinity of the Site.
9 REFERENCES
CAPCA, 2007, Design Brief for Archaeological Evaluation, Unpublished
Brief
Geological Survey of Great Britain, 1975, Huntington, Sheet 187, Drift
Deposits, 1:50,000
Stratascan, 2007, Geophysical Survey Report; Orchard House, Houghton, St.
Ives Unpublished Client Report ref. J2304
Stace, C., 1997. New flora of the British Isles. 2nd
Edition. Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press
Wessex Archaeology, 2007, Land West of Orchard House, Houghton Road,
St. Ives, Cambridgeshire; Written Scheme of Investigation for an
Archaeological Evaluation, Unpublished Client Rep. Ref. 65440
10
APPENDIX 1 TRENCH SUMMARY TABLES
TRENCH 1
NGR 530007.2, 272418.5, 30.3 529976.2, 272421.5, 31.0
Dimensions Length 31.1, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.45 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
101 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. Relict ploughsoil. 0 ­ 0.25
102 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with coarse sand. Several ceramic land drains
present, some ridge and furrow ploughing in the E containing animal bone and
cinders/coke (not retained)
 0.25
E end was flooded.
TRENCH 2
NGR 529974.7, 272391.9, 31.3 530005.6, 272393.0, 30.4
Dimensions Length 30.9, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.38 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
201 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. Relict ploughsoil. 0 ­ 0.25
202 Natural: A yellowish brown clay/coarse sandy clay with frequent medium gravel.
Occasional patches of highly calcareous clay.
 0.25
A 9.7m long and 0.3m wide slot was excavated to 0.4m max. along to N edge of trench
to try (unsuccessfully) to locate geophysical anomaly.
TRENCH 3
NGR 529975.9, 272386.9, 31.2 530008.0, 272357.2, 30.5
Dimensions Length 146.9 (total), Width 11.0 (max.), Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
301 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0 - 0.25
302 Natural: Yellowish brown silty clay with frequent pea grit, gravel (flint and chalk).
Patches of orange brown coarse sandy clay.
 0.25
303 Shallow pit: A 0.50m by 0.56m oval with a concave base at 0.17m depth. Possibly over-
excavated where bone and burnt/fired clay had migrated down cracks in natural.
Excavated in quadrants and 100% sampled.
0.25 ­ 0.42
304 Fill: The upper f of 303 was a very dark grey/black with much charcoal, burnt bone re
burnt/fired clay and occasional small flint gravel. Sharp boundary with 305.
0.25 ­ 0.31
305 Fill: A yellowish brown silty clay with rare small flint gravel. Although pos. in situ
natural this contained burnt bone, charcoal and red clay. The artefacts may have fallen
down cracks opened during long periods of dry weather or bioturbation may have been
responsible.
0.31 ­ 0.42
A 11m by 7m area was opened around 303 and 116m of extra trench excavated in a star
radiating from it.
TRENCH 4
NGR 529986.1, 272341.2, 31.2 530014.4, 272327.8, 30.53
Dimensions Length 31.3, Width 2.5 (max.), Max. depth 0.35 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
401 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0 - 0.22
402 Natural: Yellowish brown clay with frequent pea grit, occasional gravel and chalk. Rare
patches of coarse sandy clay.
 0.22
403 Fill: Greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0.22 ­ 0.42
404 Ditch: A N to S V-shaped ditch that was 0.2m wide and produced post medieval pottery. 0.22 ­ 0.42
TRENCH 5
NGR 529975.4, 272345.8, 31.4 529981.1, 272315.1, 31.4
Dimensions Length 31.3, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.38 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
501 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0 ­ 0.25
502 Natural: A yellowish brown clay with pea grit and flint and chalk gravel. 0.25
11
TRENCH 6
NGR 529967.0, 272322.5, 31.5 529935.4, 272322.0, 32.1
Dimensions Length 31.6, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.38 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
601 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0 - 0.25
602 Natural: Yellowish brown clay with frequent pea grit, occasional small flint gravel and
occasional small rounded chalk.
 0.25
TRENCH 7
NGR 529956.3, 272341.9, 31.7 529940.1, 272367.9, 31.9
Dimensions Length 30.6, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.48 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
701 Topsoil: A brown silty clay with rare flint, some rounded chalk and rare pea grit. 0 ­ 0.30
702 Natural: Pale greyish brown to yellowish brown silty clay. Some small chalk fragments
and rare flint gravel.
 0.30
TRENCH 8
NGR 529935.4, 272377.2, 32.0 529965.1, 272385.5, 31.4
Dimensions Length 30.7, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
801 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0 ­ 0.25
802 Natural: A yellowish brown clay with occasional small gravel. 0.25
Much of the E was flooded.
TRENCH 9
NGR 529939.6, 272394.0, 32.0 529957.0, 272418.7, 31.5
Dimensions Length 30.2, Width 2.4, Max. depth 0.47 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
901 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare medium to large flint gravel and some
brick fragments.
0 - 0.25
902 Natural: Pale yellowish brown silty clay with patches of large flint gravel and in the
middle of the trench an area of calcareous silty clay.
 0.25
Several field drains ran NE to SW across the trench and one N to S.
TRENCH 10
NGR 529928.2, 272411.2, 32.1 529896.6, 272410.6, 32.2
Dimensions Length 31.6, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1001 Topsoil: A brown silty clay with rare flint, some rounded chalk and rare pea grit. 0 ­ 0.25
1002 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with occasion coarse calcareous sand and small
stones and some flint gravel.
 0.25
Much of the trench flooded.
TRENCH 11
NGR 529909.0, 272405.6, 32.2 529909.0, 272375.8, 32.3
Dimensions Length 29.8, Width 2.0, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1001 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare to common medium gravel. 0 ­ 0.30
1002 Natural: A yellowish brown clay with occasional medium and some large gravel. Very
calcareous in S of trench.
 0.25
Three approx. E to W furrows crossed the trench the N third of which was under water.
12
TRENCH 13
NGR 529923.7, 272363.4, 32.1 529892.1, 272363.4, 32.3
Dimensions Length 31.6, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1301 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare medium to large flint gravel and some
brick fragments.
0 - 0.20
1302 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with coarse sand. 0.20
Large puddles in the whole trench.
TRENCH 14
NGR 529912.1, 272338.8, 32.3 529882.1, 272339.7, 32.6
Dimensions Length 30.0, Width 2.1, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1401 Topsoil: A brown silty clay with rare flint, some rounded chalk and rare pea grit. 0 ­ 0.26
1402 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with calcareous pea grit in the centre and gravel
in W of trench.
 0.26
1403 Ditch: A NW to SE aligned 0.6m wide linear feature with gently sloping sides and
rounded base.
0.26 ­ 0.51
1404 Fill: A pale greyish brown silty clay containing rare medium flint gravel. The only fill,
from which no dating evidence was recovered.
0.26 ­ 0.51
TRENCH 15
NGR 529905.5, 272323.3, 32.3 529890.2, 272297.7, 32.6
Dimensions Length 29.38, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.45 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1501 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare medium gravel. 0 ­ 0.25
1502 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay. In the centre and NE was very calcareous with
chalk peagrit and very small stones, some rare flint gravel.
 0.25
Two approx. E to W furrows crossed the trench and two or three field drains were
present.
TRENCH 16
NGR 529871.4, 272304.1, 32.8 529870.6, 272334.7, 32.8
Dimensions Length 30.5, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.45 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1601 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare flint gravel and rare chalk fragments. 0 - 0.25
1602 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with rare medium gravel and rare small chalk
fragments. Some large flint.
 0.25
Four furrows and a land drain were present.
TRENCH 17
NGR 529862.1, 272862.1, 32.8 529844.1, 272376.1, 33.0
Dimensions Length 29.6, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.38 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1701 Topsoil: A brown silty clay. 0 ­ 0.22
1702 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay 0.22
Two furrows crossed the trench
TRENCH 18
NGR 529894.3, 272373.0, 32.3 529863.5, 272372.3, 32.7
Dimensions Length 30.8, Width 2.1, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1800 Topsoil: A greyish brown sandy clay with rare medium gravel. 0 ­ 0.30
1801 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay. In the centre and NE was very calcareous with
chalk peagrit and very small stones, some rare flint gravel.
 0.30
1802 Natural: Twelve metres from the W end was a patch of silty clay containing many
medium and large flints. This was 2m across, was cut to the N by ridge and furrow and
coincided with a large positive oval geophysical anomaly.
 0.30
13
1803 Tree throw: A crescentic feature, concave to the NE. It was 2m across, shallow to SW
and overhung to NE.
0.30 ­ 0.75
1804 Fill: A yellowish brown silty clay that contained a 50mm thick charcoal rich lens at a
depth of 0.3m.
0.30 ­ 0.75
TRENCH 19
NGR 529867.1, 272399.3,32.6 529885.8, 272421.3, 32.4
Dimensions Length 28.9, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
1901 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare flint gravel and rare chalk fragments. 0 - 0.25
1902 Natural: A mid yellowish brown silty clay with occasional to frequent peagrit and very
small gravel
 0.25
Land drains and mole ploughing evident.
TRENCH 20
NGR 529858.5, 272399.4, 32.7 529830.3, 272409.2, 33.2
Dimensions Length 29.8, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.37 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
2001 Topsoil: A grey silty clay with few small angular flints. Some fine roots and a sharp
boundary. The top had a small blocky/large crumb structure and the base large blocky.
0 ­ 0.20
2002 Natural: mostly silty clay varying between pale yellow brown and brown in colour.
Common medium angular flint and few medium rounded chalk fragments. Bands of
reddish brown fine sandy clay, 0.2m wide were present. Patches were stone free and few
large flints were present.
 0.20
2003 Tree throw: A 1.5m by 1.1m oval shape with gently sloping sides and a flat base. A
former 0.1m diameter root was evident descending through the natural.
0.20 ­ 0.37
2004 Fill: A cresentic f around the W of the tree hollow. Strongly coloured red and black. 0.20 ­ 0.33
2005 Fill: A yellowish brown silty clay redeposited natural mostly to E of 2003.
TRENCH 21
NGR 529843.9, 272295.0, 33.5 529819.6, 272295.6, 33.9
Dimensions Length 22.4, Width 2.1, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
2101 Topsoil: A greyish brown sandy clay with rare medium gravel. 0 ­ 0.20
2102 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with common peagrit, gravel and rounded chalk.
There were patches of paler silty clay and of sandy clay.
 0.20
2103 Burnt tree roots: A subrectangle of 0.40m by 0.65m. It had a max. depth of 0.1m
decreasing to 0.02m in the recorded section.
0.20 ­ 0.30
2104 F of 2103: A redeposited natural containing common charcoal fragments. 0.20 ­ 0.30
2105 Burnt tree roots: A slightly irregular oval of 0.34m by 0.50m with a concave
undulating base.
0.20 ­ 0.33
2106 F of 2105: Redeposited natural containing few small stones and common charcoal. 0.20 ­ 0.33
2107 Ditch: A N to S ditch that was 1.8m wide. The W side sloped at c. 45º to a rounded
base but the E side had a c. 0.8m wide horizontal step ­ the ditch may originally have
been 0.8m wide but obscured by a hedge to its E.
0.20 ­ 0.45
2108 F of 2107: A yellowish brown silty clay with occasional gravel. 0.20 ­ 0.45
2109 F of 2107: A pale greyish brown silty clay with frequent flint and chalk stones. Not
present in section.
0.25 ­ 0.35
2110 F of 2107: A yellowish brown clay with frequent manganese dioxide staining filling a
slight hollow at the base of the cut. Not present in section.
0.35 ­ 0.45
TRENCH 22
NGR 529855.2, 272334.2, 33.1 529826.1, 272343.7, 33.6
Dimensions Length 29.1, Width 2.2, Max. depth 0.30 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
2201 Topsoil: A greyish brown silty clay with rare flint gravel and rare chalk fragments. 0 - 0.25
2202 Natural: A pale to mid yellowish brown clay with frequent peagrit and occasional small
gravel
 0.25
Land drains ran N to S and mole ploughing ran both E to W and N to S.
14
TRENCH 23
NGR 529847.2, 272312.1, 33.3 529820.5, 272307.8, 33.9
Dimensions Length 27.1, Width 2.3, Max. depth 0.40 (m)
Context Description Depth (m)
2301 Topsoil: A grey silty clay with few small angular flints. Some fine roots and a sharp
boundary. The top had a small blocky/large crumb structure and the base large blocky.
0 ­ 0.20
2302 Natural: A yellowish brown silty clay with few to common peagrit, gravel and chalk
very small stones.
 0.20
2303 Fill: A yellowish brown silty clay with occasional flint gravel.
2304 Ditch: A N to S, 1m wide ditch, the same as 2107. It was not excavated in this trench
due to flooding.
0.20 ­ 0.33
15
30.4330.39
30.3430.46
30.42
30.40
30.6730.9631.1731.3431.6431.96
32.1032.1632.14
32.16
32.3332.54
32.6532.81
32.9933.16
33.21
33.35
33.41
33.54
33.46
33.81
34.03
33.72
33.8233.9534.00
34.02
34.18
34.09
34.5434.51
34.48 34.41 34.32 34.24
34.06
33.82
33.58
33.33
33.05
32.87
32.80
32.77
32.61
32.43
32.26
32.08
31.86
31.72 31.62
31.40
31.15
30.83
30.52
30.21
29.88
33.87
33.98
34.06
30.3930.54
30.99
31.55
32.03
32.20
32.33
32.56
33.0533.09
33.75
30.19
30.1730.18
30.1129.8630.0030.02
29.94
33.80
33.85
33.97
33.94
34.32
34.10
34.2534.12
34.1734.10
33.59
33.33
32.86
32.37
32.11
31.87
31.36
31.25
31.06
30.83
30.55
30.01
30.02 29.18 29.15
29.2429.3529.4029.4929.5129.5829.55
29.6129.5829.52
30.29
30.67
31.02
31.32
31.59
31.84
32.06
32.34
32.56
32.75
32.92
33.13
33.35
33.64
33.93
34.20
34.37
32.84
32.83
33.0233.04
33.12
33.46
33.2633.37
30.28
32.51
31.02
30.19
29.95
30.72
30.43
30.41
30.32
30.33
30.30
30.3230.34
30.82
31.18
31.57
31.9832.14
32.1632.32
32.5132.64
32.88
33.12
33.21
33.32
33.44
33.49
33.41
33.61
33.83
33.82
33.95
34.02 33.71
33.35
32.92
32.75
32.46
32.32
32.14
31.94
31.67
31.35
30.93
30.74
30.72
33.15
32.76
32.56
32.33
32.19
32.05
31.60
31.13
30.67
30.34
30.31
30.93
31.34
31.90
32.20
32.26
32.50
32.76
33.07
33.35
33.42
32.96
32.65
32.42
32.32
32.07
31.67
31.20
30.70
30.40
30.45
31.07
31.49
31.90
32.21
32.33
32.59
32.91
33.32
33.78
33.95
33.42
33.01
32.67
32.39
32.25
31.94
31.58
31.16
30.53
34.42 34.39 34.15
33.80
33.20
33.03
32.80
32.54
32.36
32.14
31.98
31.65
31.24
30.80
30.95 30.56
30.81
30.6230.5230.5930.5530.43
30.4930.4530.3730.3530.22
30.37 30.11
33.11
33.30
34.40 34.09
33.81
33.64
33.26
33.10
32.98
32.86
32.54
32.49
32.16
32.21
31.93
31.79
31.52
31.14
30.73
30.53
34.01
34.35
34.20
34.28 34.14
34.31
34.4234.13
30.80
30.68
30.55
30.80
33.87
33.98
33.96
33.9933.98
34.51
34.31
34.32
33.40
32.93
34.38
34.23
33.98
33.74
33.48
33.24
33.03
32.86
32.65
32.45
32.24
32.03
31.79
31.56
31.31
31.00
30.67
30.31
30.00
32.84
32.66
32.48
32.24
32.07
31.83
31.56
31.29
30.98
30.58
30.13
34.10
38.67
30.69
33.1633.21
HAWTHORN 2m
CROP EDGE
(WHEAT)
HAWTHORN 3m
FWS IN DITCH
BOLTED + SEALED
BLUE UPVC PIPE 200mm
BLUE UPVC PIPE 200mm
BLUEUPVCPIPE200mm
BLUEUPVCPIPE200mm
GREYUPVCPIPE200mm
ELECTRIC
ELECTRIC
STEEL PIPE
GREY PIPE POSSIBILY
BELOW ELECTRIC??
THRUST BLOCK
E
A
V
E
S
R
ID
G
E
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Tr Pit
Pipe
0.100
29.41
Pipe
29.55
Pipe
31.73
Pipe
31.94
Pipe
32.87
Pipe
32.79
Pipe
32.77
Pipe
31.81
Pipe
30.91
Pipe
29.83
Pipe
29.80
Pipe
29.40
Pipe
29.33
Pipe
29.24
Pipe
29.58
Pipe
32.90
Pipe
32.88
Pipe
32.84
Pipe
32.58
Pipe
31.54
Pipe
30.83
Pipe
30.57
Pipe
30.10
Pipe
29.64
Pipe
29.63
Pipe
29.81
30.50
30.75
31.25
31.50
31.75
32.25
32.50
32.75
33.25
33.50
33.75
33.75
30.50
30.75
31.25
31.50
31.75
32.25
32.50
32.75
33.25
30.50
30.75
31.25
31.50
31.75
32.25
32.50
32.75
33.25
33.50
31.00
32.00
33.00
34.00
34.00
31.00
32.00
33.00
31.00
32.00
33.00
TP
RS
RS
FH
FH
MK
MK
MHCL=
28.55
SV
SV
SV
BT
BT
BT
ICCL=
RS
RS
OAK
H 7.0
OAK
H 7.0
MAPLE
H 6.0MAPLE
H 6.0
MAPLE
H 7.0
POPLAR
H 18.0
LIME
H 6.0
ASH
H 12.0
ASH
H 10.0
ASH
H 10.0
ASH
H 12.0
ELM
H 8.0
HAWTHORN
HAWTHORN
HAWTHORN
TREE OF HEAVEN
WHITEBEAM
H 5.0
CRAB APPLE
H 8.0
FIELD MAPLE
H 6.0
FIELD MAPLE
H 7.0
OrchardHouse
+33.40
PW+BW HT 1.2
+33.05
PW+BW HT 1.2
31.89
+
+32.77
0.5/8.0
CHERRY
0.58.0
+32.23
+32.07
+31.26
+32.32
31.54
+
BW HT 1.1
32.51
+
+32.26
0.3/6.0
0.45/8.0
CHERRY
0.25/4.0
0.65/16.0
CHERRY
0.3/8.0
ASPHALT
32.77
+
SIGN
+32.70
0.65/16.0
+32.66
33.99
+
34.08
+
MOUND
EARTH
32.98
+
+32.78
0.3/6.0
0.25/6.0
1.5/14.0 1.0
HT
BW
0.6
BKW HT
0.5/14.0
6.0
MULTI/
2x0.4/12.0
33.14
+
0.7/16.0
+33.41
+32.80
33.72
+
33.91
+
34.09
+
+
+34.340
34.67
+
WATER METER
IC'S CL 34.34
+34.30HT 1.0
BW
34.36
+
32.82
33.03 31.91
31.91
32.07
32.03
32.20
32.25
32.38
2 O/H
34.45
34.22
34.31
BUS
STOP
BUS
STOP
1.80 2.75 2.75 1.80
BUS
LANE
ENDS
CYCLEWAY
BUS LANE
Wessex
Archaeology
The Site
The Site
271000
272000
273000
530000
531000
532000
529800
272400
Date:
Revision Number:
Scale:
Illustrator:
Path:
Reproduced from the 1995 Ordnance Survey 1:50 000 Explorer ®
© Crown copyright, Wessex Archaeology, Portway House, Old Sarum Park
Digital survey supplied by client.
This material is for client report only © Wessex Archaeology.
21/03/07
0
1:50 000 1:800 @ A3
LJC
Y:\PROJECTS\65440\D.. O..\
Site and trench location with geophysical survey Figure 1
map with the permission of the controller of Her Majesty's Stationery Office
Salisbury, Wiltshire. SP4 6EB. Licence Number: 100028190.
No unauthorised reproduction.
Report Figures\EVAL\07-03-21\65440eval.dwg
Tr 20
Tr 19 Tr 10
Tr 11
Tr 18
Tr 13
Tr 17
Tr 22
Tr 14
Tr 23
Tr 16
Tr 15
Tr 21
Tr 6
Tr 5
Tr 4
Tr 7
Tr 8
Tr 3
Tr 2Tr 9
Tr 1
Evaluation trench
Arrchaeology
Ridge and furrow
Tree throw hole
1403
2304
2107
404
303
272300
529900
523000
0 50m
Plates 1 2
Plate 1: Cremation pit 303
Plate 2: Ditch 2107
Wessex
Archaeology Y:\PROJECTS\64550\Drawing Office\Report Figures\EVAL\07_03_21\65440photos.cdr
LJC21/03/07
Path:
Illustrator:Date:
WESSEX ARCHAEOLOGY LIMITED.
Head Office: Portway House, Old Sarum Park, Salisbury, Wiltshire SP4 6EB.
Tel: 01722 326867 Fax: 01722 337562 info@wessexarch.co.uk www.wessexarch.co.uk
London Office: Unit 113, The Chandlery, 50 Westminster Bridge Road, London SE1 7QY.
Tel: 020 7953 7494 Fax: 020 7953 7499 london-info@wessexarch.co.uk www.wessexarch.co.uk
Registered Charity No. 287786. A company with limited liability registered in England No. 1712772.
<Node id="46656"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="5519" EndNode="5583">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="2" Type="Negation" StartNode="11686" EndNode="11734">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="3" Type="Negation" StartNode="19110" EndNode="19137">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="20900" EndNode="20937">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="5" Type="Negation" StartNode="26653" EndNode="26708">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="27633" EndNode="27678">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="7" Type="Negation" StartNode="27887" EndNode="27951">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="8" Type="Negation" StartNode="15542" EndNode="15593">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="9" Type="Negation" StartNode="19916" EndNode="19959">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="10" Type="Negation" StartNode="20136" EndNode="20154">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="46656">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
