<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO8859-1'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">text/plain</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/media/Data/Extracting_GreyLit/Extraction_Development/OPTIMA_Complete/documents/evaluationCorpus/wessexar1-5680.txt</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">docNewLineType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">LF</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>CUMBERLAND SCHOOL SPORTS HALL
BARKING ROAD, CANNING TOWN
LONDON E16
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION 
ASSESSMENT REPORT
Prepared on behalf of
London Borough of Newham
Environment and Regeneration Department
by
Wessex Archaeology
Unit 701
The Chandlery
50 Westminster Bridge Road
London SE1 7QY
Report reference: 55860
December 2004
© Wessex Archaeology Limited 2004 all rights reserved
r Wessex Archaeology Limited is a Registered Charity No. 287786
CONTENTS
1. Summary............................................................................................................i
2. Acknowledgements...........................................................................................ii
3. 1 INTRODUCTION............................................................................................1
4. 1.1 Project Background......................................................................................1
5. 1.2 The Site.........................................................................................................1
6. 2 Archaeological Background...........................................................................2
7. 3 methodology....................................................................................................2
8. 3.1 Excavation Strategy......................................................................................2
9. 3.2 Fieldwork Recording....................................................................................3
10. 3.3 Health and Safety.........................................................................................3
11. 4 results..............................................................................................................4
12. 5 Finds ...............................................................................................................5
13. 6 Discussion.......................................................................................................5
14. 7 conclusion ......................................................................................................6
15. 8 Proposals for further analysis and publication..............................................6
16. 9 Archive............................................................................................................6
17. 10 OASIS ...........................................................................................................7
18. 11 BIBLIOGRAPHY...........................................................................................7
19. APPENDIX 1: CONTEXT DESCRIPTIONS....................................................8
20. APPENDIX 2: OASIS Form............................................................................10
FIGURES
1 Location of Site and Excavation Area
2 Location of previous evaluation trenches and all archaeological features
3 Sections through features 309, 311, and 313
CUMBERLAND SCHOOL SPORTS HALL
BARKING ROAD, CANNING TOWN
LONDON E16
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION 
ASSESSMENT REPORT
Summary
Wessex Archaeology was commissioned by London Borough of Newham 
Environment and Regeneration Department to conduct an archaeological excavation 
at the site of the proposed Cumberland School Sports Hall, Barking Road, Newham, 
centred on NGR 540055, 181897.
The excavation follows an evaluation of the Site which found evidence for possible 
Roman activity along with a single prehistoric/Roman unurned cremation burial.
The excavation comprised a 12m x 18m area centred on a previous evaluation trench. 
The fieldwork was undertaken over four days, from the 5th
 to 8th
 April 2004.
Four separate features were found during the excavation. Three of these appear to be 
natural marshland channels and the fourth, a postmedieval drainage ditch.
The postmedieval activity in the area appears to have been curtailed by an episode of 
flooding which is represented by a thick layer of alluvium that overlies all features. 
The results of both the excavation and evaluation suggest that no further significant 
activities occurred in the area until its development in the 19th
 century. 
<Node id="4115"/>No further evidence for cremation burials was found during the excavation<Node id="4188"/>. 
It is proposed that further analysis of the cremation burial found during the evaluation 
be carried out to attempt to ascertain its date and that a summary report of the 
excavation be submitted for publication in The London Archaeologist.
 
i
Acknowledgements
Wessex Archaeology is grateful for the assistance and help provided by Bruce 
McSweeny of the London Borough of Newham Environment and Regeneration 
Department, and the staff of Cumberland School during the course of the project.
The project was monitored on behalf of the Local Planning Authority by Nick Truckle 
of the Greater London Archaeological Advisory Service.
The fieldwork was carried out by Susan Clelland and Claire Davies. The report was 
prepared by Susan Clelland with contributions from Lorraine Mepham and Jackie 
Mckinley (Finds) and Mark Roughly and Liz James (Illustrations). The project was 
managed on behalf of Wessex Archaeology by Robert Wardill.
ii
CUMBERLAND SCHOOL SPORTS HALL
BARKING ROAD, CANNING TOWN
LONDON E16
ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXCAVATION 
ASSESSMENT REPORT
1 INTRODUCTION
1.1 Project Background
1.1.1 Wessex Archaeology was commissioned by Newham Borough Council (the 
Client) to conduct an archaeological excavation on land at the site of a 
proposed sports hall at Cumberland School, Barking Road, Newham, centred 
on NGR 540055, 181897 (the Site). 
1.1.2 The works were carried out in accordance with a Written Scheme of 
Investigation (Wessex Archaeology 2004) which was approved by the 
Greater London Archaeological Advisory Service (GLASS) of English 
Heritage, and followed an earlier trenching evaluation of the Site carried out 
in 2003 (PreConstruct Archaeology Ltd). 
1.1.3 This document reports on the results of the excavation and sets out proposals 
for the further assessment of the findings and final publication of the project.
1.2 The Site
1.1.4 Cumberland School is located to the south of the A124 Barking Road. The 
proposed sports hall development is to be sited in the southeast corner of the 
school grounds (Figure 1).
1.1.5 The excavation area measured 12m x 18m and was positioned within the 
footprint of the proposed building, towards its southeast corner where pile 
foundations w be at their most dense. The position of the excavation area 
was also located to coincide with the site of a previous evaluation trench 
(Figure 2) where potentially significant archaeological remains were 
uncovered.
1.1.6 The ground surface of the excavation area was covered by grass. Natural 
geological deposits beneath the Site were found to comprise a light, yellow 
brickearth. 
1
2 ARCHAEOLOGICAL BACKGROUND
1.1.7 A desktop assessment of the Site (PreConstruct Archaeology 2003a) 
indicated there was high potential for prehistoric material to be found at the 
Site. Prehistoric activity has been identified within a Bronze Age or Iron Age 
soil horizon to the south of the Site and to the east in excavations along the 
A13. The study concluded there was low to moderate potential for Roman 
and medieval activity in the area.
1.1.8 The Site lay within marshland until reclaimation commenced in the post 
medieval period. The reclaimed land was used for agricultural purposes until 
the 19th
 century when the development of the docks and railways led to 
extensive building in the area. By 1868 streets had been laid out and by 1896 
the Site was occupied by terrace housing (PreConstruct Archaeology 
2003a).
1.1.9 An archaeological evaluation (PreConstruct Archaeology Ltd 2003b) 
comprising two trenches (Figure 2) revealed potentially significant 
archaeological activity on the Site. Two ditches interpreted as Roman 
drainage ditches were recorded in the northern of the two trenches and a wide 
shallow channel, possibly a natural feature, and the remains of an unurned 
cremation burial of an adult human were recorded in the southerly trench. 
The unurned cremation burial could not be properly dated due to a lack of 
artefactual remains. The nature of the feature however, was indicative of 
being either prehistoric or Roman in date.
1.1.10 Sealing these features was a thick layer of alluvial material indicative of 
widespread flooding in the postRoman period (PreConstruct Archaeology 
2003).
3 METHODOLOGY
3.1 Excavation Strategy
1.1.11 The excavation was carried out between the 5th
 and 8th
 April 2004 to coincide 
with the school Easter break.
1.1.12 Topsoil, modern overburden and the thick layer of alluvium mentioned in 
2.1.4 above was removed using a mechanical excavator under constant 
archaeological supervision. Subsequent excavation of exposed archaeological 
features and deposits was undertaken by hand.
2
1.1.13 Machine excavated spoil was visually examined for archaeological material.
3.2 Fieldwork Recording
1.1.14 All archaeological deposits and features were recorded using the Wessex 
Archaeology pro forma recording system.
1.1.15 A complete drawn record of archaeological features and deposits was 
compiled. This includes sections and plans, drawn to an appropriate scale. 
The Site and associated archaeological features were tied to the Ordnance 
Survey National Grid. Ordnance Datum (OD) heights of all features and 
layers were established.
1.1.16 A full photographic record was maintained using both colour transparencies 
and black and white negatives (on 35mm film).
1.1.17 A Museum of London code of BKP 04, was issued for the Site.
3.3 Health and Safety
1.1.18 All work was carried out in accordance with the Health and Safety at Work 
etc. Act 1974 and the Management of Health and Safety regulations 1992 
and all other relevant Health and Safety legislation and regulations and codes 
of practice in force at the time.
1.1.19 Prior to the commencement of the fieldwork a Risk Assessment was 
produced. All site staff involved in works signed and complied with this 
document. 
3
4 RESULTS
1.1.20 Beneath modern deposits (301303) comprising dumps of building material, 
concrete foundations and levelling deposits was layer (305) which was a 
thick greyish brown clay layer characteristic of alluvium. The layer, of 
average depth 0.5m, extended across the Site. <Node id="10324"/>No artefacts were retrieved 
from this deposit<Node id="10370"/>.
1.1.21 The upper part of this alluvial layer (304) had been affected by 
contamination and compaction from the overlying modern activity.
1.1.22 Archaeological features were found beneath the alluvial layer.
1.1.23 Two irregular, wide (3.56m) and shallow (0.19m deep) channels [311 and 
309] (Figure 3), orientated west­north east and south east­north west 
respectively, intersected towards the centre of the Site. Alluvial clay deposits 
(312) and (310) filled these channels. Two pieces of worked flint, a core 
fragment and a retouched flake, were recovered from (312) however, neither 
could be dated more closely than within the prehistoric period.
1.1.24 A third feature [306] was present in the southwest corner of the excavation 
area and appeared to be another shallow natural channel however, its full 
extent could not be assessed as the feature was only partially exposed within 
the excavation area. <Node id="11286"/>No artefacts were found in the alluvial clay<Node id="11330"/> f (307). 
1.1.25 In the north west corner of the excavation a north eastsouth west linear ditch 
[313] (Figure 3) with moderate to steep stepped sides and a flat base was 
found. The ditch contained two fills. The lower f (315) was an 
homogenous greyish blue sandy silt with very rare charcoal flecking. The 
upper f (314) was a midlight brown stiff alluvial clay. As with the other 
f deposits at the Site the upper interface with overlying alluvial clay layer 
(305) was very diffuse. One postmedieval pottery sherd (coarse redware) 
and several small bone fragments were retrieved from the centre of the ditch 
fill.
1.1.26 All features cut into the natural brickearth (308) which was encountered at a 
height of around 0.74m above Ordnance Datum.
4
5 FINDS
1.1.27 As described above, the finds from the Site comprised two pieces of worked 
flint, a core fragment and a retouched flake from f (312) which were 
datable only to the prehistoric period, and one postmedieval pottery sherd 
(coarse redware) and 3 joining fragments of large mammal longbone from 
f (314).
1.1.28 The material recovered during the evaluation of the Site (PreConstruct 
Archaeology 2003) was reexamined for this report.
1.1.29 The 130g of cremated bone represents the remains of a single adult. The 
surviving bone is well oxidised, and not much trabecular bone survives (due 
to soil acidity). The accompanying bag of residue appears to contain quite a 
lot of charcoal, as well as more bone.
1.1.30 The report and records from the evaluation give insufficient detail on the 
deposit containing the cremated bone, and it appears that the contents of this 
relatively large feature (0.40m diameter, 0.20m deep) were excavated as a 
single block. The nature of its excavation mean<Node id="13091"/> that there is no way of 
determining whether the remains represent those of an unurned buria<Node id="13184"/>l with 
redeposited pyre debris, or a deposit of pyre debris. This circumstance limits 
the usefulness of the deposit in understanding the Site. 
6 DISCUSSION
1.1.31 The shallow and irregular nature of the wide channels [311 and 309] 
supports the conclusion of the earlier evaluation results that these features are 
likely to be natural channels within a marshland environment. The 
intersection of these two features was investigated during the evaluation and 
no evidence of phasing was found. It is probable that the both features are 
contemporary. The two flint artefacts recovered from the f of [311] is 
insufficient evidence to prove that these features are the result of human 
activities. 
1.1.32 Finds recovered from the ditch [313] in the western corner of the excavation 
suggest that it is postmedieval in origin. This feature may represent a 
continuation of one of the ditches found in the northerly evaluation trench as 
the profiles, fills and alignments of both features are similar. If this is the 
case the tentative interpretation of the feature in the evaluation trench as 
being of Roman date is likely to be erroneous. 
1.1.33 The 0.50.7m layer of alluvium located in the evaluation trenches was found 
to be consistent across the whole of the excavation area as layers (304 and 
305). No evidence was found to contradict the evaluation conclusion that this 
5
layer was the result of flooding however the history of the area and finds 
recovered from feature [313] show the flooding event to have occurred 
during the postmedieval period.
7 CONCLUSION 
1.1.34 Four features were found during the excavation. Three of these appear to be 
natural marshland channels and the fourth a drainage ditch indicative of post
medieval efforts to drain the area for agriculture purposes.
1.1.35 The postmedieval activity in the area appears to have been curtailed by an 
episode of flooding which is represented by a thick layer of alluvium that 
overlies all features. 
1.1.36 The results of both the excavation and evaluation suggest that no further 
significant activities occurred in the area until its residential development in 
the 19th
 century. 
1.1.37 <Node id="15362"/>No further evidence for any prehistoric/Roman cremation burials was found 
during the excavation<Node id="15458"/>. If further burials do exist then they are likely to be 
located beyond the southeast boundary of the Site.
8 PROPOSALS FOR FURTHER ANALYSIS AND PUBLICATION
1.1.38 It is proposed that the cremation burial found during the evaluation works be 
further assessed. This would comprise extracting the remaining bone 
fragments from the residue, record the bone to archive level and submit 
appropriate samples for radiocarbon dating. 
1.1.39 It is recommended that a summary report of the project be submitted for 
publication in The London Archaeologist.
9 ARCHIVE
1.1.40 The project archive w be held at the offices of Wessex Archaeology at Old 
Sarum, Salisbury, Wiltshire. In due course the archive w be deposited with 
the Museum of London and stored under the site code BKP 04. 
6
10 OASIS 
1.1.41 An Online Access to the Index of Archaeological Investigations (OASIS) 
form has been completed in accordance with the GLAAS policy on 
improving access to information on PPG16 related fieldwork, and a hard 
copy is included in this report as Appendix 2. 
11 BIBLIOGRAPHY
PreConstruct 
Archaeology Ltd
2003a An Archaeological Desktop Assessment of Land 
at Cumberland School, Alexandra Street, 
London Borough of Newham. Unpublished
PreConstruct 
Archaeology Ltd
2003b An Archaeological Evaluation at Cumberland 
School, Alexandra Street, London Borough of 
Newham. Unpublished
Wessex 
Archaeology
2004 Cumberland School Sports Hall, Barking Road, 
Written Scheme of Investigation for 
Archaeological Excavation. Unpublished
7
APPENDIX 1: CONTEXT DESCRIPTIONS
Excavation 
Trench
Max depth: 1.34m Length: 18m Width: 12m
Contex
t No.
Type: Description: Depth:
301 Layer Topsoil/Turf Line A middark brown clayey 
loam with sparse inclusions
0­0.1m
302 Layer A deposit of light brown clayey loam with 
common rounded gravel inclusions
0.10.25m
303 Layer Made ground comprising rubble, brickwork and 
asphalt
0.250.5m
304 Layer Contaminated Alluvium, mid brown stiff clay. 
Upper part of alluvial episode relating to 305 
representing postdepositional interaction with 
overlying make up deposit. Lower interface very 
diffuse
305 Layer Greyish brown stiff clay. Occasional semifine 
roots spreads of very fine charcoal flecks 
forming a layer of alluvial clays deposited in a 
marsh environment.
0.71.2m
306 Cut Cut of shallow channel. Only present in the SW 
corner of the trench, full extent and profile 
unknown
1.21.35m
307 F Midlight brown stiff clay alluvial f of channel 
[306]. Occasional spreads of very fine charcoal 
flecks. Vertical Fe staining. Very diffuse 
interface with overlying deposit (305). No 
artefacts retrieved
1.21.35m
308 Natur
al
Light creamy yellow, soft spongy brickearth. 
Very homogenous deposit containing moderate 
orange brown mineralisations which increase in 
density with depth
1.2m+
309 Cut SENW irregular curvilinear shallow channel
310 F Midlight brown stiff clay alluvial f of channel 
[309]. Occasional spreads of very fine charcoal 
flecks. Vertical Fe staining. Very diffuse 
interface with overlying deposit (305). No 
artefacts retrieved
311 Cut WNE irregular curvilinear shallow channel
312 F Midlight brown stiff clay alluvial f of channel 
[311]. Occasional spreads of very fine charcoal 
flecks and sparse semifine roots. Vertical Fe 
staining. Very diffuse interface with overlying 
deposit (305). One worked flint flake retrieved 
during initial machining.
8
313 Cut NESW linear ditch. Moderatesteep sides with 
square flat base. 
314 F Upper midlight brown stiff clay alluvial f of 
channel [313]. Occasional spreads of very fine 
charcoal flecks and sparse semifine roots. 
Vertical Fe staining. Very diffuse interface with 
overlying deposit (305). One pottery sherd and 
several small bone fragments retrieved from the 
centre of the deposit.
315 F Basal f of [313]. A greyish blue sandy silt with 
very rare charcoal flecks.
9
APPENDIX 2: OASIS FORM
10
<Node id="19365"/></TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="key">
<Annotation Id="1" Type="Negation" StartNode="4115" EndNode="4188">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="4" Type="Negation" StartNode="10324" EndNode="10370">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="5" Type="Negation" StartNode="13091" EndNode="13184">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="6" Type="Negation" StartNode="15362" EndNode="15458">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="7" Type="Negation" StartNode="11286" EndNode="11330">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="0" Type="paragraph" StartNode="0" EndNode="19365">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
